<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<!--********************************************************************
Copyright 2021 Aaron Wong
*********************************************************************-->

<frontmatter xml:id="frontmatter" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">

    <titlepage>

        <author>
            <personname>Aaron Wong</personname>
            <department>Department of Data, Media, and Design</department>
            <institution>Nevada State University</institution>
            <email>aaron.wong@nevadastate.edu</email>
        </author>

        <date><today /></date>

    </titlepage>
    
    <colophon xml:id="front-colophon">

        <edition>Spring 2023</edition>

        <website>
            <url href="http://www.nsc.edu/FoundationsTextbook">Foundations Textbook</url>
        </website>

        <copyright>
            <year>2020<ndash />2024</year>
            <holder>Aaron Wong</holder>
            <minilicense>Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0</minilicense>
            <shortlicense>
                Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0
                <ul>
                    <li>
                        <p>
                            Attribution: You must give appropriate credit, provide a link to the license, and indicate
                            if changes were made.
                        </p>
                    </li>
                    <li>
                        <p>
                            Noncommercial: You may not use the material for commercial purposes.
                        </p>
                    </li>
                    <li>
                        <p>
                            ShareAlike: If you mix, transform, or build upon the material, you must distribute your
                            contributions under the same license as the original.
                        </p>
                    </li>
                </ul>
            </shortlicense>
        </copyright>
    </colophon>

    <preface xml:id="preface">
        <paragraphs xml:id="preface-why">
            <title>Underlying Philosophy</title>
            <p>
                Why write this book? That's a question that I needed to have a clear answer to before I began the
                process. The short answer is that I felt like I had little choice. Here is our reality:
                <ul>
                    <li>
                        <p>
                            Nevada is historically among the lowest-ranked states for K-12 math education in the nation.
                        </p>
                    </li>
                    <li>
                        <p>
                            The Nevada System of Higher Education passed a policy that completely eliminates any
                            standalone math remediation for students, forcing us to adopt a full corequisite model.
                        </p>
                    </li>
                    <li>
                        <p>
                            We want students to be successful in our college level math courses while maintaining our
                            standards.
                        </p>
                    </li>
                    <li>
                        <p>
                            The materials that currently exist are insufficient for the task.
                        </p>
                    </li>
                </ul>
                And so by the necessity of the situation, we needed to come up with <em>something</em> to help our
                students.
            </p>

            <p>
                But the longer answer to the question is that this moment of disruption is also the right time to try to
                make a change in how remedial mathematics (including corequisite courses) are taught and understood.
                I've spent over a decade working with students with weak mathematical backgrounds. I've watched how they
                think and how they attempt to learn mathematical material. I've come to the conclusion that I think
                there are better ways to help students become successful.
            </p>

            <p>
                Of course, if we are talking about "success" then we need to define what that actually means. I will say
                that the traditional methods of remediation are pretty good at doing what they are designed to do. The
                primary emphasis of traditional remediation is to help students become proficient at specific algebraic
                manipulations. The entire structure of textbooks is based on that premise:
            </p>
            <p>
                <q>
                    Here is an example. Now try a problem exactly like that one. Now do that 50 more times (but only the
                    odd numbered problems so you can check your answer).
                </q>
            </p>
            <p>
                If all you want out of students is to get them to perform manipulations on command, this is a very good
                way of doing it.
            </p>
            <p>
                But as I think about the students I encounter, I don't think this is really that helpful. I question
                whether they actually remain proficient in those manipulations after the semester is over. After all,
                they've been through this before, perhaps even two or three times. Why is this time going to be
                different? I also question what they actually learned from the class, and I question the true value that
                the students get from courses like these. It all comes back down to a question that's at the core of
                education: What do we <em>really</em> want students to learn?
            </p>
            <p>
                If we only have one semester to teach students about mathematics, do we really want to teach them that 
                he core of mathematics is doing algebraic manipulations? Is that what math is? Is that what we actually
                care about? I understand that some people would agree that it is. They think the goal is to get students
                to be proficient at these particular algebraic manipulations so that they can execute those
                manipulations in their other courses (college algebra/precalculus, physics, chemistry, statistics). I
                don't think this is wrong, I just think it's short-sighted.
            </p>
            <p>
                <aside>
                    <p>
                        Here is a subset of topics that may appear in a high school Algebra 2 course: rationalizing the
                        denominator of radical expressions, complex numbers and the fundamental theorem of algebra,
                        exponentials, logarithms, matrices, synthetic division, logic, probability, infinite series...
                    </p>
                </aside>
                I believe that the core skill that students should get is not mathematical manipulations, but the
                development of mathematical reasoning. The emphasis of the K-12 system is still currently heavily
                invested in mathematical manipulations. If you look at most Algebra 2 textbooks, you'll find an
                incredibly broad range of topics that are covered. Most of these topics end up being manipulations
                piled on top of other manipulations.
            </p>
            <p>
                When I look at students in remedial courses, I make two primary observations about them. The first is
                that students are often very confused about mathematics. They operate from a very rule-based perspective
                and often feel as though the bulk of their work is memorizing manipulations and memorizing when they
                need to use them. The second, which follows from the first, is that they completely lack confidence in
                their mathematical abilities. This is a learned helplessness from all the times they tried to memorize
                something and failed. They have had many years to develop the "not a math person" identity where they do
                not embody any level of mathematical confidence and show few signs of mathematical reasoning. Many
                students simply guess at whether they are doing the right thing, then sit back and wait to be told
                whether it's right or wrong. And when you look at the educational system that they've come through, you
                can understand why this is.
            </p>
            <p>
                My goal with this book is to change how students think about mathematics. I would love to have two or
                three semesters of math courses to really bring students to a place of thinking about mathematics at a
                college level. But there is only so much that can be done in one semester, especially when that semester
                is contextualized as a support for a college level math course. And that's the reality. We simply need
                to do the best we can with the time that we have.
            </p>
        </paragraphs>

        <paragraphs xml:id="preface-target-audience">
            <title>Who is the Target Audience?</title>
            <p>
                This book is written for all college students who are interested in improving their mathematical
                foundation. This includes students that are either destined for a liberal arts or statistics college
                math course, and students on the STEM trajectory headed towards calculus. I also think this has value
                to anyone who is teaching or will teach math at any level (especially K-12). There is a lot of systemic
                brokenness in the math education system, and I will be glad if these ideas help to fix even a smallest
                part of that.
            </p>
        </paragraphs>

        <paragraphs xml:id="preface-book-goal">
            <title>The Goal of the Book</title>
            <p>
                So we return to the driving question: What do we <em>really</em> want students to learn? The answer that
                this book gives is that the goal is to get students to become better and more confident mathematical
                thinkers. They've spent enough time doing the lather-rinse-repeat of pure manipulations. They need to
                develop a different intellectual foundation. The good news is that we're not working from scratch.
                Because although students may struggle with certain types of algebraic manipulations, it's rare that all
                the students need to relearn all of them. Those past experiences are our starting point.
            </p>
            <p>
                So instead of treating students as if they've never seen these manipulations before (which is how the
                majority of remedial coursework approaches topics), we're going to work with students as people who have
                experience but have not carefully reflected on those experiences. A lot of the manipulations that we ask
                of them are already somewhere in their heads, and we're simply working with them to connect those
                neurons to other neurons and strengthen that signal.
            </p>
            <aside>
                <p>
                    Instructors will likely be pleased by students having an organized framework for writing their
                    mathematics, even if the students are doing everything wrong. At least it's legible!
                </p>
            </aside>
            <p>
                This begins with the very first section. The emphasis is on mathematical communication. This is already
                a significant divergence from most other approaches, where the goal is to get the right answer. The
                majority of students don't even have a basic framework for understanding mathematical communication. We
                lay out simple but clear expectations for how to begin to organize their mathematical writing, and that
                foundation is the tool that we use to help students reorganize the information in their heads. Once we
                can get them to write their work in an organized manner, it becomes easier to begin to isolate specific
                struggles that students are having, and they can even begin to start to recognize them for themselves.
            </p>
            <p>
                Every section that follows treats students as adults who already have mathematical experiences. We do
                not treat the students as kids who need to have to be told exactly what to do all the time. In fact, we
                emphasize throughout the book that mathematics is not about following rules, but about being able to
                think through situations and understanding what they're doing and why they're doing it. You will find
                that some of the "Try It" problems do not have an example that models the exact thing they need to do.
                Those examples often become a crutch for students as they realize that they don't actually need to think
                for themselves, and simply have to hunt down the right example to show them exactly what to do. You will
                see this philosophy expressed in the worksheets as well, as many of them will touch topics that were not
                directly discussed in the text.
            </p>
            <p>
                We have done this specifically because we want students to learn to think for themselves. The goal is
                not just that students will learn the idea, but that they will begin to develop metacognitive strategies
                for how they approach new mathematical ideas. This is a much broader foundation that they are more
                likely to carry forward with them into their future classes. If you just teach the manipulations, then
                it's going to be hit-or-miss whether they will remember those manipulations when they need them in the
                future. But if you give them the tools to think about the mathematics effectively (and the confidence to
                trust their thinking), they will be far more able to reconstruct the ideas behind the manipulations if
                they've forgotten them. It simply puts them in a much better position for long-term success.
            </p>
        </paragraphs>

        <paragraphs xml:id="preface-book-structure">
            <title>The Structure of the Book</title>
            <aside>
                <p>
                    The whole book can be used as a self-study book if one is independently motivated. But most students
                    will need to transition into it.
                </p>
            </aside>
            <p>
                One of the features of this book to help students accomplish the goal is that only part of the book is
                intended to be "taught" in the classroom. Self-efficacy comes with the practice of being
                self-efficacious. This was an intentional decision based on the use of this material as part of a
                corequisite math course. As much as we can want to aim for deeper learning outcomes, we still need to
                confront the practical reality of our students' struggles with mathematics.
            </p>
            <aside>
                <p>
                    We view the content like a tree. After covering the main trunk, the branches can be done as distinct
                    topics.
                </p>
                <image xml:id="book-structure-tree" width="60%">
                    <description>The book is structured like a tree.</description>
                    <latex-image>
                        \begin{tikzpicture}
                            \draw (0,0) node[rotate=90,anchor=west] {Main Trunk};
                            \draw (-0.2,1.5) node[rotate=-45,anchor=east] {Branch 1};
                            \draw (-0.2,0.75) node[rotate=-45,anchor=east] {Branch 2};
                            \draw (0.2,1.5) node[rotate=45,anchor=west] {Branch 3};
                            \draw (0.2,0.75) node[rotate=45,anchor=west] {Branch 4};
                        \end{tikzpicture}
                    </latex-image>
                </image>
            </aside>
            <p>
                The book is broken into five sections:
                <ul>
                    <li>The Main Trunk: Core algebra (Sections 1-11)</li>
                    <li>Branch 1: Linear equations and the coordinate plane (Sections 12-16)</li>
                    <li>Branch 2: Fractions and decimals (Sections 17-23)</li>
                    <li>Branch 3: A review of arithmetic (Sections 24-32)</li>
                    <li>Branch 4: A few applications (Sections 33-36)</li>
                </ul>
            </p>
            <aside>
                <p>
                    Sections 8 and 9 (factoring quadratic polynomials) can be skipped without loss of continuity if
                    these skills are deemed unnecessary for the students.
                </p>
            </aside>
            <p>
                The main trunk is the set of core algebra that we think are absolutely critical before launching into
                any college level mathematics. We spend the first two weeks of the semester covering these sections.
                They are meant to be reminders of things students have already learned, not a complete reteaching of
                the content from scratch.
            </p>
            <aside>
                <p>
                    The presentation framework is to line up the equal signs vertically and use the space to the right
                    to explain or justify the steps. And we really do make students do this!
                </p>
            </aside>
            <p>
                The most important section is the first one, where we introduce the idea of mathematical communication.
                In that section, we provide students a framework that we expect them to follow. The idea is to slow them
                down and get them to think about the algebraic manipulations, and to otherwise disrupt the bad habits
                they've developed. Without this shift, it's significantly more difficult for students to make the
                necessary changes.
            </p>
            <aside>
                <p>
                    Yes, we also expect students to <em>read</em> the words in the textbook!
                </p>
            </aside>
            <p>
                Beyond the main trunk, the students are expected to work on the sections more or less on their own. We
                do have times of in-class activities that will include demonstrating that they've worked through these
                sections, but we generally do not intend for our instructors to directly teach out of the book after
                completing the main trunk. The textbook is written in a conversational tone that students should be able
                to read and understand.
            </p>
            <aside>
                <p>
                    We win when we get this reaction from students: "Oh! Now I understand why we do it this way!"
                </p>
            </aside>
            <p>
                Rather than being a few big, complex ideas, it's really more a collection of a lot of little ideas to
                help math "make sense" to students. The instructors are expected to be available to help students if
                they get stuck on topics, but we are generally confident in the students' ability to mostly work things
                out on their own. 
            </p>
            <p>
                The emphasis of the branches is not about getting students to execute technical manipulations. It's
                about getting them to start to think and interact differently with mathematical concepts. Remember that
                the goal is to have increased mathematical thinking and mathematical confidence, not growing their
                catalog of algebraic manipulations. So while we do also review manipulations (especially see
                <xref ref="sec-fb-5-deeper" />), the context and presentation lend themselves more towards
                thinking accurately about these mathematical ideas and not treating them as a series of rule-based
                manipulations.
            </p>
            <p>
                This perspective is the opposite of how many math textbooks are written. Most of the time, there is a
                core thread of content and the branches point outward to bigger ideas and more distant horizons. For
                this book, the branches point inward to the main trunk. Rather than using the main trunk as a launching
                point for new ideas, it is the home base that we return to over and over again. And this is how we
                achieve the depth of mathematical thinking.
            </p>
            <aside>
                <p>
                    The college level math course is where students will face new ideas!
                </p>
            </aside>
            <p>
                Simply put, for a support course like this we would rather that students make the mental effort to
                connect the dots of ideas that already exist in their heads instead of asking them to pursue new topics.
            </p>
        </paragraphs>

        <paragraphs xml:id="preface-section-structure">
            <title>The Structure of Each Section</title>
            <p>
                The core structure of each section is the following:
                <ul>
                    <li>
                        <em>Learning Objectives:</em> Each section has 1 to 4 learning objectives. This gives a brief
                        summary of the core concepts in the section.
                    </li>
                    <li>
                        <em>Main Content with Examples:</em> Students are expected to read the text and complete the
                        "Try It" examples. If students are reading the text, they should be able to do these problems.
                        And if they can't do these problems, that's a signal to them that they need to contact the
                        instructor (or campus tutoring services, if available) to get help. The solutions to these
                        examples are provided in the text.
                    </li>
                    <li>
                        <em>Worksheets:</em> The worksheets are extra problems that are sometimes similar to the "Try
                        It" examples, but they also sometimes diverge into a deeper look at familiar ideas. Those
                        problems are where students are being asked to think mathematically. Given what they know, can
                        they push deeper and make a new connection? We encourage students to approach these as group
                        explorations because the act of talking through ideas (communication) is important to the
                        primary learning outcomes. The worksheets are intentionally short to allow for these types of
                        conversations to happen relatively quickly, rather than having them first do dozens of rote
                        exercises before sharing their ideas with each other.
                    </li>
                    <li>
                        <em>Deliberate Practice:</em> Most sections will have a short collection of exercises to allow
                        students a bit of additional practice. This is called "deliberate practice" because students are
                        given a number of ideas to focus on while they do these problems. These are supplements to
                        provide students with further opportunities to practice the skills that they've developed
                        (thinking, presenting, explaining, and executing) by doing standard manipulations. If you are
                        looking to just dump a bunch of problems on students, you're much better off using a different
                        textbook. These sections are intentionally kept short to discourage instructors from just
                        assigning students to do rote exercises.
                    </li>
                    <li>
                        <em>Closing Ideas:</em> Each section has a brief discussion that summarizes the ideas that are
                        found in the section and the worksheets. The purpose of this is to redirect the focus towards
                        the horizon. As students work their way through each section, it's easy to get fully absorbed
                        in executing the calculations and lose track of how this fits into the bigger picture.
                    </li>
                    <li>
                        <em>Going Deeper:</em> Many sections will have an additional topic that pushes students deeper.
                        These sections exist to better illuminate the ways that the ideas from the section link to
                        higher levels of mathematics and other applications of the ideas in each section. These
                        additional topics can all be skipped without losing any of the core content of the book, but
                        some instructors may find some of the topics to be helpful for use in just-in-time remediation.
                        For example, there is a series of sections that focus on manipulating rational expressions that
                        a precalculus course may want to cover. Other sections are there simply as fodder for discussion
                        and to broaden students' mathematical perspective.
                    </li>
                </ul>
            </p>
        </paragraphs>

        <paragraphs xml:id="preface-precalculus-alignment">
            <title>Alignment with Precalculus Courses</title>
            <p>
                This textbook was organized with precalculus in mind. While precalculus textbooks vary somewhat, they
                mostly fit the same basic pattern. This means that this textbook should work well with most standard
                first semester precalculus courses. We wanted to create a rough alignment between this material and the
                basic structure those courses. Specifically, there were three major touch points that we wanted to have:
                <ul>
                    <li>
                        <p>
                            Discuss the coordinate plane and graphing lines around the same time students are studying
                            the general properties of functions.
                        </p>
                    </li>
                    <li>
                        <p>
                            Discuss of fractions before introducing of rational functions to remind students of the
                            underlying manipulations before they need it.
                        </p>
                    </li>
                    <li>
                        <p>
                            Discuss scientific notation around the time as logarithmic functions to create the
                            opportunity to connect the two ideas.
                        </p>
                    </li>
                </ul>
            </p>
            <p>
                The suggested course alignment below is based on having extra contact time with students for the
                corequisite content, which allows for the extra time up front to set the stage with the Main Branch of
                this book. (I don't know how you would try to teach both the support material and the core content
                without extra contact time!) It's possible to use this material without it, but students may not adopt
                the mindset and writing habits if those sections are not treated as the primary learning outcomes. After
                the Main Branch, very little in-class time is spent directly teaching the Foundations content. Students
                are expected to read the book, and only a small portion of the class time is dedicated to completing the
                worksheets and discussing the ideas directly. 
                <table>
                    <title>Precalculus Alignment</title>
                    <tabular>
                        <row>
                      <cell width="1">Weeks</cell>
                      <cell>Foundations Textbook</cell>
                      <cell>Precalculus Content</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                      <cell>1-2</cell>
                      <cell>
                        <line>Main Trunk</line>
                        <line>(Core Algebra)</line>
                      </cell>
                      <cell></cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                      <cell>3-5</cell>
                      <cell>
                        <line>Branch 1</line>
                        <line>(Linear Equations/Coordinate Plane)</line>
                      </cell>
                      <cell>Introduction to Functions</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                      <cell>6-10</cell>
                      <cell>
                        <line>Branch 2</line>
                        <line>(Fractions/Decimals)</line>
                      </cell>
                      <cell>Polynomials and Rational Functions</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                      <cell>11-15</cell>
                      <cell>
                        <line>Branches 3-4</line>
                        <line>(Arithmetic/Applications)</line>
                      </cell>
                      <cell>Logarithmic Functions</cell>
                        </row>
                    </tabular>
                </table>
            </p>
        </paragraphs>

        <paragraphs xml:id="sec-other-alignment">
            <title>Alignment with Other Courses</title>
            <p>
                Although the organization of this textbook is not built around other first semester courses (such as a
                quantitative literacy course or a "liberal arts" math course), the content of the course is perhaps even
                more valuable to those students and those classes. Those students are actually the ones I have had the
                most experience teaching. However, those courses tend to be quite varied in their structure, and so it
                would be impossible to align this text with that. While the branches are set up in a specific and
                intended order, it's the ideas are sufficiently self-contained that they can be rearranged without much
                harm to the overall delivery of the material. 
            </p>
        </paragraphs>

        <paragraphs xml:id="sec-errors-suggestions">
            <title>Errors? Suggestions?</title>
            
            <p>
                As with most things, this is a work in progress. If you find any errors in the textbook, please email me
                to let me know. Also, if you have suggestions for additional topics or alternative approaches, I'm
                always open to new ideas. The best way to contact me is through email
                (<email>aaron.wong@nsc.edu</email>).
            </p>
        </paragraphs>

    </preface>


</frontmatter>
