<section xml:id="sec-fqp-5-deeper">
	<title>Going Deeper: Special Factorizations</title>

	<p>
		There are certain factoring patterns that are useful to learn to recognize. It's not that you would be unable to
		factor these without recognizing them, but they come up so frequently that they have special names so that we
		can identify them when they happen: 
	</p>
	<image xml:id="sec-fqp-5-factorizations" width="80%">
		<latex-image>
			\begin{tikzpicture}
				\draw (0,0) node[anchor=north] {
						\begin{tabular}{ll}
							Square of a binomial sum: \amp $a^2 + 2ab + b^2 = (a + b)^2$ \\
							Square of a binomial difference: \amp $a^2 - 2ab + b^2 = (a - b)^2$ \\
							Difference of squares: \amp $a^2 - b^2 = (a + b)(a - b)$
						\end{tabular}
				};
			\end{tikzpicture} 
		</latex-image>
	</image>
	<p>
		The basic idea of using these patterns to factor is that you need to match your expression with one of the above
		formulas and identify the appropriate values of <m>a</m> and <m>b</m>. For example, suppose you want to factor
		<m>x^2 + 6x + 9</m> and you want to check whether this fits one of the patterns above. By counting the number of
		terms and looking at the signs, we can see that there's only one formula that has a chance.
	</p>
	<image xml:id="sec-fqp-5-special-factorizations" width="100%">
		<latex-image>
			\begin{tikzpicture}[scale=1.2]
				\draw (0,0.5) node[anchor=north] {Square of a binomial sum}; 
				\draw (0,0) node[anchor=north] {
					$\begin{array} {ccccc}
						a^2 \amp + \amp 2ab \amp + \amp b^2 \\
						\updownarrow \amp \updownarrow \amp \updownarrow \amp \updownarrow \amp \updownarrow \\
						x^2 \amp + \amp 6x \amp + \amp 9 \\
					\end{array} $}; 
				\draw (5,0.5) node[anchor=north] {Square of a binomial difference}; 
				\draw (5,0) node[anchor=north] {
					$\begin{array} {ccccc}
						a^2 \amp - \amp 2ab \amp + \amp b^2 \\
						\updownarrow \amp \times \amp \updownarrow \amp \updownarrow \amp \updownarrow \\
						x^2 \amp + \amp 6x \amp + \amp 9 \\
					\end{array} $}; 
				\draw (10,0.5) node[anchor=north] {Difference of Squares}; 
				\draw (10,0) node[anchor=north] {
					$\begin{array} {ccccc}
						a^2 \amp \amp - \amp \amp b^2 \\
						\updownarrow \amp \times \amp \times \amp \times \amp \updownarrow \\
						x^2 \amp + \amp 6x \amp + \amp 9 \\
					\end{array} $}; 
			\end{tikzpicture} 
		</latex-image>
	</image>
	<p>
		Once we know that we should be focusing on the square of a binomial sum, we can try to identify the <m>a</m> and
		the <m>b</m> by looking at the terms on the end and then check to see if the term in the middle matches. We can
		see that we can take <m>a = x</m> and <m>b = 3</m>, which means that the middle term should be <m>2ab = 6x</m>.
		And this all matches perfectly.
		<me>
			x^2 + 6x + 9 = x^2 + 2 \cdot x \cdot 3 + 3^2 = (x + 3)^2
		</me> 
	</p>
	<p>
		The nice part about these formulas is that it gives us insights into other factorizations that we may not
		immediately see using the method. Here's an example:
		<me>
			x^2 + 2 \sqrt{2} x + 2 = x^2 + 2 \cdot x \cdot \sqrt{2} + ( \sqrt{2})^2 = (x + \sqrt{2})^2
		</me>
		It's not that the method can't be applied here. Here's how it would look.
		<me>
			x^2 + 2 \sqrt{2} x + 2 \longrightarrow \left\{
				\begin{array}{l}
					\text{Multiply to $2\sqrt{2}$} \\
					\text{Add to $2$}
				\end{array} \right.
		</me>
		It's technically true that <m>\sqrt{2} + \sqrt{2} = 2 \sqrt{2}</m> and <m>\sqrt{2} \cdot \sqrt{2} = 2</m>, and
		we would be able to do the factorization by grouping: 
		<me>
			\begin{aligned}
				x^2 + 2 \sqrt{2} x + 2 \amp = x^2 + \sqrt{2} x + \sqrt{2} x + 2 \amp \eqnspacer \amp \text{The $ac$ method} \\
				\amp = x(x + \sqrt{2}) + \sqrt{2} (x + \sqrt{2}) \amp \amp \text{Factor by grouping} \\
				\amp = (x + \sqrt{2})(x + \sqrt{2}) \amp \amp \text{Factor out the common factor} 
			\end{aligned}
		</me>
		But we can see from this that the <m>ac</m> method is really designed for thinking through integer
		factorizations. Recognizing the factorization with square roots is just not something we should expect students
		at this level to do. 
	</p>
	<p>
		The reason we use these special factorizations is because they are a special pattern that we can learn to
		recognize with practice. And that's pretty much all this is. By learning to recognize these patterns, you have
		access to a larger collection of factorizations that you might otherwise miss. Here are some examples: 
	</p>
	<aside>
		<p>
			You should check these factorizations by working out the products. 
		</p>
	</aside>
	<image xml:id="sec-fqp-5-factorization-examples" width="90%">
		<latex-image>
			\begin{tikzpicture}[scale=1.1]
				\draw (0,0.5) node[anchor=north] {Square of a binomial sum};
				\draw (0,0) node[anchor=north] {\renewcommand{\arraystretch}{1.5}
					$\begin{array}{lcl}
						x^2 + 6x + 9 \amp = \amp (x + 3)^2 \\
						x^2 + 2xy + y^2 \amp = \amp (x + y)^2 \\
						x^4 + 10x^2 + 25 \amp = \amp (x^2 + 5)^2 \\
					\end{array}$};
				\draw (7,0.5) node[anchor=north] {Square of a binomial difference};
				\draw (7,0) node[anchor=north] {\renewcommand{\arraystretch}{1.5}
					$\begin{array}{lcl}
						x^2 - 12x + 36 \amp = \amp (x - 6)^2 \\
						x^2 - 4xy + 4y^2 \amp = \amp (x - 2y)^2 \\
						x^6 - 2x^3y^2 + y^4 \amp = \amp (x^3 - y^2)^2 \\
					\end{array}$};
				\draw (3.5,-2.5) node[anchor=north] {Difference of squares};
				\draw (3.5,-3) node[anchor=north] {\renewcommand{\arraystretch}{1.5}
					$\begin{array}{lcl}
						x^2 - 49 \amp = \amp (x + 7)(x - 7) \\
						4x^2 - 9y^2 \amp = \amp (2x + 3y)(2x - 3y) \\
						x^2 - 2 \amp = \amp (x + \sqrt{2})(x - \sqrt{2}) \\
					\end{array}$};
			\end{tikzpicture}
		</latex-image>
	</image>	
	<aside>
		<p>
			Freshmen dream is that this is true because it would keep them from losing so many points! 
		</p>
	</aside>
	<p>
		Another aspect of these formulas is that your awareness of them can help you to avoid a few very specific
		algebraic errors. If you are familiar with the formulas for the square of a binomial sum and difference, you
		would immediately recognize what these expressions should be. These are errors that are so common that one of
		them has been given the nickname of "the freshman's dream." 
	</p>
	<image xml:id="sec-fqp-5-bad-factorizations" width="80%">
		<latex-image>
			\begin{tikzpicture}
				\draw (0,0) node[anchor=north] {\renewcommand{\arraystretch}{1.5}
					$\begin{array}{rclcrcl}
						(a+b)^2 \amp \overset{\times}{=} \amp a^2 + b^2 \amp \text{\textcolor{white}{.}} \hspace{2cm}
						\text{\textcolor{white}{.}} \amp (a-b)^2 \amp \overset{\times}{=} \amp a^2 - b^2
					\end{array} $}; 
			\end{tikzpicture} 
		</latex-image>
	</image>
	<aside>
		<p>
			This logic works for anything of the form <m>x^2 + y^2</m>. 
		</p>
	</aside>
	<p>
		You might have noticed that that there's a formula for the square of a binomial sum and difference, but only a
		formula for the difference of squares and not a sum of squares. It turns out that the sum of squares cannot be
		factored using the tools that we have developed so far. We can use logic to prove that we can't do this. Let's
		try to factor <m>x^2 + 9</m> as an example. Using the method, we have to find values that do the following:
		<me>
			x^2 + 9 \longrightarrow \left\{
				\begin{array}{l}
					\text{Multiply to $9$} \\
					\text{Add to $0$}
				\end{array} \right.
		</me>
		In order to get two numbers to multiply to a positive number, they must either both be positive or both be
		negative. But if they are both positive or both negative, then when you add them together, you can't get zero
		because both numbers have the same sign. And so there aren't any numbers that will do this for us. 
	</p>
	<aside>
		<p>
			At least, none of the real numbers would work. But that hasn't stopped mathematicians from imagining new
			types of numbers that could do this. (Pun intended.) 
		</p>
	</aside>
	<p>
		The special factorization formulas don't stop there. Factorization is such an important concept in mathematics
		that there are all sorts of factorizations that can be helpful at various times and various situations. Here are
		a few examples, all of which you can check by multiplying everything out: 
		<ul>
			<li>
				<p>
					The sum of cubes: <m>a^3 + b^3 = (a + b)(a^2 - ab + b^2)</m> 
				</p>
			</li>
			<li>
				<p>
					The difference of cubes: <m>a^3 - b^3 = (a - b)(a^2 + ab + b^2)</m> 
				</p>
			</li>
			<li>
				<p>
					The difference of fourth powers: <m>a^4 - b^4 = (a - b)(a^3 + a^2b + ab^2 + b^3)</m> 
				</p>
			</li>
			<li>
				<p>
					A "magic" formula: <m>x^2 + bx + c = \left( x - \left( - \frac{b}{2} + \sqrt{\frac{b^2}{4} - c} \right) \right) \left( x + \left( - \frac{b}{2} - \sqrt{\frac{b^2}{4} - c} \right) \right)</m> 
				</p>
			</li>
		</ul>
	</p>
	<aside>
		<p>
			Do you see the pattern in the difference of powers? 
		</p>
	</aside>
	<p>
		The last formula is not one that you're likely to find anywhere, but it may look similar to something you might
		remember from your past mathematical experiences. And it's actually related to an approach to factoring that was
		known by mathematicians over 3500 years ago that was introduced to the modern world by Dr. Po-Shen Loh in 2019.
	</p>
	<aside>
		<p>
			You can find several understandable explanations of this alternative factoring technique on the internet. 
		</p>
	</aside>
</section>
