<section xml:id="sec-mpd-4-closing">
	<title>Closing Ideas</title>
	<p>
		As mentioned before, most decimal multiplication is performed by calculators or computers. But computers are
		usually not able to perform percent calculations without a person correctly identifying the part, the whole, and
		the percent, and then determining what calculations are required to solve the problem. With the goal of
		mathematical thinking in mind, the problems in this section were set up so that calculators would not be needed. 
	</p>
	<p>
		But if you were run into a situation where you would need a calculator, as long you have the correct
		mathematical thinking then all you need to do is replace the mental calculation with a calculator calculation.
		There is no real loss (from the perspective of logic) in trading that out. Here is the light bulb problem again,
		but with slightly more realistic numbers: 
	</p>
	<p>
		 The last batch of 1500 light bulbs had 37 defects. What is the percent of defective bulbs? 
	</p>
	<p>
		<ul>
			<li>
				<p>
					The part: The number of defective bulbs is 37.
				</p>
			</li>
			<li>
				<p>
					The whole: The total number of bulbs in the batch is 1500.
				</p>
			</li>
			<li>
				<p>
					The percent: The percent of defective bulbs is unknown. 
				</p>
			</li>
		</ul>
		<me>
			\begin{aligned}
				(\text{the part}) \amp = (\text{the percent}) \cdot (\text{the whole}) \\
				37 \amp = x \cdot 1500 \\
				\frac{37}{1500} \amp = x \\
				x \amp \approx 0.02467 \\
				x \amp \approx 2.467\% \\
			\end{aligned}
		</me>
		 Answer: About 2.5% of the bulbs were defective. 
	</p>
	<aside>
		<p>
			This number came from a calculator.
		</p>
	</aside>
	<p>
		<idx><h>algebraic reasoning</h></idx>
		Notice that the overall process is unchanged, and it's just a matter of using different numbers. This is very
		similar to the process of learning to treat variables like numbers in other calculations, such as reducing
		fractions. In fact, the particular area of mathematical thinking, which is sometimes called <term>algebraic
		reasoning</term>, is the whole idea that you can generalize the methods and ideas of simple examples so that
		they can be applied in more complex situations. You got a hint of this type of reasoning in the last few
		problems where you had to do a mental manipulation before putting the numbers into the parts of a whole
		framework. And that is the skill that you should be aiming to develop in your college level courses. You want to
		be more than a calculator.
	</p>
</section>
