<section xml:id="sec-fm-5-deeper">
	<title>Going Deeper: Additional Factoring Techniques</title>

	<p>
		In <xref ref="sec-fqp-1-main" /> and <xref ref="sec-fqp-5-deeper" />, we looked at various factoring ideas and
		techniques. We're going to push that a little bit deeper here. Before getting started, we want to remind
		ourselves of the most common special factorizations patterns from that section: 
		<me>
			\begin{array}{ll}
				\text{Square of a binomial sum:} \amp a^2 + 2ab + b^2 = (a + b)^2 \\
				\text{Square of a binomial difference:} \amp a^2 - 2ab + b^2 = (a - b)^2 \\
				\text{Difference of squares:} \amp a^2 - b^2 = (a + b)(a - b) \\
				\text{Sum of cubes:} \amp a^3 + b^3 = (a + b)(a^2 - ab + b^2) \\
				\text{Difference of cubes:} \amp a^3 - b^3 = (a - b)(a^2 + ab + b^2)
			\end{array}
		</me>
	</p>
	<p>
		When working with these expressions, we noted how we can use these formulas to factor expressions even when the
		expressions contain multiple variables or higher powers of the variables. As long as the expression can be made
		to fit the form, then the factorization works. 
	</p>
	<aside>
		<p>
			It's the same as larger numbers having more factors than smaller numbers. 
		</p>
	</aside>
	<p>
		But there's something else that can happen with those more complicated expressions, which is that it may take
		multiple factorizations to factor it completely. In other words, after one factorization step, you may discover
		that the factors can be factored again. Here is an example: 
		<me>
			\begin{aligned}
				x^4 - 1 \amp = (x^2 + 1)(x^2 - 1) \amp \eqnspacer \amp \text{Difference of squares} \\
				\amp = (x^2 + 1)(x + 1)(x - 1) \amp \amp \text{Difference of squares} 
			\end{aligned}
		</me>
	</p>
	<p>
		Unfortunately, there is no indicator that you will need to continue to factor other than recognizing that you
		can continue to factor. However, as you gain experience, you will get better at recognizing when expressions can
		be factored and when they can't. 
	</p>
	<aside>
		<p>
			Some students find it easier to substitute <m>y = x^2</m> so that this becomes <m>y^2 + 4y - 5</m> before
			attempting to factor it. 
		</p>
	</aside>
	<p>
		<idx><h>quadratic in form</h></idx>
		It turns out that the <m>ac</m> method of factoring can also be extended to factor certain types of expressions.
		Expressions of this type are said to be <em>quadratic in form</em>, which means that we can treat them as a
		quadratic expression by thinking about them in the right way. Here is an example:
		<me>
			x^4 + 4x^2 - 5
		</me>
		This is not a quadratic expression, but it is quadratic in form. This means that if we think about it the right
		way, we can treat it like a quadratic expression. Specifically, we can rewrite it by treating <m>x^2</m> as the
		variable: 
		<me>
			\begin{aligned}
				x^4 + 4x^2 - 5 \amp = (x^2)^2 + 4(x^2) - 5 \amp \eqnspacer \amp \text{Rewrite as a quadratic} \\
				\amp = (x^2 + 5)(x^2 - 1) \amp \amp \text{$ac$ method} \\
				\amp = (x^2 + 5)(x + 1)(x - 1) \amp \amp \text{Difference of squares} 
			\end{aligned}
		</me>
	</p>
	<aside>
		<p>
			<idx><h>perfect square</h></idx>
			A <em>perfect square</em> is the square of an integer. 
		</p>
	</aside>
	<p>
		It would be nice if there were some fixed set of rules for when to factor expressions and when to leave them
		alone. Unfortunately, those decisions are often driven by context. The most common place this becomes an issue
		is with a difference of squares. For example, consider this quadratic expression:
		<me>
			x^2 - 3
		</me>
		On the one hand, we can look at this and say that is not a perfect square and just leave it in that form. On the
		other hand, while isn't a perfect square, it is the square of which means that we can still factor it. 
		<me>
			\begin{aligned}
				x^2 - 3 \amp = x^2 - (\sqrt{3})^2 \amp \eqnspacer \amp \text{Rewrite $3$ as a square} \\
				\amp = (x + \sqrt{3})(x - \sqrt{3}) \amp \amp \text{Difference of squares} 
			\end{aligned}
		</me>
	</p>
	<p>
		Does this mean that we should factor <m>x^2 - 3</m> using square roots? The answer is that it depends. The
		factorization into linear terms is helpful for some mathematical operations, but other times it's an unnecessary
		step. So the decision of whether to factor will be dependent upon the context. This is an idea that we've
		touched on many times before, which is that you don't want to think about math as a set of rules that you follow
		every single time. It is better to recognize that you have the option of taking that factorization one step
		further, but then to decide what you're going to do based on the specific goals for the problem. 
	</p>
	<aside>
		<p>
			Students usually learn a combination of the rational root theorem and either synthetic division or
			polynomial long division. 
		</p>
	</aside>
	<p>
		This may not be the last factoring technique that you'll encounter. In many precalculus courses, you will learn
		about other techniques that can be applied to help to sometimes factor higher degree polynomials that don't fit
		any of our current ideas. But even with that technique, you still will not be able to factor everything. In
		fact, one of the big questions that mathematicians had wondered about for a long time is whether there's a
		formula that can be used to factor everything. This question was ultimately answered in the early 1800s, when
		it was proven that there are fifth degree equations that have roots that are "impossible" write down.
	</p>
	<aside>
		<p>
			<idx><h>Galois Theory</h></idx>
			This question is answered by a mathematical field known as Galois Theory.
		</p>
	</aside>
</section>
