<section xml:id="sec-sif-1-main">
	<title>The Line in the Sand</title>
	<objectives>
		<ul>
			<li>
				<p>
					Identify the slope of a line from a graph and from a chart of values.
				</p>
			</li>
			<li>
				<p>
					Calculate the coordinates of the <m>y</m>-intercept of a line.
				</p>
			</li>
			<li>
				<p>
					Convert linear equations into slope-intercept form.
				</p>
			</li>
			<li>
				<p>
					Sketch the graph of a line.
				</p>
			</li>
		</ul>
	</objectives>
	<p>
		In the previous section, we used intuition to find solutions to linear equations in two variables. It is not
		always the case that we can easily find solutions by inspection. So we are going to develop a more systematic
		approach to graphing that does not rely on intuition. To do this, we're going to build off of the solutions of
		lines that we looked at in the previous section. 
	</p>
	<p>
		You might have noticed that when we had charts of values that you can find other charts by changing the <m>x</m>
		and <m>y</m> values in a consistent manner. This sets up the idea that points on a line satisfy a certain ratio
		with regards to how the coordinates change. This can be formalized as the concept of the slope of a line. 
	</p>
	<aside>
		<p>
			The use of <m>\Delta</m> (the capital Greek letter "delta") to represent the change of a variable between
			two points is also used in physics and chemistry applications. 
		</p>
	</aside>
    <definition xml:id="def-slope">
        <title>Slope</title>
        <idx><h>slope (of a line)</h></idx>
        
        <statement>
            <p>
				The <term>slope</term> of a line is defined by the following ratio for any two distinct points on the
				line:
				<me>
					m = \frac{\Delta y}{\Delta x} = \frac{\text{The change of $y$}}{\text{The change of $x$}}
				</me>
            </p>
        </statement>
    </definition>
	<aside>
		<p>
			This is not the first time that we have run into the prohibition of dividing by zero. It is something very
			core to the concept of division. Have you thought through the reason for this yet? 
		</p>
	</aside>
	<p>
		There is a logical reason for not trying to apply this to vertical lines. In a vertical line, there is no change
		in the <m>y</m>-coordinate which means that we would be dividing by zero, and that leads to an undefined
		expression.
	</p>
	<activity xml:id="sec-sif-1-ac1-calculate-slopes">
		<title>Calculating Slopes from Points</title>
		<p>
			The slope can be calculated between any two points on the line and it will result in the same value. The
			consistent ratio of the changes of the two variables is what makes the line straight.
		</p>
		<aside>
			<p>
				Ask yourself: "What are the changes in the <m>x</m> and <m>y</m> coordinates going from this point to
				that point?" 
			</p>
		</aside>
		<p>
			<me>
				\begin{array}{c|c|c}
					x \amp y \amp (x,y) \\ \hline
					-5 \amp -2 \amp (-5, -2) \\
					-3 \amp -1 \amp (-3, -1) \\
					-1 \amp 0 \amp (-1, 0) \\
					1 \amp 1 \amp (1,1) \\
					3 \amp 2 \amp (3,2) \\
					5 \amp 3 \amp (5,3)
				\end{array}
			</me>
		</p>
		<p>
			<alert xml:id="sec-sif-1-ac1-ti">Try it!</alert>
		</p>
		<aside>
			<p>
				Notice that the fractions reduce. You could actually apply this idea backwards if you wanted to get new
				points on the line. 
			</p>
		</aside>
		<p>
			Calculate the slope of this line using three different pairs of points. Do not always pick consecutive
			points for this exercise. 
		</p>
		<solution>
			<p>
				The selected points may vary, but the slope will always be <m>\frac{1}{2}</m>.
				<me>
					\begin{array}{ll}
						\text{From $(-5, -2)$ to $(-3, -1)$:} \amp m = \frac{\Delta y}{\Delta x} = \frac{1}{2} \\ 
						\text{From $(-3, -1)$ to $(1, 1)$:} \amp m = \frac{\Delta y}{\Delta x} = \frac{2}{4} = \frac{1}{2} \\ 
						\text{From $(-1, 0)$ to $(5, 3)$:} \amp m = \frac{\Delta y}{\Delta x} = \frac{3}{6} = \frac{1}{2} 
					\end{array}
				</me>
			</p>
		</solution>
	</activity>
	<activity xml:id="sec-sif-1-ac2-slope-from-graph">
		<title>Identifying the Slope from a Graph</title>
		<p>
			When working with graphs of lines, we often use a different language to represent the same concept. The
			"rise" of a function is the change in the variable between two points (up is positive, down is negative),
			and the "run" of a function is the change in the variable between two points (right is positive, left is
			negative). This leads us to sometimes say "the slope is the rise over the run." 
		</p>
		<aside>
			<p>
				Most people make the run positive because it's more natural to move left-to-right. 
			</p>
		</aside>
		<image xml:id="sec-sif-1-slope-of-line" width="50%">
			<latex-image>
				\begin{tikzpicture}[scale=0.5]
					\draw[ultra thin, gray] (-5,-5) grid (5,5); 
					\draw[stealth-stealth] (-5.5,-3) -- (5.5,-3) node[black, anchor=west] {$x$}; 
					\draw[stealth-stealth] (-3,-5.5) -- (-3,5.5) node[anchor=south, black] {$y$}; 
					\draw (-5.5,-3.333) -- (5.5,4); 
					\draw[fill=black] (-2,-1) circle (0.1); 
					\draw[fill=black] (4,3) circle (0.1); 
					\draw (-2,-1) -- (4,-1) node[midway,anchor=north] {$\Delta x = \text{(Run)}$}; 
					\draw (4,-1) -- (4,3) node[midway,anchor=west] {$\Delta y = \text{(Rise)}$}; 
				\end{tikzpicture} 
			</latex-image>
		</image>
		<aside>
			<p>
				Since the fraction reduces, there is a point on the grid between the two marked points. Can you identify
				it? 
			</p>
		</aside>
		<p>
			<alert xml:id="sec-sif-1-ac2-ti">Try it!</alert>
		</p>
		<p>
			Determine the slope of the line in the diagram above. 
		</p>
		<solution>
			<p>
				<me>
					m = \frac{\Delta y}{\Delta x} = \frac{4}{6} = \frac{2}{3}
				</me> 
			</p>
		</solution>
	</activity>
	<image xml:id="sec-sif-1-slope-signs" width="100%">
		<latex-image>
			\begin{tikzpicture}
				\begin{scope}
					\draw (-2,-1) -- (2,1); 
					\draw (0,-1.5) node[anchor=north] {Positive slope}; 
				\end{scope} 
				\begin{scope} [shift={(6,0)}]
					\draw (-2,0) -- (2,0); 
					\draw (0,-1.5) node[anchor=north] {Zero slope}; 
				\end{scope} 
				\begin{scope} [shift={(12,0)}]
					\draw (-2,1) -- (2,-1); 
					\draw (0,-1.5) node[anchor=north] {Negative slope}; 
				\end{scope}
			\end{tikzpicture} 
		</latex-image>
	</image>
	<p>
		If the slope is positive, the line points from the lower-left to upper-right, and if the slope is negative, the
		line points from upper-left to lower-right. If the line is horizontal, then the slope is 0. 
	</p>
	<aside xml:id="sec-sif-1-slope-formula">
		<title>The Slope Formula</title>
		<p>
			<idx><h>slope</h></idx>
			The slope of the line that passes through the points <m>(x_1, y_1)</m> and <m>(x_2, y_2)</m> is given by
			<m>m = \frac{y_2 - y_1}{x_2 - x_1}</m>. 
		</p>
	</aside>
	<p>
		There is a formula for the slope of the line if you have the coordinates of two points. The formula is commonly
		given to students, but it can sometimes be a distraction. If you are able to construct a meaningful picture of
		the line, you will not need to memorize this formula. There are some practical uses from an algebraic
		perspective, but it's far better to have an understanding of the concepts than simply trying to apply formulas
		blindly. 
	</p>
	<p>
		The slope is one of the two parameters in the slope-intercept form of a line. The other parameter is the of the
		<m>y</m>-intercept. The <m>y</m>-intercept is the point where the line crosses the When this point is not a
		point on the grid, students often try to estimate the value. This is somewhat acceptable when sketching a graph,
		but it is usually not acceptable when reading a graph. The challenge is that is can be very difficult to
		identify them correctly. 
	</p>
	<p>
		Try to estimate the of the in the two graphs below, and you'll understand why estimation is not a reliable
		technique. 
	</p>
	<aside>
		<p>
			The <m>y</m>-intercept of the of the graph on the left is <m>\frac{1}{3}</m> and the <m>y</m>-intercept of
			the of the graph on the right is <m>\frac{2}{5}</m>.
		</p>
	</aside>
	<image xml:id="sec-sif-1-guess-intercepts" width="100%">
		<latex-image>
			\begin{tikzpicture} [scale=0.5]
				\begin{scope}
					\draw[ultra thin, gray] (-5,-5) grid (5,5); 
					\draw[stealth-stealth] (-5.5,0) -- (5.5,0) node[black, anchor=west] {$x$}; 
					\draw[stealth-stealth] (0,-5.5) -- (0,5.5) node[anchor=south, black] {$y$}; 
					\draw (-5.5,-3.333) -- (5.5,4); 
				\end{scope} 
				\begin{scope} [shift={(13,0)}]
					\draw[ultra thin, gray] (-5,-5) grid (5,5); 
					\draw[stealth-stealth] (-5.5,0) -- (5.5,0) node[black, anchor=west] {$x$}; 
					\draw[stealth-stealth] (0,-5.5) -- (0,5.5) node[anchor=south, black] {$y$}; 
					\draw (-5.5,-2.9) -- (5.5,3.7); 
				\end{scope}
			\end{tikzpicture} 
		</latex-image>
	</image>
	<p>
		This highlights the importance of developing an algebraic method for working with lines so that we can avoid
		needing to make estimates. Specifically, if we're given the equation of a line, it is a common goal to write it
		in slope-intercept form. 
	</p>

    <definition xml:id="def-slope-intercept-form">
        <title>Slope-Intercept Form</title>
        <idx><h>slope-intercept form (of a line)</h></idx>
        
        <statement>
            <p>
				The <term>slope-intercept form</term>  of a line is <m>y = mx + b</m>. In this form, <m>m</m> represents
				the slope and <m>b</m> represents the <m>y</m>-coordinate of the <m>y</m>-intercept of the line.
            </p>
        </statement>
    </definition>

	<p>
		The reason this works is because the of a line is the solution when <m>x = 0</m>. But in this form, setting
		<m>x = 0</m> makes the first term disappear, and you're left with <m>y = b</m>, which tells us that the line
		must pass through the point <m>(x,y) = (0,b)</m>. 
	</p>
	<activity xml:id="sec-sif-1-ac3-slope-intercept-form">
		<title>Writing a Line in Slope-Intercept Form</title>
		<p>
			Writing an equation in slope-intercept form is simply a matter of solving for in a linear equation. 
			<me>
				\begin{aligned}
					3x + 4y \amp = 8 \\
					4y \amp = -3x + 8 \amp \eqnspacer \amp \text{Subtract $3x$ from both sides} \\
					y \amp = -\frac{3}{4} x + 2 \amp \amp \text{Divide both sides by $4$} 
				\end{aligned}
			</me>
		</p>
		<aside>
			<p>
				Some people would write the last line as <m>y = -\frac{3x}{4} + 2</m>. It doesn't matter which way you
				do it as long as you recognize that they are both the same result. 
			</p>
		</aside>
		<p>
			<alert xml:id="sec-sif-1-ac3-ti">Try it!</alert>
		</p>
		<p>
			Write the equation <m>2x - 5y = 10</m> in slope-intercept form. 
		</p>
		<solution>
			<p>
				<me>
					\begin{aligned}
						2x - 5y \amp = 10 \\
						-5y \amp = -2x + 10 \amp \amp \text{Subtract $3x$ from both sides} \\
						y \amp = \frac{2}{5} x - 2 \amp \amp \text{Divide both sides by $-2$} 
					\end{aligned}
				</me>
			</p>
		</solution>
	</activity>
	<p>
		Once you have the equation written in slope-intercept form, you have the information to sketch the graph. You
		can immediately identify the and then you can use the slope to find a second point. 
	</p>
	<activity xml:id="sec-sif-1-ac4-graph-line">
		<title>Graphing a Line from Slope-Intercept Form</title>
		<aside>
			<p>
				Remember: "Slope is rise over run." 
			</p>
		</aside>
		<p>
			The line <m>y = -\frac{1}{2} x + 1</m> has its at the point <m>(0, 1)</m>. Since the slope is
			<m>-\frac{1}{2}</m> we can find a second point on the line by moving to the right 2 spaces and down 1 space.
			This gives us enough information to sketch the line. 
		</p>
		<aside>
			<p>
				You can also move left 2 spaces and up 1 space, but most people move to the right because it feels more
				natural. 
			</p>
		</aside>
		<p>
			<alert xml:id="sec-sif-1-ac4-ti">Try it!</alert>
		</p>
		<p>
			Graph the line <m>y = -\frac{1}{2} x + 1</m> on the empty grid.
		</p>
		<image xml:id="sec-sif-1-ac4-empty-grid" width="50%">
			<latex-image>
				\begin{tikzpicture}
					\begin{scope}
						\draw[ultra thin, gray] (-5,-5) grid (5,5); 
						\draw[stealth-stealth] (-5.5,0) -- (5.5,0) node[black, anchor=west] {$x$}; 
						\draw[stealth-stealth] (0,-5.5) -- (0,5.5) node[anchor=south, black] {$y$}; 
					\end{scope}
				\end{tikzpicture} 
			</latex-image>
		</image>
		<solution>
			<image xml:id="sec-sif-1-ti4-solution" width="50%">
				<latex-image>
					\begin{tikzpicture} [scale=0.5] 
						\begin{scope}
							\draw[ultra thin, lightgray] (-5,-5) grid (5,5); 
							\draw[stealth-stealth] (-5.5,0) -- (5.5,0) node[black, anchor=west] {$x$}; 
							\draw[stealth-stealth] (0,-5.5) -- (0,5.5) node[anchor=south, black] {$y$}; 
							\draw[fill=black] (0,1) circle (0.1); 
							\draw[fill=black] (2,0) circle (0.1); 
							\draw (-5.5,3.75) -- (5.5,-1.75); 
						\end{scope}
					\end{tikzpicture} 
				</latex-image>
			</image>
		</solution>
	</activity>
</section>
