<section xml:id="sec-vas-1-main">
	<title>This is a That</title>
	<objectives>
		<ul>
			<li>
				<p>
					Substitute a number for a variable then simplify or solve.
				</p>
			</li>
			<li>
				<p>
					Substitute a variable expression for another variable then simplify or solve.
				</p>
			</li>
		</ul>
	</objectives>
	<p>
		We have previously seen how we can substitute a number for a variable. This led us to write sentences like "If
		<m>x = 3</m>, then <m>2x + 1 = 7</m>." 
	</p>
	<aside>
		<p>
			In math, we often loop back to previous ideas to give ourselves a chance to go deeper. 
		</p>
	</aside>
	<p>
		We are not restricted to just single variable expressions. It is often the case that a problem is modeled using
		multiple variables. Algebraically, this is just a matter of making sure you use the correct value for the
		correct variable. But there are some potential pitfalls as the substitutions become more complex. 
	</p>
	<activity xml:id="sec-vas-1-ac1-multiple-substitutions">
		<title>Substituting for Multiple Variables</title>
		<p>
			The problem is fundamentally about demonstrating that you can make substitutions and perform the
			corresponding arithmetic correctly. When making a substitution, it is helpful to be in the habit of putting
			that substitution inside of parentheses. Sometimes it's necessary, and sometimes it's extraneous. Over time,
			you will have the experience and insight to see whether it's necessary, but to start off it's best be in the
			habit of using parentheses all the time. 
		</p>
		<aside>
			<p>
				Some people are comfortable doing both arithmetic steps mentally, while others aren't. For this section,
				we recommend showing your work at about this level to help identify any errors in your mental
				arithmetic. 
			</p>
		</aside>
		<p>
			Here is a presentation for finding the value of <m>3a - 2b</m> when <m>a = 2</m> and <m>b = 4</m>: 
			<me>
				\begin{aligned}
					3a - 2b \amp = 3(2) - 2(4) \amp \eqnspacer \amp \text{Substitute $a = 2$ and $b = 4$} \\
					\amp = 6 - 8 \amp \amp \text{Arithmetic} \\
					\amp = -2 \amp \amp \text{Arithmetic} 
				\end{aligned}
			</me>
			<me> \text{If <m>a = 2</m> and <m>b = 4</m>, then <m>3a - 2b = -2</m>.} </me> 
		</p>
		<p>
			<alert xml:id="sec-vas-1-ac1-ti">Try it!</alert>
		</p>
		<p>
			Determine the value of the expression <m>2x + 5y</m> when <m>x = 3</m> and <m>y = -2</m>. Show the
			calculation and write your result as an if-then statement. 
		</p>
		<solution>
			<p>
				<me>
					\begin{aligned}
						2x + 5y \amp = 2(3) + 5(-2) \amp \amp \text{Substitute $x = 3$ and $y = -2$} \\
						\amp = 6 + (-10) \amp \amp \text{Arithmetic} \\
						\amp = -4 \amp \amp \text{Arithmetic} 
					\end{aligned}
				</me>
				<me>
					\text{If $x = 3$ and $y = -2$, then $2x + 5y = -4$.}
				</me> 
			</p>
		</solution>
	</activity>
	<p>
		A major step in your mathematical thinking is the ability to apply previous results in new settings, and
		combining old ideas in new ways. We have talked about substituting a value for a variable, and we've talked
		about solving for a variable. We can combine the two into a new type of problem. 
	</p>
	<activity xml:id="sec-vas-1-ac2-substitute-solve-1">
		<title>Substituting a Value for a Variable and Solving</title>
		<aside>
			<p>
				In this case, no matter what value of <m>m</m> or <m>n</m> is given to you, there will always be a
				solution. But for some equations, this won't happen. 
			</p>
		</aside>
		<p>
			Here is an example of combining the two ideas together. Consider the equation <m>3m + 5n = 30</m>. This
			 equation has two variables in it. If we declare a value for one of the variables, then we can solve for the
			 other one. For example, if we are told that <m>m = 5</m>, then we have the following: 
			<me>
				\begin{aligned}
					3m + 5n \amp = 30 \\
					3(5) + 5n \amp = 30 \amp \eqnspacer \amp \text{Substitute $m = 5$} \\
					15 + 5n \amp = 30 \amp \amp \text{Arithmetic} \\
					5n \amp = 15 \amp \amp \text{Subtract $15$ from both sides} \\
					n \amp = 3 \amp \amp \text{Divide both sides by 5} 
				\end{aligned}
			</me>
		</p>
		<aside>
			<p>
				Don't be afraid of fractions. 
			</p>
		</aside>
		<p>
			<alert xml:id="sec-vas-1-ac2-ti">Try it!</alert>
		</p>
		<p>
				Solve the equation <m>3m + 5n = 30</m> for when <m>n = -2</m>. Use a complete presentation. 
		</p>
		<solution>
			<p>
				<me>
					\begin{aligned}
						3m + 5n \amp = 30 \\
						3m + 5(-2) \amp = 30 \amp \amp \text{Substitute $n = -2$} \\
						3m + (-10) \amp = 30 \amp \amp \text{Arithmetic} \\
						3m \amp = 40 \amp \amp \text{Add $10$ to both sides} \\
						m \amp = \frac{40}{3} \amp \amp \text{Divide both sides by $3$} 
					\end{aligned}
				</me>
			</p>
		</solution>
	</activity>
	<p>
		There are other types of substitutions that we can make. In the definition of a variable
		(<xref ref="def-variable"/>), we said that variables can also represent mathematical expressions.
		Fortunately, there is no conceptual difference between the two. It all comes down to the proper execution of
		algebra. 
	</p>
	<activity xml:id="sec-vas-1-ac3-substitute-expressions">
		<title>Substituting an Expression for a Variable</title>
		<p>
			When substituting an expression for a variable, it is important to wrap the expression inside of
			parentheses. This small detail is extremely important because it represents a container that holds the
			entire contents of the variable. Failure to do so will often lead to failing to properly apply the
			distributive property or committing other types of errors. 
		</p>
		<p>
			This is how it looks to substitute <m>x = 2y - 1</m> into the expression <m>-x + 6</m>: 
			<me>
				\begin{aligned}
					-x + 6 \amp = -(2y - 1) + 6 \amp \eqnspacer \amp \text{Substitute $x = 2y - 1$} \\
					\amp = -2y + 1 + 6 \amp \amp \text{Distributive property} \\
					\amp = -2y + 7 \amp \amp \text{Combine like terms} 
				\end{aligned}
			</me>
		</p>
		<p>
			<alert xml:id="sec-vas-1-ac3-ti">Try it!</alert>
		</p>
		<p>
			Substitute <m>a = -2b + 3</m> into the expression <m>-2a - 5</m> and simplify the result. Use a 
			 presentation. 
		</p>
		<solution>
			<p>
				<me>
					\begin{aligned}
						-2a - 5 \amp = -2(-2b + 3) - 5 \amp \amp \text{Substitute $a = -2b + 3$} \\
						\amp = 4b - 6 - 5 \amp \amp \text{Distributive property} \\
						\amp = 4b - 11 \amp \amp \text{Combine like terms} 
					\end{aligned}
				</me>
			</p>
		</solution>
	</activity>
	<activity xml:id="sec-vas-1-ac4-substitute-solve-2">
		<title>Substituting an Expression for a Variable and Solving</title>
		<p>
			Conceptually, substituting into an expression is not different from substituting into an equation because an
			equation is just two expressions that are claimed to represent the same value. 
		</p>
		<aside>
			<p>
				This might remind you of the substitution method of solving linear equations. If you don't know what
				that is, we'll get to it in <xref ref="sec-mos-1-main"/>. 
			</p>
		</aside>
		<p>
			<alert xml:id="sec-vas-1-ac4-ti">Try it!</alert>
		</p>
		<p>
			Substitute <m>x = 2y + 1</m> into the equation <m>3x - 2y = 7</m> and solve for Use a complete presentation. 
		</p>
		<solution>
			<p>
				<me>
					\begin{aligned}
						3x - 2y \amp = 7 \\
						3(2y + 1) - 2y \amp = 7 \amp \amp \text{Substitute $x = 2y + 1$} \\
						6y + 3 - 2y \amp = 7 \amp \amp \text{Distributive property} \\
						4y + 3 \amp = 7 \amp \amp \text{Combine like terms} \\
						4y \amp = 4 \amp \amp \text{Subtract $6$ from both sides} \\
						y \amp = 1 \amp \amp \text{Divide both sides by $4$} 
					\end{aligned}
				</me>
			</p>
		</solution>
	</activity>
</section>
