<section xml:id="sec-fas-5-deeper">
	<title>Going Deeper: Adding and Subtracting Rational Expressions</title>
	<p>
		In some ways, the exercises in this section give a false impression of working with rational expressions. It is
		not often the case that we're adding and subtracting the types of <em>monomial</em> expressions that were
		presented. The reason the exercises look that way is because the emphasis is on learning to recognize when the
		denominators have common factors and when they don't, which leads to knowing what to multiply by to create the
		common denominators. By using different variables, it's much easier for students to train themselves to
		recognize the common factors. 
	</p>
	<aside>
		<p>
			More specifically, the most common manipulation you will encounter will involve binomial factors. 
		</p>
	</aside>
	<p>
		It's likely that you will only ever encounter single variable rational expressions. But the skill of identifying
		different terms will still come into play because you will need to recognize when <em>polynomial</em> factors
		are the same or different. For example, instead of working with fractions of the form
		<me>
			\frac{1}{a} + \frac{1}{b}
		</me>
		you will be working with fractions of the form
		<me>
			\frac{1}{x + 2} + \frac{1}{x - 3}.
		</me> 
	</p>
	<p>
		In the previous "Going Deeper" section, we emphasized the importance of multiplicative factors when reducing
		rational expressions. The same idea holds for adding and subtracting rational expressions. We need to think in
		terms of multiplicative factors. The way we accomplish this is to think of the whole binomial as a single
		object. Basically, we want to envision a set of parentheses around each binomial.
		<me>
			\frac{1}{x + 2} + \frac{1}{x - 3} = \frac{1}{(x + 2)} + \frac{1}{(x - 3)}
		</me>
		And once we have done this, all of the experience that we were developing in this section can come into play.
		All of the previous logic applies to this calculation.
	</p>
	<aside>
		<p>
			We encourage students to leave the denominator as a product. Since it's easier to multiply than it is to
			factor, it makes more sense to leave it in the form that is easier to work with. 
		</p>
	</aside>
	<p>
		<me>
			\begin{aligned}
				\frac{1}{x + 2} + \frac{1}{x - 3}
				\amp = \frac{1 \cdot (x - 3)}{(x + 2) \cdot (x - 3)} + \frac{1 \cdot (x + 2)}{(x - 3) \cdot (x + 2)} \amp \eqnspacer \amp \text{Common denominator} \\
				\amp = \frac{x - 3}{(x + 2)(x - 3)} + \frac{x + 2}{(x + 2)(x - 3)} \\
				\amp = \frac{(x - 3) + (x + 2)}{(x + 2)(x - 3)} \\
				\amp = \frac{2x - 1}{(x + 2)(x - 3)} 
			\end{aligned}
		</me>
	</p>
	<aside>
		<p>
			This idea goes all the way back to <xref ref="sec-lult-1-main" /> . 
		</p>
	</aside>
	<p>
		When subtracting rational expressions, it's extremely important to keep the parentheses around terms when
		subtracting. This did not come up in the section because we were only working with monomial terms. But when
		working with binomials, those parentheses are critical to avoid errors. 
		<me>
			\begin{aligned}
				\frac{x}{x - 1} - \frac{3}{x + 3}
				\amp = \frac{x \cdot (x + 3)}{(x - 1) \cdot (x + 3)} - \frac{3 \cdot (x - 1)}{(x + 3) \cdot (x - 1)} \amp \eqnspacer \amp \text{Common denominator} \\
				\amp = \frac{x^2 + 3x}{(x - 1)(x + 3)} - \frac{3x - 3}{(x - 1)(x + 3)} \\
				\amp = \frac{(x^2 + 3x) - (3x - 3)}{(x - 1)(x + 3)} \\
				\amp = \frac{x^2 + 3x - 3x + 3}{(x - 1)(x + 3)} \\
				\amp = \frac{x^2 + 3}{(x - 1)(x + 3)} 
			\end{aligned}
		</me>
	</p>
	<p>
		In some expressions, you may find that after adding or subtracting, it may be possible to factor the numerator.
		When you can see a way to factor, it's best to do it. The reason is that sometimes these factorization steps
		will reveal that the fraction can be reduced or simplified, which can be very helpful. 
		<me>
			\begin{aligned}
				\frac{1}{x - 2} + \frac{x - 5}{(x - 2)(x + 1)}
				\amp = \frac{1 \cdot (x + 1)}{(x - 2) \cdot (x + 1)} + \frac{x - 5}{(x - 2)(x + 1)} \amp \eqnspacer \amp \text{Common denominator} \\
				\amp = \frac{x + 1}{(x - 2)(x + 1)} + \frac{x - 5}{(x - 2)(x + 1)} \\
				\amp = \frac{(x + 1) + (x - 5)}{(x - 2)(x + 1)} \\
				\amp = \frac{2x - 4}{(x - 2)(x + 1)} \\
				\amp = \frac{2(x - 2)}{(x - 2)(x + 1)} \\
				\amp = \frac{2 \cdot \cancel{(x - 2)}}{(x + 1) \cdot \cancel{(x - 2)}} \\
				\amp = \frac{2}{x + 1} 
			\end{aligned}
		</me>
	</p>
	<p>
		It is hard to know in advance which calculations will lead to fractions that reduce and which ones don't,
		so you will just want to get into the habit of factoring the numerator when you can.
	</p>
</section>
