<section xml:id="sec-fd-5-deeper">
	<title>Going Deeper: Fractions Inside of Fractions</title>
	<p>
		The technique of multiplying the top and bottom of a fraction by the same value to eliminate the denominators
		seems odd when working with fractions involving numbers, but its value goes up significantly when working with
		rational expressions. One of the more algebraically difficult situations to work with is when you have fractions
		inside of other fractions. It's not that anything about the process is different, but the sheer number of
		symbols can cause students to feel overwhelmed and make mistakes. 
	</p>
	<p>
		Here is an example. The goal is to simplify the following fraction:
		<me>
			\frac{ \frac{1}{x + 1} - \frac{3}{x - 2}}{ \frac{2} {x - 2} + \frac{1}{x + 3}}
		</me>
		We will first do the calculation by adding the fractions in the numerator and denominator, and then dividing the
		resulting fractions by multiplying by the reciprocal. 
		<me>
			\begin{aligned}
				\frac{\frac{1}{x + 1} - \frac{3}{x - 2}}{ \frac{2} {x - 2} + \frac{1}{x + 3}}
				\amp = \frac{ \frac{1 \cdot (x - 2)}{(x + 1) \cdot (x - 2)} - \frac{3 \cdot (x + 1)}{(x - 2) \cdot (x + 1)}}{ \frac{2 \cdot (x + 3)} {(x - 2) \cdot (x + 3)} + \frac{1 \cdot (x - 2)}{(x + 3) \cdot (x - 2)}} \amp \eqnspacer \amp \text{Common Denominator} \\
				\amp = \frac{ \frac{(x - 2) - (3x + 3)}{(x + 1) (x - 2)} }{ \frac{(2x + 6) + (x - 2)} {(x - 2) (x + 3)}} \\
				\amp = \frac{ \frac{-2x - 5}{(x + 1) (x - 2)} }{ \frac{3x + 4} {(x - 2) (x + 3)}} \amp \amp \text{Combine like terms} \\
				\amp = \frac{-2x - 5}{(x + 1) (x - 2)} \cdot \frac{(x - 2) (x + 3)}{3x + 4} \amp \amp \text{Multiply by the reciprocal} \\
				\amp = - \frac{(2x + 5)(x - 2)(x + 3)}{(x + 1)(x - 2)(3x + 4)} \amp \amp \text{Multiply and factor out the negative} \\
				\amp = - \frac{(2x + 5)(x + 3) \cdot \cancel{(x - 2)}}{(x + 1)(3x + 4) \cdot \cancel{(x - 2)}} \amp \amp \text{Reduce} \\
				\amp = - \frac{(2x + 5)(x + 3)}{(x + 1)(3x + 4)} \amp \amp \text{Reduce} \\
			\end{aligned}
		</me>
	</p>
	<aside>
		<p>
			This process somewhat mirrors the process of clearing the denominator in <xref ref="sec-bap-5-deeper" /> . 
		</p>
	</aside>
	<p>
		We will now do the same calculation, but we will multiply the numerator and denominator by the same value to
		eliminate the fractions inside of the fraction. 
		<me>
			\begin{aligned}
				\frac{\frac{1}{x + 1} - \frac{3}{x - 2}}{ \frac{2} {x - 2} + \frac{1}{x + 3}}
				\amp = \frac{\frac{1}{x + 1} - \frac{3}{x - 2}}{ \frac{2} {x - 2} + \frac{1}{x + 3}} \cdot \frac{(x+1)(x-2)(x+3)}{(x+1)(x-2)(x+3)} \amp \eqnspacer \amp \text{Multiply top and bottom} \\
				\amp = \frac{\frac{(x+1)(x-2)(x+3)}{x + 1} - \frac{3(x+1)(x-2)(x+3)}{x - 2}}{ \frac{2(x+1)(x-2)(x+3)} {x - 2} + \frac{(x+1)(x-2)(x+3)}{x + 3}} \amp \amp \text{Distribute} \\
				\amp = \frac{\frac{\cancel{(x+1)}(x-2)(x+3)}{\cancel{x + 1}} - \frac{3(x+1)\cancel{(x-2)}(x+3)}{\cancel{x - 2}}}{ \frac{2(x+1)\cancel{(x-2)}(x+3)} {\cancel{x - 2}} + \frac{(x+1)(x-2)\cancel{(x+3)}}{\cancel{x + 3}}} \amp \amp \text{Reduce} \\
				\amp = \frac{(x-2)(x+3) - 3(x+1)(x+3)}{2(x+1)(x+3) + (x+1)(x-2)} \amp \amp \text{Rewrite and simplify} \\
				\amp = \frac{(x^2 + x - 6) - (3x^2 + 12x + 9)}{(2x^2 + 8x + 6) + (x^2 - x - 2)} \\
				\amp = \frac{-2x^2 - 11 x - 15}{3x^2 + 7x + 4} \\
				\amp = - \frac{2x^2 + 11 x + 15}{3x^2 + 7x + 4} \amp \amp \text{Factor out the negative} \\
				\amp = - \frac{(2x + 5)(x + 3)}{(x+1)(3x + 4)} 
			\end{aligned}
		</me>
	</p>
	<aside>
		<p>
			You should go through each calculation step by step to make sure that you really understand what happened. 
		</p>
	</aside>
	<p>
		Both of these calculations involve a lot of steps, and neither one is necessarily better than the other. The
		first one required the proper execution of more fraction calculations, but the second one required a
		factorization step to ensure that the expression cannot be reduced. Both of those steps can be difficult in
		their own ways. 
	</p>
	<p>
		It should be noted that expressions that are this messy do not appear particularly frequently, but if you
		continue along in mathematics, you will find that calculations involving fractions inside of fractions do
		appear. There are two reasons for including this calculation here. The first is to expose you to some of the
		more intricate algebraic manipulations that arise in higher levels of mathematics. The second is to point out
		the fact that even though the algebra may look complicated, there's nothing here that you haven't seen before or
		is beyond your ability. Your capacity for handling complicated expressions like these will grow as you continue
		to practice and gain experience.
	</p>
</section>
