<section xml:id="sec-das-1-main">
	<title>Making Sense with Dollars and Cents</title>
	<objectives>
		<ul>
			<li>
				<p>
					Understand the relationship between decimals and fractions.
				</p>
			</li>
			<li>
				<p>
					Add and subtract decimals.
				</p>
			</li>
		</ul>
	</objectives>
	<p>
		Although fractions are important and useful for algebraic manipulations, many of the day-to-day numbers that
		people encounter are decimals. But it turns out that decimals are just a special way of writing parts of a
		whole, which means that they're also just fractions. Most students don't have a good sense of the interplay
		between the two notations, and quite often think of them as mostly unrelated to each other. 
	</p>
	<p>
		<idx><h>place value system</h></idx>
		Where do decimals even come from? It turns out that this is an extension of the way we write numbers. We use
		what a <em>place value system</em> which means that our numbers depend on both the symbol we use (the digits
		0-9) and the position of that digit within the number itself. 
	</p>
	<activity xml:id="sec-das-1-ac1-representing-numbers">
		<idx><h>standard form (of a number)</h></idx>
		<idx><h>exapnded form (of a number)</h></idx>
		<title>Representations of Numbers</title>
		<aside>
			<p>
				The normal way of writing numbers is known as the <em>standard form</em> of a number. \\ \\
				Breaking a number into distinct units like this is called the <em>expanded form</em> of a number. 
			</p>
		</aside>
		<image xml:id="sec-das-1-representations" width="60%">
			<latex-image>
				\begin{tikzpicture}[scale=0.58]
					\draw (0,0) node[anchor=west] {$238 = 200 + 30 + 8$}; 
					\draw[stealth-] (0.45,-0.5) -- ++ (0,-0.5) -- (-1.5,-1) node[anchor=east] {\strut 2 Hundreds}; 
					\draw[stealth-] (0.8,-0.5) -- ++ (0,-1.5) -- (-1.5,-2) node[anchor=east] {\strut 3 Tens}; 
					\draw[stealth-] (1.15,-0.5) -- ++ (0,-2.5) -- (-1.5,-3) node[anchor=east] {\strut 8 Ones}; 
					\draw[stealth-] (2.7,0.5) -- ++ (0,2.5) -- (7,3) node[anchor=west] {\strut 2 Hundreds}; 
					\draw[stealth-] (4.5,0.5) -- ++ (0,1.5) -- (7,2) node[anchor=west] {\strut 3 Tens}; 
					\draw[stealth-] (5.9,0.5) -- ++ (0,0.5) -- (7,1) node[anchor=west] {\strut 8 Ones}; 
				\end{tikzpicture} 
			</latex-image>
		</image>
		<p>
			Let's think about the number 237. We have been trained to understand that when we put digits side-by-side
			like this to make larger numbers, that each digit refers to a different group size. 
		</p>
		<p>
			<alert xml:id="sec-das-1-ac1-ti">Try it!</alert>
		</p>
		<p>
			Write the number 8367 in expanded form and label each of the parts with the corresponding unit (as shown above). 
		</p>
		<solution>
			<image xml:id="sec-das-1-ti1-solution" width="90%">
				<latex-image>
					\begin{tikzpicture} [scale=0.5]
						\draw (0,0) node[anchor=west] {$8367 = 8000 + 300 + 60 + 7$}; 
						\draw[stealth-] (0.5,-0.5) -- ++ (0,-0.5) -- (-1.5,-1) node[anchor=east] {\strut 8 Thousands}; 
						\draw[stealth-] (0.9,-0.5) -- ++ (0,-1.5) -- (-1.5,-2) node[anchor=east] {\strut 3 Hundreds}; 
						\draw[stealth-] (1.3,-0.5) -- ++ (0,-2.5) -- (-1.5,-3) node[anchor=east] {\strut 6 Tens}; 
						\draw[stealth-] (1.7,-0.5) -- ++ (0,-3.5) -- (-1.5,-4) node[anchor=east] {\strut 7 Ones}; 
						\draw[stealth-] (4,0.5) -- ++ (0,3.5) -- (11,4) node[anchor=west] {\strut 8 Thousands}; 
						\draw[stealth-] (6.2,0.5) -- ++ (0,2.5) -- (11,3) node[anchor=west] {\strut 3 Hundreds}; 
						\draw[stealth-] (8.4,0.5) -- ++ (0,1.5) -- (11,2) node[anchor=west] {\strut 6 Tens}; 
						\draw[stealth-] (10,0.5) -- ++ (0,0.5) -- (11,1) node[anchor=west] {\strut 7 Ones}; 
					\end{tikzpicture} 
				</latex-image>
			</image>
		</solution>
	</activity>
	<p>
		The choice to use ones, tens, and hundreds (and also thousands, ten thousands, and so forth) is because each of
		those numbers turns out to be a power of 10.
	</p>
		<image xml:id="sec-das-1-positive-powers-of-10" width="70%">
			<latex-image>
				\begin{tikzpicture}
					\draw (0,0) node[anchor=north] {
						\begin{tabular}{c|rr}
							Units \amp \multicolumn{2}{c}{Representations} \\ \hline
							Ones \amp $10^0 =$ \amp 1 \\
							Tens \amp $10^1 =$ \amp 10 \\
							Hundreds \amp $10^2 =$ \amp 100 \\ 
							Thousands \amp $10^3 =$ \amp 1\,000 \\
							Ten thousands \amp $10^4 =$ \amp 10\,000 \\
							Hundred thousands \amp $10^5 =$ \amp 100\,000 \\
							Millions \amp $10^6 =$ \amp 1\,000\,000 \\
							Billions \amp $10^9 =$ \amp 1\,000\,000\,000 \\
							Trillions \amp $10^{12} =$ \amp 1\,000\,000\,000\,000 \\
						\end{tabular}
					};
				\end{tikzpicture}
			</latex-image>
		</image>
	<aside>
		<p>
			For the sake of space, we skipped over ten million and a hundred million, and similarly for billions. It
			just follows the same pattern. 
		</p>
	</aside>
	<p>
		Notice that as we go down the list, the exponents increase and so do the numbers. If we go up the list, the
		exponents get decrease and so do the numbers. And in the same way we used this pattern to develop negative
		exponents, we can develop decimals. The naming of these units are a little awkward to say out loud, but the
		mathematics behind them is simple. Tenths are the size you get when you take one object and break it into ten
		pieces. Hundredths are the size you get when you take one object and break it into one hundred pieces. 
	</p>
	<activity xml:id="sec-das-1-ac2-expanded-form">
		<title>Expanded Form of a Number</title>
		<p>
		</p>
		<p>
			<alert xml:id="sec-das-1-ac2-ti">Try it!</alert>
		</p>
		<p>
			Write the number 35.79 in expanded form and label each of the parts with the corresponding unit. 
		</p>
		<solution>
			<image xml:id="sec-das-1-ti2-solution">
				<latex-image>
					\begin{tikzpicture} [scale=0.5]
						\draw (0,0) node[anchor=west] {$35.79 = 30 + 5 + 0.7 + 0.09$}; 
						\draw[stealth-] (0.5,-0.5) -- ++ (0,-0.5) -- (-1.5,-1) node[anchor=east] {\strut 3 Tens}; 
						\draw[stealth-] (0.9,-0.5) -- ++ (0,-1.5) -- (-1.5,-2) node[anchor=east] {\strut 5 Ones}; 
						\draw[stealth-] (1.6,-0.5) -- ++ (0,-2.5) -- (-1.5,-3) node[anchor=east] {\strut 7 Tenths}; 
						\draw[stealth-] (2.0,-0.5) -- ++ (0,-3.5) -- (-1.5,-4) node[anchor=east] {\strut 9 Hundredths}; 
						\draw[stealth-] (3.7,0.5) -- ++ (0,3.5) -- (11,4) node[anchor=west] {\strut 3 Tens}; 
						\draw[stealth-] (5.3,0.5) -- ++ (0,2.5) -- (11,3) node[anchor=west] {\strut 5 Ones}; 
						\draw[stealth-] (7.1,0.5) -- ++ (0,1.5) -- (11,2) node[anchor=west] {\strut 7 Tenths}; 
						\draw[stealth-] (9.4,0.5) -- ++ (0,0.5) -- (11,1) node[anchor=west] {\strut 9 Hundredths}; 
					\end{tikzpicture} 
				</latex-image>
			</image>
		</solution>
	</activity>
	<p>
		It turns out that decimals have multiple representations. This comes out of thinking about multiple
		representations of the same fraction. 
		<me>
			\begin{aligned}
				0.3 = \frac{3}{10} \amp = \frac{30}{100} = 0.30 \\
				\amp = \frac{300}{1000} = 0.300 \\
				\amp = \frac{3000}{10000} = 0.3000 
			\end{aligned}
		</me>
	</p>
	<activity xml:id="sec-das-1-ac3-fractions-decimals">
		<title>The Connection Between Fractions and Decimals</title>
		<p>
			There is a simple connection between the number of decimals and the powers of ten. The number of zeros in
			the power of in the denominator corresponds to the number of decimal places for that representation of the
			number. For example, the number 0.0365 (four decimal places) corresponds to <m>\frac{365}{10000}</m> (four
			zeros in the denominator). In fact, this number also corresponds to the exponent of the in the denominator:
			<m>\frac{365}{10000} = \frac{365}{10^4}</m>. Thinking about numbers this way will help to avoid certain
			types of errors. 
		</p>
		<aside>
			<p>
				For the purposes of this section, it's not important to reduce the fraction. 
			</p>
		</aside>
		<p>
			<alert xml:id="sec-das-1-ac3-ti">Try it!</alert>
		</p>
		<p>
			Write the number as a fraction. 
		</p>
		<solution>
			<p>
				<me> 0.086 = \frac{86}{1000} = \frac{86}{10^3} </me> 
			</p>
		</solution>
	</activity>
	<aside>
		<p>
			If all the numbers have the same number of decimals, it's ensuring that all of the corresponding fractions
			have the same denominator. 
		</p>
	</aside>
	<p>
		Most of the challenges with addition and subtraction of decimals are resolved by simply ensuring that all your
		numbers have the same number of decimal places. The best analogy for this is money. American currency is always
		written with two decimal places (if decimal places are being used). And what this does is that it helps us think
		about the coins relative to same base unit (1 cent) all the time, and there's no confusion about whether a dime
		($0.10) is the same as a penny ($0.01). 
	</p>
	<activity xml:id="sec-das-1-ac4-add-decimals">
		<title>Adding Decimals</title>
		<p>
			It can be helpful to ensure that all of the numbers are written to the same number of decimals if the
			calculation is intended to be performed mentally or by hand. This will help to reinforce the underlying
			concept as well as avoid computational errors.
			<me>
				3.04 + 1.1 = 3.04 + 1.10 = 4.14
			</me> 
		</p>
		<p>
			<alert xml:id="sec-das-1-ac4-ti">Try it!</alert>
		</p>
		<p>
			Calculate <m>2.5 + 1.22</m>. 
		</p>
		<solution>
			<p>
				<me> 2.5 + 1.22 = 2.50 + 1.22 = 3.72 </me> 
			</p>
		</solution>
	</activity>
	<activity xml:id="sec-das-1-ac5-subtract-decimals">
		<title>Subtracting Decimals</title>
		<p>
			The exact same trick applies to subtraction.
			<me>
				2.8 - 1.06 = 2.80 - 1.06 = 1.74
			</me> 
		</p>
		<p>
			<alert xml:id="sec-das-1-ac5-ti">Try it!</alert>
		</p>
		<p>
			Calculate <m>4.77 - 2.3</m>. 
		</p>
		<solution>
			<p>
				<me> 4.77 - 2.3 = 4.77 - 2.30 = 2.47 </me> 
			</p>
		</solution>
	</activity>
	<p>
		In practice, most decimal calculations are done by calculator or computer. In fact, certain disciplines (such as
		physics and chemistry) use the number of decimals as an indication of the quality of a measurement, so that 4.21
		is not the same measurement as 4.21000. So we will not be spending a lot of time performing large decimal
		calculations by hand. Instead, this section should be interpreted as developing a conceptual basis, not a
		computational basis, for decimals. 
	</p>
</section>
