<section xml:id="sec-bap-1-main">
    <title>How We Write Affects How We Think</title>

    <objectives>
        <ul>
            <li>
                <p>
                    Present a sequence of algebraic manipulations with the equal signs lined up.
                </p>
            </li>
            <li>
                <p>
                    State an algebraic manipulation in words and then execute that manipulation correctly.
                </p>
            </li>
        </ul>
    </objectives>

    
    <p>
        Welcome to college level mathematics! It is a well-known fact that many students struggle with college
        mathematics. There are many people who proudly announce that they took a college math course three or
        four times before they passed.
    </p>
    <aside>
        <p>
            What does it say about the state of math education when people are proud that they failed math classes?
        </p>
    </aside>
    <p>
        But what is less known are the reasons why students struggle with college level mathematics. Some will cite
        math anxiety, others may blame the instructor, and others will simply say that they're not math people. And
        there's probably a hint of truth to all of those.
    </p>
    <aside>
        <p>
            Growth Mindset: "I'm not a math person ... yet."
        </p>
    </aside>
    <p>
        A more basic reason for struggling with mathematics is that most students simply have not learned to think
        mathematically before they get to college. Maybe they've memorized some formulas and some basic ways to
        manipulate equations, but there's often a gap of understanding and the inability to communicate mathematics
        effectively.
    </p>
    <aside>
        <p>
            Have you ever said "I know what I'm doing, but I can't explain it"?
        </p>
    </aside>
    <p>
        The easiest way to spot this is when a student says, "I know what I'm doing, but I can't explain it." This might
        be good enough at lower levels of mathematics, where the goal is simply to get the answer, but college level
        mathematics is different. We want students to be able to explain what they're doing and why.
    </p>
    <aside>
        <p>
            A couple more aspects of mathematical thinking:
            <ul>
                <li>
                    <p>
                        The confidence to attempt to solve problems using mathematics.
                    </p>
                </li>
                <li>
                    <p>
                        The curiosity to ask questions about mathematical ideas. 
                    </p>
                </li>
            </ul>
        </p>
    </aside>
    <p>
        <idx><h>mathematical thinking</h></idx>
        These materials are designed to help students bridge that gap so that they can become mathematical thinkers. But
        what is mathematical thinking? While it's hard to describe it in complete detail, it includes (and is not
        limited to) the following:
        <ul>
            <li>
                <p>
                    The ability to think logically and analytically to solve problems
                </p>
            </li>
            <li>
                <p>
                    The proper manipulation of symbols in the process of solving problems
                </p>
            </li>
            <li>
                <p>
                    The ability to communicate and explain the ideas behind algebraic manipulations and the reasons for
                    using them
                </p>
            </li>
        </ul>
    </p>
    <aside>
        <p>
            You will often hear people say that math is a language. It can be useful to think of it in that way.
        </p>
    </aside>
    <p>
        As you work your way through these materials, you should be finding yourself being able to do these things
        better through thoughtful practice and repetition. Just as with a foreign language, it's not enough to just
        say a phrase once to learn it. You need to do it over and over again, and you need to see it or hear in multiple
        contexts.
    </p>
    <aside>
        <p>
            These are not "rules" that must be followed all the time. But they are good guidelines for what clean
            mathematical presentation should look like.
        </p>
    </aside>


    <activity xml:id="sec-bap-1-ac1-expectations">
        <title>The Basic Presentation Expectations</title>
        <p>
            <idx><h>complete presentation</h></idx>
            We're going to start with some basic ideas for communicating mathematics. For the purposes of this book, a
            <term>complete presentation</term> of a mathematical manipulation includes the following pieces:
            <ul>
                <li>
                    <p>
                        A series of equations or expressions with the equal signs lined up vertically
                    </p>
                </li>
                <li>
                    <p>
                        An explanation of the manipulations on the right side of each manipulation
                    </p>
                </li>
            </ul>
        </p>       
        <aside>
            <p>
                Most textbooks use this format when presenting examples.
            </p>
        </aside>
        <p>
            Here is an example of solving the equation <m>3x + 4 = 16</m> using a complete presentation:
            <me>
                \begin{aligned}
                    3x + 4 \amp = 16 \\
                    3x \amp = 12 \amp \eqnspacer \amp \text{Subtract $4$ from both sides} \\
                    x \amp = 4 \amp \amp \text{Divide both sides by $3$}
                \end{aligned}
            </me>
        </p>
        <p>
            <alert xml:id="sec-bap-1-ac1-ti">Try it!</alert>
        </p>
        <p>
            Using <xref ref="sec-bap-1-ac1-expectations"/> as a model, solve the equation <m>5x - 7 = 23</m>.
        </p>
        <solution>
            <p>
                <me>
                    \begin{aligned}
                        5x - 7 \amp = 23 \\
                        5x \amp = 30 \amp \eqnspacer \amp \text{Add $7$ to both sides} \\
                        x \amp = 6 \amp \amp \text{Divide both sides by $5$}
                    \end{aligned}
                </me>                
            </p>
        </solution>
    </activity>
    
    
    <activity xml:id="sec-bap-1-ac2-vertical-align">
        <title>Lining up Equal Signs Vertically</title>
        <aside>
            <p>
                If you want to be environmentally conscious, you can work in two or three columns on your page instead
                of leaving the right half of the paper blank.
            </p>
        </aside>
        <p>
            Lining up the equal signs is mostly a matter of organization and readability. Some students learned to do
            this because then they can use up the entire width of their paper and can cram in more problems per page.
            Unfortunately, as problems become more complex, this leads to all sorts of small errors that could easily
            be avoided by a more organized presentation.
        </p>
        <aside>
            <p>
                This exercise is much more difficult with handwritten math. Typed math is so clean that the errors
                easier to find.
            </p>
        </aside>
        <p>
            Consider the following set of equations:
            <me>5x + 9 = -3x - 7 \qquad 5x = - 3x + 16 \qquad 2x = 16 \qquad x = 8</me>
            There are two errors embedded into these calculations. Notice how much your eyes have to go back and forth
            to match up the terms. Lining up the equal signs vertically reduce that distance and make it easier to see
            when terms change or disappear. It also helps you to keep track of what is on the left side of the equation
            and what is on the right side of the equation.
        </p>
        <aside>
            <p>
                    If you aren't familiar with solving equations like this, talk to your instructor for further help.
            </p>
        </aside>
        <p>
            <alert xml:id="sec-bap-1-ac2-ti">Try it!</alert>            
        </p>
        <p>
            Present the calculation in <xref ref="sec-bap-1-ac2-vertical-align"/> using a complete presentation. Be
            sure to fix the errors.
        </p>
        <solution>
            <p>
                The two errors:
                <ol>
                    <li>
                        <p>
                            Line 2: Wrong sign on the 16
                        </p>
                    </li>
                    <li>
                        <p>
                            Line 3: Calculation error
                        </p>
                    </li>
                </ol>
            </p>
            <p>
                <me>
                    \begin{aligned}
                        5x + 9 \amp = -3x - 7 \\
                        5x \amp = -3x - 16 \amp \eqnspacer \amp \text{Subtract $9$ from both sides} \\
                        8x \amp = -16 \amp \amp \text{Add $3x$ to both sides} \\
                        x \amp = -2 \amp \amp \text{Divide both sides by $8$}
                    \end{aligned}
                </me>
            </p>
        </solution>
    </activity>
    
    
    <activity xml:id="sec-bap-1-ac3-common-problem">
        <title>A Common Presentation Problem</title>
        <aside>
            <p>
                You probably had a teacher teach you that this is the right way to write math. Unfortunately, they were
                wrong and you're going to need to unlearn it.
            </p>
        </aside>
        <p>
            There is a common way of writing equations that some people use which is less than ideal:
            <image xml:id="sec-bap-1-ac3-eq1" width="16%">
                <latex-image>
                    \begin{tikzpicture}
                        \draw (-0.7, 0) node[anchor=center] {$\strut 4x$};
                        \draw (-0.3, 0) node[anchor=center] {$\strut +$};
                        \draw (-0.0, 0) node[anchor=center] {$\strut 7$};
                        \draw (0.25, 0) node[anchor=center] {$\strut =$};
                        \draw (0.75, 0) node[anchor=center] {$\strut 19$};

                        \draw (-0.21, -0.4) node[anchor=center] {$\strut -7$};
                        \draw (0.7, -0.4) node[anchor=center] {$\strut -7$};

                        \draw (-1, -0.6) -- (1, -0.6);

                        \draw (-0.7, -0.85) node[anchor=center] {$\strut 4x$};
                        \draw (0.25, -0.85) node[anchor=center] {$\strut =$};
                        \draw (0.75, -0.85) node[anchor=center] {$\strut 12$};

                        \draw (-0.9, -1.05) -- (-0.5, -1.05);
                        \draw (-0.7, -1.05) node[anchor=north] {$4$};
                        \draw (0.6, -1.05) -- (0.95, -1.05);
                        \draw (0.775, -1.05) node[anchor=north] {$4$};
                        
                        \draw (0.3,-1.7) node[anchor=center] {$x=3$};
                    \end{tikzpicture}
                </latex-image>
            </image>
        </p>
        <aside>
            <p>
                A good explanation of an idea should not require the reader to have to guess about what happened. This
                means that the responsibility is on the writer to write clearly.
            </p>
        </aside>
        <p>
            There are a number of problems with this. To start, there's not really an organized way to read this. The
            best way to think of it is that it breaks apart into four pieces with three of them overlapping each other.
            Another problem is that the reader is expected to simply know what's happening. This is sometimes at the
            root of students' complaints about "skipped steps." 
            <image xml:id="sec-bap-1-ac3-eq1-explained" width="100%">
                <latex-image>
                    \begin{tikzpicture}
                        \begin{scope}[shift={(-6,0)}]
                            \draw (0,0.3) node[anchor=south] {\strut Original Problem};
                        
                            \draw (-0.7, 0) node[anchor=center] {$\strut 4x$};
                            \draw (-0.3, 0) node[anchor=center] {$\strut +$};
                            \draw (-0.0, 0) node[anchor=center] {$\strut 7$};
                            \draw (0.25, 0) node[anchor=center] {$\strut =$};
                            \draw (0.75, 0) node[anchor=center] {$\strut 19$};
                        \end{scope}

                        \begin{scope}[shift={(-2,0)}]
                            \draw (0,0.8) node[anchor=south] {\strut Subtract 7 to};
                            \draw (0,0.3) node[anchor=south] {\strut get a new equation};

                            \draw (-0.7, 0) node[anchor=center] {$\strut 4x$};
                            \draw (-0.3, 0) node[anchor=center] {$\strut +$};
                            \draw (-0.0, 0) node[anchor=center] {$\strut 7$};
                            \draw (0.25, 0) node[anchor=center] {$\strut =$};
                            \draw (0.75, 0) node[anchor=center] {$\strut 19$};
                        
                            \draw (-0.21, -0.4) node[anchor=center] {$\strut -7$};
                            \draw (0.7, -0.4) node[anchor=center] {$\strut -7$};
                        
                            \draw (-1, -0.6) -- (1, -0.6);
                        
                            \draw (-0.7, -0.85) node[anchor=center] {$\strut 4x$};
                            \draw (0.25, -0.85) node[anchor=center] {$\strut =$};
                            \draw (0.75, -0.85) node[anchor=center] {$\strut 12$};
                        \end{scope}
                        
                        \begin{scope}[shift={(2,0)}]
                            \draw (0,0.8) node[anchor=south] {\strut Divide the new};
                            \draw (0,0.3) node[anchor=south] {\strut equation by 4};

                            \draw (-0.7, -0.85) node[anchor=center] {$\strut 4x$};
                            \draw (0.25, -0.85) node[anchor=center] {$\strut =$};
                            \draw (0.75, -0.85) node[anchor=center] {$\strut 12$};

                            \draw (-0.9, -1.05) -- (-0.5, -1.05);
                            \draw (-0.7, -1.05) node[anchor=north] {$4$};
                            \draw (0.6, -1.05) -- (0.95, -1.05);
                            \draw (0.775, -1.05) node[anchor=north] {$4$};
                        \end{scope}
                        
                        \begin{scope}[shift={(5.5,0)}]
                            \draw (0,0.3) node[anchor=south] {\strut Final answer};
                            \draw (0.3,-1.7) node[anchor=center] {$x=3$};
                        \end{scope}
                    \end{tikzpicture}
                </latex-image>
            </image>
        </p>
        <aside>
            <p>
                This all makes sense as you're writing it out, and it's good to help you put your ideas together and get
                the overall picture of what's happening in a problem, but the final result isn't a carefully organized
                presentation. In writing courses, the equivalent work would be called a "rough draft."
            </p>
        </aside>
        <p>
            <alert xml:id="sec-bap-1-ac3-ti">Try it!</alert>
        </p>
        <p>
            Write the calculation in <xref ref="sec-bap-1-ac3-common-problem"/> using a complete presentation.
        </p>
        <solution>
            <p>
                <me>
                    \begin{aligned}
                        4x + 7 \amp = 19 \\
                        4x \amp = 12 \amp \eqnspacer \amp \text{Subtract $7$ from both sides} \\
                        x \amp = 3 \amp \amp \text{Divide both sides by $4$}
                    \end{aligned}
                </me>
            </p>
        </solution>
    </activity>
    
    
    <activity xml:id="sec-bap-1-ac4-describe-steps">
        <title>Describing the Steps</title>
        <aside>
            <p>
                Working with fractions is its own challenge for a lot of students. A lot of students have very little
                conceptual foundation for the fraction manipulations, and a lot of it is just brute force memorization.
                We'll try to enlighten fractions a bit later so that they really start to make sense.
            </p>
        </aside>
        <p>
            One other aspect of taking the time to carefully write what you're doing is that it causes you to think more
            clearly about what you're doing. Consider the following equation: <m>2x = \frac{1}{2}</m>. A fair number of
            students see this and think they should "cancel out" the 2 from both sides. This is not correct. There are
            times you can cancel out numbers if one of them is in the numerator and the other is in the denominator, but
            this isn't one of them.
        </p>
        <p>
            The act of explicitly stating what mathematical operation you're performing helps your brain to make
            categories of information. A more simple "error" of this type is that some students refer to all algebraic
            manipulations as "moving the term to the other side." Here are two examples of what that could mean to
            students:
            <image xml:id="sec-bap-1-ac4-good" width="60%">
                <latex-image>
                    \begin{tikzpicture}
                        \draw (-3, 0) node[anchor=center] {$\begin{aligned}
                            3x + 5 \amp = 14 \\
                            3x \amp = 9
                        \end{aligned}$};
                        \draw (3, 0) node[anchor=center] {$\begin{aligned}
                            3x - 7 \amp = 14 \\
                            3x \amp = 21
                        \end{aligned}$};
                    \end{tikzpicture}
                </latex-image>
            </image>
        </p>
        <aside>
            <p>
                We use <m>\overset{\times}{=}</m> to indicate that there was an algebraic error.
            </p>
        </aside>
        <p>
            Each of these is a different mathematical operation and a different algebraic step. It is not uncommon to
            see the following mistakes:
            <image xml:id="sec-bap-1-ac4-bad" width="60%">
                <latex-image>
                    \begin{tikzpicture}
                        \draw (-3, 0) node[anchor=center] {$\begin{aligned}
                            3x + 5 \amp = 14 \\
                            3x \amp \overset{\times}{=} 19
                        \end{aligned}$};
                        \draw (3, 0) node[anchor=center] {$\begin{aligned}
                            3x - 7 \amp = 14 \\
                            3x \amp \overset{\times}{=} 7
                        \end{aligned}$};
                    \end{tikzpicture}
                </latex-image>
            </image>
        </p>
        <aside>
            <p>
                Metacognition is the awareness of your own thinking. Many students lack this with mathematics, and are
                simply manipulating symbols on the page. By thinking about the algebraic steps you're executing, you
                give yourself better learning opportunities.
            </p>
        </aside>
        <p>
            Usually, when I ask students to state in words what they did, they're able to see their mistake for
            themselves. So the act of stating the mathematical operation in words allows students to avoid errors.
        </p>
        <p>
            <alert xml:id="sec-bap-1-ac4-ti">Try it!</alert>
        </p>
        <p>
            Solve the equations <m>3x + 5 = 14</m> and <m>3x - 7 = 14</m> using a complete presentation.
        </p>
        <solution>
            <p>
                <me>
                    \begin{aligned}
                        3x + 5 \amp = 14 \\
                        3x \amp = 9 \amp \eqnspacer \amp \text{Subtract $5$ from both sides} \\
                        x \amp = 3 \amp \amp \text{Divide both sides by $3$}
                    \end{aligned}
                </me>
                <me>
                    \begin{aligned}
                        3x - 7 \amp = 14 \\
                        3x \amp = 21 \amp \eqnspacer \amp \text{Add $7$ to both sides} \\
                        x \amp = 7 \amp \amp \text{Divide both sides by $3$}
                    \end{aligned}
                </me>
            </p>
        </solution>
    </activity>
    
    
    <p>
        You will not always need to use a complete presentation. There are many times when it is tedious and unnecessary
        to state what is happening at every single algebraic step. This becomes more and more true as your basic algebra
        gets stronger and stronger. What ends up happening is that the steps that need to be described become less about
        the small details and more about the big picture. When solving for <m>x</m>, it may be enough to say, "Apply the
        quadratic formula" and not have to explain all of the individual arithmetic steps.
    </p>
    <p>
        That being said, it is very important to develop the habit of keeping your equal signs lined up when writing
        math. If there is any one writing habit you develop from these worksheets, it should be that one. This one
        change by itself does a lot of things for you that you may not be consciously aware of.
    </p>
</section>