<section xml:id="sec-ref1-1-main">
    <title>A Pause for Reflection</title>

    <p>
        Congratulations! You have just completed the "main trunk" of the course. The algebraic skills that we have
        been discussing are the foundation of college level mathematics. But that doesn't mean that there's nothing more
        to learn. Mathematical knowledge is deeply scaffolded. And weaknesses in the lower level can manifest in an
        unstable understanding down the line. What we have done up to this point is attempt to plug the biggest holes as
        fast as possible so that you can move forward in your college level math courses. It's really just a patchwork
        job that tries to get you to a place where you have a decent chance of being successful at that college level
        coursework.
    </p>
    <aside>
        <p>
            When we say that knowledge is scaffolded, we mean that new ideas are built on top of old ones.
        </p>
    </aside>
    <p>
        The sections that follow are going to be focused on getting deeper into the foundation in search of filling the
        cracks that lie beneath the surface. As we follow the different "branches" of mathematical thinking, the hope
        is that you will come to a new and deeper understanding of ideas that you have seen for years. Some of these
        ideas may help feed directly into your college level work, but other things may simply be about uncovering a new
        perspective of mathematics.
    </p>
    <aside>
        <p>
            These are the branches:
            <ul>
                <li>
                    The coordinate plane and linear equations
                </li>
                <li>
                    Fractions and decimals
                </li>
                <li>
                    Arithmetic
                </li>
                <li>
                    Applications
                </li>
            </ul>
        </p>
    </aside>
    <p>
        As we have been emphasizing throughout this text, there is more to math than just executing calculations. Yes,
        that's a part of it, but there's an element of communicating and understanding the ideas and a curiosity for how
        ideas fit together. Ultimately, this is all about building a mindset towards mathematical thinking that is
        robust enough to help you be successful at whatever you do. One of the reasons that mathematical skills are so
        highly valued is not because there aren't a lot of people who can do the raw manipulations (we have computers to
        do that for us), but it's because there aren't a lot of people who can meaningfully interpret that information
        and apply it to new situations.
    </p>
    <aside>
        <p>
            Metacognition is the understanding and awareness of your own thinking.
        </p>
    </aside>
    <p>
        For these reasons, it's important to take a pause every now and then and think about what's happening beyond
        just the calculations and think about what's happening to your mindset as you've been working your way through
        the content.
    </p>
    <p>
        In this portion of the course, we have covered the following topics:
        <ul>
            <li>
                Basic Algebraic Presentation
            </li>
            <li>
                Variables in Expressions and Equations
            </li>
            <li>
                Like and Unlike Terms
            </li>
            <li>
                Simplifying Expressions and Solving Equations
            </li>
            <li>
                Variables and Substitutions
            </li>
            <li>
                The Properties of Exponents
            </li>
            <li>
                Products of Polynomials
            </li>
            <li>
                Common Factors
            </li>
            <li>
                Factoring Quadratic Polynomials
            </li>
            <li>
                Reading Mathematical Expressions
            </li>
        </ul>
    </p>
</section>