<section xml:id="sec-lult-1-main">
    <title>One of These Things is Not Like the Other</title>

    <objectives>
        <ul>
            <li>
                <p>
                    Identify the coefficient and variable part of a monomial.
                </p>
            </li>
            <li>
                <p>
                    Identify the monomials of a polynomial.
                </p>
            </li>
            <li>
                <p>
                    Determine whether terms in a mathematical expression are like terms or unlike terms.
                </p>
            </li>
            <li>
                <p>
                    Simplify expressions by combining like terms.
                </p>
            </li>
        </ul>
    </objectives>

    <p>
        The concept of combining like terms is not that different from the way we naturally organize information in our
        heads. Consider the following question: If you have one bag that contains two apples and three oranges and you
        had a second bag that has four apples and one orange, how many of each fruit do you have?
    </p>
    <aside>
        <p>
            Did you think about the question before moving on? Or did you just keep on reading without stopping? When
            books ask you a question like this, the hope is that you would think about it for yourself because that
            helps you to understand the ideas better.
        </p>
    </aside>
    <p>
        It should only take a moment's thought to conclude that you have six apples and four oranges. We can write this
        out in a mathematical notation as follows:
        <me>
            ( 2 \text{ apples} + 3 \text{ oranges} ) + (4 \text{ apples} + 1 \text{ orange}) = 6 \text{ apples} + 4 \text{ oranges}
        </me>
        There's a lot to say here about the notation:
    </p>
    <ul>
        <li>
            <aside>
                <p>
                    Parentheses are called "grouping symbols" because they group different types of objects together.
                </p>
            </aside>
            <p>
                Notice how the parentheses serve as natural boundary markers for each bag. By looking at the
                mathematical notation, you know exactly what's contained in the first bag and what's contained in the
                second bag.
            </p>
        </li>
        <li>
            <p>
                Notice how the addition sign corresponds to your intuition about addition. You can rearrange things so
                that the first set of apples are with the other set of apples, and the same thing with the oranges.
            </p>
        </li>
        <li>
            <aside>
                <p>
                    You can conclude that there are 10 pieces of fruit, but that doesn't answer the question.
                </p>
            </aside>
            <p>
                Notice how you have no impulse to try to combine the apples and oranges together to get
                "10 apple-oranges" as your final answer.
            </p>
        </li>
    </ul>
    <aside>
        <p>
            A shorter example of this is that one apple and one tree does not give you two apple trees. But that
            doesn't let us explore the notation as much.
        </p>
    </aside>
    <p>
        This simple word problem serves as an illustration for how we think about combining like terms. It's easier for
        us to see what's going on here because we have some experience handling pieces of fruit and we can easily
        recognize that one type of fruit is different from the other. The same concept applies to algebraic expressions,
        but we first need to make sure we know what we're looking at.
    </p>
    <definition xml:id="def-monomial-coefficient-variable-part">
        <title>Monomial, Coefficient, Variable Part</title>
        <idx><h>monomial</h></idx>
        <idx><h>coefficient</h></idx>
        <idx><h>variable part</h></idx>
        <statement>
            <p>
                A <term>monomial</term> is any product of numbers and variables. The <term>coefficient</term> is the
                product of all of the numbers and the <term>variable part</term> is the product of all the variables.
            </p>
        </statement>
    </definition>
    <p>
        Although it's possible for us to write a monomial as <m>3 \cdot x \cdot x \cdot x \cdot x \cdot y \cdot y</m>,
        we usually take advantage of exponent notation to write it as <m>3x^4 y^2</m> to keep things compact. This also
        makes it much easier to read. In this example, the coefficient is 3 and the variable part is <m>x^4 y^2</m>.
    </p>
    <aside>
        <p>
            <idx><h>degree</h></idx>
            The <term>degree</term> of a monomial is the number of variables in the product when we write it out in
            the expanded form. So <m>3x^4 y^2</m> has degree 6.
        </p>
    </aside>
    <p>
        There are a couple special situations to remember:
        <ul>
            <li>
                <p>
                    <idx><h>constant</h></idx>
                    If you have a number by itself (such as the number 12), the term is called a <term>constant</term>
                    and it is considered to have no variable part.
                </p>
            </li>
            <li>
                <aside>
                    <p>
                        Mathematicians prefer an economy of notation, so symbols like that are dropped when they're
                        easily understood.
                    </p>
                </aside>
                <p>
                    If you have a variable by itself (such as with <m>x</m> or <m>y^2</m>), the coefficient is
                    implicitly a 1. So it would be correct to think of <m>x</m> as <m>1x</m> and <m>y^2</m> as
                    <m>1y^2</m>.
                </p>
            </li>
        </ul>
    </p>
    <definition xml:id="def-polynomial">
        <title>Polynomial</title>
        
        <idx><h>polynomial</h></idx>
        
        <statement>
            <aside>
                <p>
                    We allow for monomial by itself to be a polynomial because it would be annoying if we didn't. The
                    use of an inclusive terminology greatly simplifies things for us.
                </p>
            </aside>
            <p>
                A <term>polynomial</term> is the sum of a number of monomials.
            </p>
        </statement>
    </definition>
    <p>
        The definition says that a polynomial is a sum of monomials, not a difference of them. But we will often write
        polynomials with subtraction, such as with <m>x^2 - 6x + 8</m>. The reason for this is that we can use the idea
        that subtraction is addition of the opposite to rewrite it:
        <me>
            x^2 - 6x + 8 = x^2 + (-6x) + 8
        </me>
        One of the features of writing subtraction as addition is that it visually groups the negative sign with the
        monomial. This means that when we identify the coefficient of a monomial term, we need to account for the
        negative sign. Therefore, the coefficient of the <m>x</m> term is -6.
    </p>
    <activity xml:id="sec-lult-1-ac1-identifying-monomial-parts">
        <title>Identifying Parts of Monomials</title>
        <aside>
            <p>
                The entire book is structured with this perspective in mind.
            </p>
        </aside>
        <p>
            Understanding vocabulary is a multi-step process. It's not enough to just read the definitions and see a
            couple examples. In order for the definition to sink in effectively, you must take the time to work o
             problems yourself.
        </p>
        <aside>
            <p>
                For terms with no variable part, writing NA in the box is good enough. Make sure you pay attention to
                the subtraction symbols and negative signs.
            </p>
        </aside>
        <p>
            <alert xml:id="sec-lult-1-ac1-ti">Try it!</alert>
        </p>
        <p>
            Using the grid below, identify all of the monomials of <m>x^2 + 7x - y - 8</m>. Then determine the
            coefficient and variable part of each term.
            <tabular top="medium" left="medium">
                <row bottom="medium">
                    <cell left="medium" right="medium">
                        Monomial
                    </cell>
                    <cell right="medium">
                        <m>\qquad</m>
                    </cell>
                    <cell right="medium">
                        <m>\qquad</m>
                    </cell>
                    <cell right="medium">
                        <m>\qquad</m>
                    </cell>
                    <cell right="medium">
                        <m>\qquad</m>
                    </cell>
                </row>
                <row bottom="medium">
                    <cell left="medium" right="medium">
                        Coefficient
                    </cell>
                    <cell right="medium">
                    </cell>
                    <cell right="medium">
                    </cell>
                    <cell right="medium">
                    </cell>
                    <cell right="medium">
                    </cell>
                </row>
                <row bottom="medium">
                    <cell left="medium" right="medium">
                        Variable Part
                    </cell>
                    <cell right="medium">
                    </cell>
                    <cell right="medium">
                    </cell>
                    <cell right="medium">
                    </cell>
                    <cell right="medium">
                    </cell>
                </row>
            </tabular>
        </p>
        <solution>
            <p>
                <tabular top="medium" left="medium">
                    <row bottom="medium">
                        <cell left="medium" right="medium">
                            Monomial
                        </cell>
                        <cell right="medium">
                            <m>x^2</m>
                        </cell>
                        <cell right="medium">
                            <m>7x</m>
                        </cell>
                        <cell right="medium">
                            <m>-y</m>
                        </cell>
                        <cell right="medium">
                            <m>-8</m>
                        </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row bottom="medium">
                        <cell left="medium" right="medium">
                            Coefficient
                        </cell>
                        <cell right="medium">
                            <m>1</m>
                        </cell>
                        <cell right="medium">
                            <m>7</m>
                        </cell>
                        <cell right="medium">
                            <m>-1</m>
                        </cell>
                        <cell right="medium">
                            <m>-8</m>
                        </cell>
                    </row>
                    <row bottom="medium">
                        <cell left="medium" right="medium">
                            Variable Part
                        </cell>
                        <cell right="medium">
                            <m>x^2</m>
                        </cell>
                        <cell right="medium">
                            <m>x</m>
                        </cell>
                        <cell right="medium">
                            <m>y</m>
                        </cell>
                        <cell right="medium">
                            NA
                        </cell>
                    </row>
                </tabular>
            </p>
        </solution>
    </activity>

    <definition xml:id="def-like-unlike-terms">
        <title>Like and Unlike Terms</title>
        <idx><h>like terms</h></idx>
        <idx><h>unlike terms</h></idx>
        
        <statement>
            <p>
                Two monomials are <term>like terms</term> if they have the same variable part. If their variable parts
                are different, then they are <term>unlike terms</term>.
            </p>
        </statement>
    </definition>

    <activity xml:id="sec-lult-1-ac2-combining-like-terms">
        <title>Combining Like Terms</title>
        <p>
            Combining like terms is an algebraic process that uses the distributive property, but it's backwards from
            how it's most commonly seen. This reverse distributive property is often called "factoring out" terms. When
            we have like terms, we can perform the arithmetic on the coefficients to simplify the expression.
            <me>
                \begin{aligned}
                    5x + 8x \amp = (5 + 8)x \amp \eqnspacer \amp \text{Factor out the $x$} \\
                        \amp = 13x \amp \amp \text{Arithmetic}
                \end{aligned}
            </me>
        </p>
        <aside>
            <p>
                Notice that the presentation follows the same general scheme as before. The equal signs are lined up and
                the explanation is on the right.
            </p>
        </aside>
        <p>
            Notice how natural this is based on the logic of combining either the apples or the oranges. If you have 5
            <m>x</m>-es and you add 8 more <m>x</m>-es, how many <m>x</m>-es do you have? 13 <m>x</m>-es.
        </p>
        <p>
            <alert xml:id="sec-lult-1-ac2-ti">Try it!</alert>
        </p>
        <p>
            Simplify the expression <m>7y^2 + 6y^2 - 5y^2</m> using a complete presentation. Show the step where you
            factor out the common factor.
        </p>
        <aside>
            <p>
                There's no example with three terms, but you can figure it out. Trust yourself!
            </p>
        </aside>
        <solution>
            <p>
                <me>
                    \begin{aligned}
                        7y^2 + 6y^2 - 5y^2 \amp = (7 + 6 - 5) y^2 \amp \eqnspacer \amp \text{Factor out the $y^2$} \\
                          \amp = 8y^2 \amp \amp \text{Arithmetic}
                    \end{aligned}
                </me>
            </p>
        </solution>
    </activity>

    <activity xml:id="sec-lult-1-ac3-combining-with-unlike-terms">
        <title>Combining Like Terms When Unlike Terms are Present</title>
        <p>
            What happens if there are unlike terms? Once again, we can think about the apples and oranges. Basically,
            we're just stuck with what we have. We've actually been using this already. In previous sections, if we had
            an expression like <m>4x + 3</m>, we just left it like that. And this was also true in the previous section
            where the different variables were all left separate.
        </p>
        <p>
            But what if there are some terms are like terms and others are unlike terms? Think back to the apples and
            oranges. What happened there? In that case, the apples were combined and the oranges were combined, but the
            fruits remained separate. We do the same thing in algebra.
            <me>
                \begin{aligned}
                    (5x - 3y) + (4x + y) \amp = 5x + 4x - 3y + y \amp \eqnspacer \amp \text{Rearrange the terms} \\
                        \amp = (5x + 4x) + ( - 3y + y) \amp \amp \text{Group the terms} \\
                        \amp = (5 + 4)x + (-3 + 1)y \amp \amp \text{Factor out the $x$ and $y$} \\
                        \amp = 9x - 2y \amp \amp \text{Arithmetic}
                \end{aligned}
            </me>
        </p>
        <aside>
            <p>
                The grouping step is the dangerous step. Be careful to keep the negative sign with the appropriate term!
            </p>
            <p>
                We normally don't show the factoring step. We're just doing here for emphasis.
            </p>
        </aside>
        <p>
            Students are sometimes not very careful with parentheses. They often write the wrong thing even if what's
            in their head is correct. Remember that the correct communication of ideas is important in math, so it's not
            good enough to write the wrong thing and pretend that it's correct. Here are two very common errors that
            students make:
            <me>
                \begin{aligned}
                    5x + 4x - 3y + y \amp \overset{\times}{=} (5x + 4x)(-3y + y) \\
                    5x + 4x - 3y + y \amp \overset{\times}{=} (5x + 4x) - (3y + y)                
                \end{aligned}
            </me>
        </p>
        <aside>
            <p>
                When parentheses are next to each other like on the first line, we call it "implied multiplication."
            </p>
        </aside>
        <p>
            The first one happens when students simply draw parentheses around symbols without thinking about how it
            affects the meaning. Notice that the right side is a product of terms because the parentheses are right
            next to each other. The second one happens when students don't pay attention to the fact that the negative
            sign is part of the coefficient of the <m>-3y</m> term. These errors are avoidable with practice. But it
            takes practice because you need to train you brain to see the expressions differently.
        </p>
        <p>
            <alert xml:id="sec-lult-1-ac3-ti">Try it!</alert>
        </p>
        <p>
            Simplify the expression <m>(-4a - 3b) + (-5a + 8b)</m> using a complete presentation. Show all the steps
            that are in the example above.
        </p>
        <aside>
            <p>
                Remember that the negative sign stays with the term!
            </p>
        </aside>
        <solution>
            <p>
                <me>
                    \begin{aligned}
                        (-4a - 3b) + (-5a + 8b) \amp = -4a - 5a - 3b + 8b \amp \eqnspacer \amp \text{Rearrange the terms} \\
                            \amp = (-4a - 5a) + (-3b + 8b) \amp \amp \text{Group the terms} \\
                            \amp = (-4 - 5)a + (-3 + 8)b \amp \amp \text{Factor out the $a$ and the $b$} \\
                            \amp = -9a + 5b \amp \amp \text{Arithmetic}
                    \end{aligned}
                </me>
            </p>
        </solution>
    </activity>

    <p>
        So far, when we have combined like terms, we've been focusing on addition. But we also need to be able to do
        this with mathematical expressions that have subtraction and multiplication. For each of these, we need to
        remember to use the distributive property.
    </p>
    <p>
        The idea behind this one comes from the concept of multiplication representing groups of things. If you have four
        bags that each contain two apples and three oranges, how much fruit do you have in total?
    </p>
    <aside>
        <p>
            We have used the multiplication dot to emphasize the multiplication.
        </p>
    </aside>
    <p>
        <me>
            4 \cdot (2 \text{ apples} + 3 \text{ oranges} ) = 8 \text{ apples} + 12 \text{ oranges}
        </me>
    </p>
    <p>
        This is a demonstration of an important property of algebra.
    </p>

    <definition xml:id="def-distributive-property">
        <title>The Distributive Property</title>
        <idx><h>distributive property</h></idx>

        <statement>
            <p>
                The <term>distributive property</term> states that <m>a(b + c) = ab + ac</m>. The full name of this the
                <term>distributive property of multiplication over addition</term>.
            </p>
        </statement>
    </definition>

    <activity xml:id="sec-lult-1-ac4-using-the-distributive-property">
        <title>Using the Distributive Property</title>
        <aside>
            <p>
                The distributive property is a multiplication operation and combining like terms is an addition and
                subtraction operation.
            </p>
        </aside>
        <p>
            You might recall that in the order of operations, multiplication comes before addition and subtraction. This
            means that you should use the distributive property before you combine like terms.
            <me>
                \begin{aligned}
                    (2x - 5y) + 3(x - 2y) \amp = (2x - 5y) + (3x - 6y) \amp \eqnspacer \amp \text{Distributive property} \\
                        \amp = 2x + 3x - 5y - 6y \amp \amp \text{Rearrange the terms} \\
                        \amp = (2x + 3x) + (- 5y - 6y) \amp \amp \text{Group the terms} \\
                        \amp = (2+3)x + (-5 - 6)y \amp \amp \text{Factor out the $x$ and the $y$} \\
                        \amp = 5x - 11y \amp \amp \text{Arithmetic}
                \end{aligned}
            </me>
        </p>
        <p>
            <alert xml:id="sec-lult-1-ac4-ti">Try it!</alert>
        </p>
        <p>
            Simplify the expression <m>(3a + 2b) + 2(5a - 3b)</m> using a complete presentation. Show the distributive
            step, the rearrangement step, the grouping step, and the arithmetic step.
        </p>
        <solution>
            <p>
                <me>
                    \begin{aligned}
                        (3a + 2b) + 2(5a - 3b) \amp = (3a + 2b) + (10a - 6b) \amp \eqnspacer \amp \text{Distributive property} \\
                        \amp = 3a + 10a + 2b - 6b \amp \amp \text{Rearrange the terms} \\
                        \amp = (3a + 10a) + (2b - 6b) \amp \amp \text{Group the terms} \\
                        \amp = (3 + 10)a + (2 - 6)b \amp \amp \text{Factor out the $a$ and $b$} \\
                        \amp = 13a - 4b \amp \amp \text{Arithmetic}
                    \end{aligned}
                </me>
            </p>
        </solution>
    </activity>
    <activity xml:id="sec-lult-1-ac5-distributing-negative-signs">
        <title>The Distributive Property With Subtraction</title>
        <p>
            Whenever we have an algebraic symbol next to a set of parentheses with multiple terms on the inside, we need
            to use the distributive property. When we were doing it earlier with addition, we basically just multiplied
            by 1, which is why there was no change. If the operation outside of the parentheses is subtraction, then we
            also need to distribute that negative sign.
        </p>
        <aside>
            <p>
                Remember that multiplying by 1 does not change the value.
            </p>
        </aside>
        <p>
            To understand why the negative sign should be distributed, we will think about another example using apples
            and oranges. Suppose you have eight apples and six oranges, and someone takes four apples and five oranges
            away from you. How much fruit do you have left?
            <me>
                (8 \text{ apples} + 6 \text{ oranges}) - (4 \text{ apples} + 5 \text{ oranges})
                = 4 \text{ apples} + 1 \text{ orange}
            </me>
        </p>
        <p>
            Notice that in context, it is completely natural to remember to subtract off the 5 oranges from the 6
            oranges. However, when manipulating symbols that context is easily lost, which leads to errors like this
            one:
            <me>
                (8x + 6y) - (4x + 5y) \overset{\times}{=} 8x + 6y - 4x + 5y
            </me>
        </p>
        <aside>
            <p>
                This is an <em>extremely</em> common error!

            </p>
        </aside>
        <p>
            <alert xml:id="sec-lult-1-ac5-ti">Try it!</alert>
        </p>
        <p>
            Simplify the expression <m>(8x + 6y) - (4x + 5y)</m> using a complete presentation. Show the distributive
            step, the rearrangement step, the grouping step, and the arithmetic step.
        </p>
        <aside>
            <p>
                Notice how these words match up with the presentation in the previous example. Language is important in
                mathematics because it helps us to communicate our ideas precisely.
            </p>
        </aside>
        <solution>
            <p>
                <me>
                    \begin{aligned}
                        (8x + 6y) - (4x + 5y) \amp = 8x + 6y - 4x - 5y \amp \eqnspacer \amp \text{Distributive property} \\
                        \amp = 8x - 4x + 6y - 5y \amp \amp \text{Rearrange the terms} \\
                        \amp = (8x - 4x) + (6y - 5y) \amp \amp \text{Group the terms} \\
                        \amp = (8-4)x + (6-5)y \amp \amp \text{Factor out the $x$ and the $y$} \\
                        \amp = 4x + y \amp \amp \text{Arithmetic}
                    \end{aligned}
                </me>
            </p>
            <aside>
                <p>
                    You can write your final result as <m>4x + 1y</m> if you want, but you will almost always see that
                    written with the implicit coefficient.
                </p>
            </aside>
        </solution>
    </activity>

</section>