<section xml:id="sec-cic-5-deeper">
	<title>Going Deeper: Mental Arithmetic</title>
	<p>
		For many students, mental arithmetic usually feels quite complicated and can be extremely frustrating. One of
		the big challenges for mental arithmetic is that most people try to do mental arithmetic the way they do
		arithmetic on paper. Unfortunately, this is both extremely inefficient and unnecessarily difficult. The primary
		reason has to do with how the paper method relies on being able to write down a digit to remember it later, but
		our brains simply cannot do that. 
	</p>
	<p>
		To get a sense of just how central that memory is, we're going to work through adding three three-digit numbers
		together, and we're going to put a box around every number that appears in the process:
		<me>
			\begin{array}{r}
				387 \\
				236 \\
				+ 523 \\
				\hline
			\end{array}
		</me> 
		<ul>
			<li>
				<p>
					Ones digit: <m>\boxed{7}</m> plus <m>\boxed{6}</m> is <m>\boxed{13}</m>, plus <m>\boxed{3}</m> more
					is <m>\boxed{16}</m>. Write the <m>\boxed{6}</m> below and carry the <m>\boxed{1}</m>.
				</p>
			</li>
			<li>
				<p>
					Tens digit: <m>\boxed{1}</m> plus <m>\boxed{8}</m> is <m>\boxed{9}</m>, plus <m>\boxed{3}</m> more
					is <m>\boxed{12}</m>, plus <m>\boxed{2}</m> more is <m>\boxed{14}</m>. Write the <m>\boxed{4}</m>
					below and carry the <m>\boxed{1}</m>.
				</p>
			</li>
			<li>
				<p>
					Hundreds digit: <m>\boxed{1}</m> plus <m>\boxed{3}</m> is <m>\boxed{4}</m>, plus <m>\boxed{2}</m>
					more is <m>\boxed{6}</m>, plus <m>\boxed{5}</m> more is <m>\boxed{11}</m>. Write down these digits
					to get the final result.
				</p>
			</li>
		</ul>
	</p>
	<p>
		Let's make a list of all the digits that appeared in the process, keeping track of the order in which they
		appeared:
		<me>
			\boxed{7} \, \boxed{6} \, \boxed{13} \, \boxed{3} \, \boxed{16} \, \boxed{6} \, \boxed{1} \, \boxed{1} \,
			\boxed{8} \, \boxed{9} \, \boxed{3} \, \boxed{12} \, \boxed{2}\, \boxed{14} \, \boxed{4} \, \boxed{1} \,
			\boxed{1} \, \boxed{3} \, \boxed{4} \, \boxed{2} \, \boxed{6} \, \boxed{5} \, \boxed{11}
		</me>
		When you look at this string of numbers, the critical observation to make is that the actual answer to the
		calculation does not appear anywhere. In fact, when you look at the numbers, you may have a hard time even
		finding the digits that make up the answer. We'll indicate those values with an arrow:
		<me>
			\boxed{7} \, \boxed{6} \, \boxed{13} \, \boxed{3} \, \boxed{16} \, \underset{\big\uparrow}{\boxed{6}} \,
			\boxed{1} \, \boxed{1} \, \boxed{8} \, \boxed{9} \, \boxed{3} \, \boxed{12} \, \boxed{2}\, \boxed{14} \,
			\underset{\big\uparrow}{\boxed{4}} \, \boxed{1} \, \boxed{1} \, \boxed{3} \, \boxed{4} \, \boxed{2} \,
			\boxed{6} \, \boxed{5} \, \underset{\big\uparrow}{\boxed{11}}
		</me>
		Now that they've been marked, notice how many numbers appear in between them. These digits are numbers that
		you're trying to hold in memory while all the other numbers are going through your head. Between the 6 for the
		ones digit and the 11 for the hundreds and thousands digit in the last step, there are 16 numbers in between,
		and one of those other numbers is one you were supposed to have memorized. 
	</p>
	<aside>
		<p>
			There is a technique of converting the digits into letters that you convert into a word to help remember
			them. The idea is that it's easier for your brain to hold a word in memory while it processes numbers rather
			than holding a number in memory while processing numbers. But that technique requires additional types of
			practice and memory training. 
		</p>
	</aside>
	<p>
		When following this algorithm on paper, our brains are allowed to forget those digits because they're written
		down. But when we do this mentally, we have to try to keep those numbers in memory while other digits are being
		processed. While it helps to have reached a level of automaticity so that you're less consciously doing those
		computations, it's still quite challenging for most people. 
	</p>
	<p>
		The standard addition algorithm uses a digit manipulation scheme. What this means is that we're looking at each
		digit as its own object. In the calculation, the number 387 is never used as a number. It's broken down into
		three separate pieces:3, 8, and 7. This causes extra strain on our brains when handing it because it requires
		more brain power to think about three separate objects rather than thinking about one. 
	</p>
	<p>
		The big transition that makes mental arithmetic easier is to reorganize the calculation so that we don't have to
		remember numbers for as long. The representations of arithmetic on the number that we developed a few sections
		ago are a big towards that end. Here is how we're going to translate the process:
		<me>
			\begin{array}{r}
				387 \\
				236 \\
				+ 523 \\
				\hline
			\end{array} \quad \longrightarrow \quad
			\begin{array}{l}
				387 \\
				+ 200 + 30 + 6 \\
				+ 500 + 20 + 3 =
			\end{array}
		</me> 
	</p>
	<p>
		Here is how we're going to work through it: 
		<ul>
			<li>
				<p>
					Add the first two numbers: <m>\boxed{387}</m> plus <m>\boxed{200}</m> is <m>\boxed{587}</m>, plus
					<m>\boxed{30}</m> more is <m>\boxed{617}</m>, plus <m>\boxed{6}</m> more is <m>\boxed{623}</m>.
				</p>
			</li>
			<li>
				<p>
					Add the next number: <m>\boxed{623}</m> plus <m>\boxed{500}</m> is <m>\boxed{1123}</m>, plus
					<m>\boxed{20}</m> more is <m>\boxed{1143}</m>, plus <m>\boxed{3}</m> more is <m>\boxed{1146}</m>.
				</p>
			</li>
		</ul>
	</p>
	<p>
		This is how those numbers look written in order:
		<me>
			\boxed{387} \, \boxed{200} \, \boxed{587} \, \boxed{30} \, \boxed{617} \, \boxed{6} \, \boxed{623} \,
			\boxed{623} \, \boxed{500} \, \boxed{1123} \, \boxed{20} \, \boxed{1143} \, \boxed{3} \, \boxed{1146}
		</me>
		Let's make some observations about this:
		<ul>
			<li>
				<p>
					The total number of boxed values is significantly lower. There were 23 in the first method and only
					14 in the second method. 
				</p>
			</li>
			<li>
				<p>
					However, the numbers that we were working with are also significantly larger. In the first method,
					we only needed to be comfortable with small addition calculations, whereas the second method
					requires a level of fluency with adding in different place values. 
				</p>
			</li>
			<li>
				<p>
					The new approach does not require any long term memory, and the final number is the complete final
					answer. In fact, the process is basically just keeping a running total as you work your way through,
					so that you only really have to remember keep three numbers in your head at any time (the previous
					total, the number you're adding, and the new total). 
				</p>
			</li>
		</ul>
	</p>
	<p>
		As with most things mathematical, this should not be seen as a "rule" for how you're "supposed to" do mental
		arithmetic. It turns out that people who are good at mental arithmetic employ a number of different techniques
		based on patterns that they identify as being familiar. It's not necessary to always go in the same order every
		time, especially if there are patterns that make more intuitive sense. 
	</p>
	<p>
		For example, in this calculation, you might notice that <m>300 + 200 + 500 = 1000</m>. This is a number that you
		can put into memory (with a little bit of practice) because it's a "nice" number. And then you would only need
		to add three two-digit numbers together instead. You might also notice that <m>387 + 3 = 390</m>, which also
		brings you to a nice number. Then you can add in the hundreds and tens digits, leaving the final 6 for the very
		last step. 
	</p>
	<p>
		You could also use other groupings if they make sense. For example, you might see
		<me>
			387 + 236 = 387 + 13 + 223 = 400 + 223 = 523
		</me>
		and do that faster than you would do
		<me>
			387 + 200 + 30 + 6 = 587 + 30 + 6 = 617 + 6 = 623.
		</me> 
	</p>
	<p>
		The main point is that mathematics favors those who are flexible in their thinking instead of being rigid.
		Throughout this book, we've emphasized just how restraining a rule-based approach to mathematics can be, and
		this thread follows all the way back to the ways that you've learned your basic arithmetic. Hopefully, as you've
		been working your way through this book, you've started to move away from those things and have started to build
		a deeper understanding of mathematics.
	</p>
</section>
