<section xml:id="sec-sese-4-closing">
	<title>Closing Ideas</title>
	<p>
		We spent a lot of time in this section discussing how mathematics is presented. One of the main challenges of
		this is that there are no formal rules that tell you how much or how little writing is required. How much work
		you show depends on the audience that will be reading the work. 
	</p>
	<p>
		Let's take another look at the example from the worksheet of the very long presentation: 
		<me>
			\begin{aligned}
				7x \amp = x + 24 \\
				7x - x \amp = x + 24 - x \amp \eqnspacer \amp \text{Subtract $x$ from both sides} \\
				7x - x \amp = x - x + 24 \amp \amp \text{Rearrange the terms} \\
				7x - x \amp = (x - x) + 24 \amp \amp \text{Group the terms} \\
				(7 - 1)x \amp = (1 - 1)x + 24 \amp \amp \text{Factor out the $x$} \\
				6x \amp = 0x + 24 \amp \amp \text{Arithmetic} \\
				6x \amp = 24 \amp \amp \text{Simplify} \\
				\frac{6x}{6} \amp = \frac{24}{6} \amp \amp \text{Divide both sides by $6$} \\
				x \amp = 4 \amp \amp \text{Arithmetic} 
			\end{aligned}
		</me>
		As was noted in that problem, there is nothing wrong with the algebra in this presentation. And if someone asked
		you to show all of the work, this is what it would look like. But in practice, we would never do this. Why?
		Because in the context of solving an equation, it's natural to assume that the reader already understands how to
		combine like terms. The focus of the problem is on the steps needed to solve the equation, and not the steps
		required to combine like terms. 
	</p>
	<aside>
		<p>
			In some situations, it is customary not to show any of the algebra! 
		</p>
	</aside>
	<p>
		A more normal level of presentation for that problem would be something like this: 
		<me>
			\begin{aligned}
				7x \amp = x + 24 \\
				6x \amp = 24 \amp \eqnspacer \amp \text{Subtract $x$ from both sides} \\
				x \amp = 4 \amp \amp \text{Divide both sides by $6$} 
			\end{aligned}
		</me>
		Notice how each step in the presentation is focused on the actual steps of solving the equation, and all the
		little steps are not shown. This is because the presentation is being tailored to match the goal of the problem. 
	</p>
	<p>
		Reading the instructions of a problem should give you a sense of what the problem is asking you to do, and from
		that information you can also make decisions about what steps are important and which ones are less so. 
	</p>
</section>
