<section xml:id="sec-vee-1-main">
    <title>Letters are Numbers in Disguise</title>

    <objectives>
        <ul>
            <li>
                <p>
                    Substitute a number for a variable and then simplify the expression.
                </p>
            </li>
            <li>
                <p>
                    Manipulate linear equations with multiple variables.
                </p>
            </li>
        </ul>
    </objectives>

    <aside>
        <p>
            In broader contexts, variables are viewed in different ways. In computer programming, variables are
            containers for information. In higher level math courses, variables are sometimes used for abstract
            mathematical objects. The way we are using it here is consistent with both perspectives.
        </p>
    </aside>
    <p>
        Some people like to say that math made sense when it was all numbers, but then things fell apart when the
        letters started showing up. This is unfortunate, because the letters are actually just a way of representing
        numbers, and thinking about them in that way can help to clarify confusion. There are a lot of ways that
        teachers talk about variables and they are of varying degrees of correctness. For example, some teachers
        say that variables represent unknown values. It's not exactly wrong, but it's not exactly right. Whether or not
        we know the value is irrelevant. In college level math courses, we can use variables to represent mathematical
        expressions with other variables in it instead of just thinking of it as a quantity. This leads us to a more
        general definition:
    </p>
    <definition xml:id="def-variable">
        <title>Variable</title>
        <idx><h>variable</h></idx>
        <statement>
            <p>
                A <term>variable</term> is a symbol that represents a quantity or a mathematical expression.
            </p>
        </statement>
    </definition>
    <aside>
        <p>
            Mathematicians love to have good definitions. They help us to think about our ideas with very high levels of
            precision.
        </p>
    </aside>
    <p>
        Notice that we allow for variables to represent both quantities and mathematical expressions. What this means is
        that both <m>x = 4</m> and <m>x = y + 1</m> are valid uses of variables.
    </p>

    <activity xml:id="sec-vee-1-ac1-quantity">
        <title>Variables as Quantities in Expressions</title>
        <idx><h>if-then</h></idx>
        <p>
            What does it mean for a variable to represent a quantity in an expression? One way to think about it is that
            it's a calculation waiting to happen. Consider the expression <m>2x</m>. This represents a number, but which
            number it represents depends on the value of <m>x</m>. As soon as I give you a value for <m>x</m>, you can
            plug it in and give me a specific number. But until then, this is just a number that is waiting to be
            calculated. For example, if you know that <m>x = 4</m>, then you can calculate that <m>2x = 8</m>. We can
            write this as an English sentence:
        </p>
        <aside>
            <p>
                It turns out that the if-then construction is at the core of basically our entire process of logical
                reasoning. You will see it in a wide range of introductory courses, from an introduction to philosophy
                to an introduction to computer science. It's also ubiquitous in mathematics, though at this level we
                don't bring much attention to it.
            </p>
        </aside>
        <me>
            \text{If $x = 4$, then $2x = 8$.}
        </me>
        <p>
            Notice that we're not saying that <m>2x</m> always has the value of 8. We're just saying that <em>if</em>
            <m>x</m> takes the value of 4, <em>then</em> the value of <m>2x</m> must be 8.
        </p>
        <aside>
            <p>
                Writing in complete sentences helps you to think in complete ideas. You may not be used to writing
                sentences in math classes, but math is much more about being able to understand and explain ideas than
                just executing calculations.
            </p>
        </aside>
        <p>
            <alert xml:id="sec-vee-1-ac1-ti">Try it!</alert>
        </p>
        <p>
            Determine the value of <m>2x</m> when <m>x = 5</m>, <m>x = 12</m>, and <m>x = -3</m>. Write your results as
            if-then statements.
        </p>
        <solution>
            <p>
                <me>
                    \begin{aligned}
                        \amp \text{If $x = 5$, then $2x = 10$.} \\
                        \amp \text{If $x = 12$, then $2x = 24$.} \\
                        \amp \text{If $x = -3$, then $2x = -6$.}
                    \end{aligned}
                </me>
            </p>
        </solution>
    </activity>
    <activity xml:id="sec-vee-1-ac2-variable-representation-1">
        <title>Variables Represent Quantities (Part 1)</title>
        <p>
            Consider the following set of equations:
            <me>
                x + 3 = 7 \hspace{2cm} x + 3 = 8 \hspace{2cm} x + 3 = 9 \hspace{2cm} x + 3 = 10
            </me> 
            Notice that to solve all of them, you would subtract 3 from both sides of the equation. This algebraic step
            solves the equation regardless of what number is on the right side of the equation.
        </p>
        <aside>
            <p>
                We will formally define what it means to <term>solve</term> an equation in a couple sections. See
                <xref ref="def-solve-solution" />.
            </p>
        </aside>
        <p>
            Now consider this equation: <m>x + 3 = a</m>. We will solve this variable for <m>x</m>. Notice that the
            algebraic step remains the same. It turns out that the final result cannot be simplified any further.
            <me>
                \begin{aligned}
                    x + 3 \amp = a \\
                    x \amp = a - 3 \amp \eqnspacer \amp \text{Subtract 3 from both sides}
                \end{aligned}
            </me>
        </p>
        <p>
            <aside>
                You might remember the concept of "combining like terms" for determining whether an expression can be
                simplified. If not, we'll get to it soon.
            </aside>
        </p>
        <p>
            <alert xml:id="sec-vee-1-ac2-ti">Try it!</alert>
        </p>
        <p>
            Solve the equation <m>x - 7 = c</m> for the variable <m>x</m> using a complete presentation.
        </p>
        <p>
            <aside>
                Your final answer will be a mathematical expression, and that's okay.
            </aside>
        </p>
        <solution>
            <p>
                <me>
                    \begin{aligned}
                        x - 7 \amp = c \\
                        x \amp = c + 7 \amp \eqnspacer \amp \text{Add $7$ to both sides}
                    \end{aligned}
                </me>
            </p>
        </solution>
    </activity>
    <activity xml:id="sec-vee-1-ac3-variable-representation-2">
        <title>Variables Represent Quantities (Part 2)</title>
        <p>
            Consider the following set of equations:
            <me>
                x + 3 = 7 \hspace{2cm} x + 4 = 7 \hspace{2cm} x + 5 = 7 \hspace{2cm} x + 6 = 7
            </me> 
            This time, the number that is being added to <m>x</m> is changing. But these are still very similar
            equations. And the algebraic step is basically the same for each one. You need to subtract whatever number
            it is that's being added to the <m>x</m>:
        </p>
        <aside>
            <p>
                A lot of math is seeking out and understanding patterns. This may be a simple pattern, but once you'v
                 internalized it, algebra becomes much easier.
            </p>
        </aside>
        <p>
            <me>
                \begin{aligned}
                    x + 3 \amp = 7 \longrightarrow \text{Subtract $3$ from both sides} \\
                    x + 4 \amp = 7 \longrightarrow \text{Subtract $4$ from both sides} \\
                    x + 5 \amp = 7 \longrightarrow \text{Subtract $5$ from both sides} \\
                    x + 6 \amp = 7 \longrightarrow \text{Subtract $6$ from both sides}
                \end{aligned}
            </me>
        </p>
        <p>
            Now consider this equation: <m>x + b = 7</m>. Based on the pattern above, you should have an idea of what
            you need to do to solve for <m>x</m>.
        </p>
        <p>
            <alert xml:id="sec-vee-1-ac3-ti">Try it!</alert>
        </p>
        <p>
            Solve the equation <m>x + b = 7</m> for the variable <m></m> using a complete presentation.
        </p>
        <solution>
            <p>
                <me>
                    \begin{aligned}
                        x + b \amp = 7 \\
                        x \amp = -b + 7 \amp \eqnspacer \amp \text{Subtract $b$ from both sides}
                    \end{aligned}
                </me>
            </p>
            <aside>
                <p>
                    <m>x = 7 - b</m> is also acceptable.
                </p>
            </aside>
        </solution>
    </activity>
    <activity xml:id="sec-vee-1-ac4-other-symbols">
        <title>Using Other Symbols</title>
        <p>
            The variable <m>x</m> is traditional, but not special. We're allowed to solve for other variables. The
            underlying thinking process remains the same.
        </p>
        <p>
            <alert xml:id="sec-vee-1-ac4-ti">Try it!</alert>
        </p>
        <p>
            Solve the equation <m>a + b - c = d - e</m> for the variable <m>c</m> using a complete presentation.
        </p>
        <aside>
            <p>
                You should be able to solve for any of the variables in this equation.
            </p>
        </aside>
        <solution>
            <p>
                <me>
                    \begin{aligned}
                        a + b - c \amp = d - e \\
                        b - c \amp = -a + d - e \amp \eqnspacer \amp \text{Subtract $a$ from both sides} \\ 
                        - c \amp = -a - b + d - e \amp \amp \text{Subtract $b$ from both sides} \\
                        c \amp = a + b - d + e \amp \amp \text{Multiply both sides by $-1$}
                    \end{aligned}
                </me>
            </p>
            <aside>
                <p>
                    It is often helpful to keep your variables in alphabetical order.
                </p>
            </aside>
        </solution>
    </activity>
</section>