<section xml:id="sec-sese-1-main">
	<title>Read the Instructions</title>
	<objectives>
		<ul>
			<li>
				<p>
					Distinguish between mathematical equations and expressions.
				</p>
			</li>
			<li>
				<p>
					Recognize the differences between different sets of instructions.
				</p>
			</li>
			<li>
				<p>
					Correctly execute the instructions that are given.
				</p>
			</li>
		</ul>
	</objectives>
	<p>
		An important aspect of mathematics is the attention to detail and precision required to do it well. However, for
		many students (and even many teachers) the importance of that precision is often overlooked in favor of
		repetitive execution. The most prevalent example of imprecision in language for mathematics at this level is the
		word "solve." Unfortunately, this word is used as a placeholder for a wide range of mathematical procedures.
	</p>
	<aside>
		<p>
			Words are extremely important to mathematics. 
		</p>
	</aside>
	<p>
		Here are some examples: 
		<ul>
			<li>
				<p>
					Solve <m>5 + 8</m>. 
				</p>
			</li>
			<li>
				<p>
					Solve <m>5x + 8x</m>. 
				</p>
			</li>
			<li>
				<p>
					Solve <m>5x + 8 = 23</m>. 
				</p>
			</li>
			<li>
				<p>
					Solve <m>x^2 + 6x + 9</m>. 
				</p>
			</li>
		</ul>
		Only one of these reflects the proper usage of the word "solve." Do you know which one it is? Can you come up
		with a description of what that word means? 
	</p>
	<aside>
		<p>
			Are you going to stop to think about that question, or just keep reading? 
		</p>
	</aside>
	<p>
		When one word comes to represent so many different activities, it becomes extremely confusing to know what's
		being asked of you. But by taking the time to be precise with our language, we can create mental categories to
		help us keep information organized. Here are the same calculations, but given with proper instructions. 
		<ul>
			<li>
				<p>
					Calculate <m>5 + 8</m>. 
				</p>
			</li>
			<li>
				<p>
					Simplify <m>5x + 8x</m>. 
				</p>
			</li>
			<li>
				<p>
					Solve <m>5x + 8 = 23</m>. 
				</p>
			</li>
			<li>
				<p>
					Factor <m>x^2 + 6x + 9</m>. 
				</p>
			</li>
		</ul>
	</p>
	<aside>
		<p>
			Do any of these words make you think of specific procedures? 
		</p>
	</aside>
	<p>
		There are even more words that can be used as instructions. Evaluate, compute, estimate, round, rewrite, verify,
		prove, plot, sketch, and graph are just some of them. Some of these are similar to each other, and some are very
		different. 
	</p>
	<p>
		The purpose of this section is to help you to make sense of some of these words to create some of the mental
		structures that will help you think through the ideas more effectively. As usual, we will start with a couple
		definitions. 
	</p>

    <definition xml:id="def-expression">
        <title>Expression</title>
        <idx><h>expression</h></idx>
        
        <statement>
            <p>
				A mathematical <term>expression</term> is a meaningful collection of mathematical symbols that
				represents a value.
            </p>
        </statement>
    </definition>

	<p>
		Whether or not something is meaningful depends on your level of knowledge. And the number of symbols that are
		meaningful should grow over time in the same way that your vocabulary grows over time. At this point, you should
		recognize that "<m>5 + \strut</m>" is not meaningful, but you might not be able to determine whether "<m>2 \sin
		\pi - 1</m>" is if you've never seen trigonometry (and maybe even if you have). 
	</p>
	<aside>
		<p>
			"<m>5 + \strut</m>" doesn't say what number to add to 5. "<m>2 \sin \pi - 1</m>" is a valid expression. It's
			okay if you don't know what that means right now. 
		</p>
	</aside>
	<p>
		Numbers (such as 5 and and monomials (such as and are expressions. Expressions may also consist of calculations
		(such as <m>5 + 8</m>) or polynomials (such as <m>x^2 - 8x + 12</m>). Between these last two examples, there is
		an important distinction. There is a shorter way to write <m>5 + 8</m> with fewer symbols (namely, as the number
		13), but we cannot do the same with <m>x^2 - 8x + 12</m>. 
	</p>

    <definition xml:id="def-simplify">
        <title>Simplify</title>
        <idx><h>simplify</h></idx>
        
        <statement>
            <p>
				To <term>simplify</term> an expression means to find the simplest mathematical expression that
				represents the same quantity.
            </p>
        </statement>
    </definition>

	<p>
		This is a broad category for a lot of mathematical concepts. For example, the process of combining like terms is
		one way to simplify an expression, since we can reasonably see that <m>5x + 8x</m> is not as simple as
		<m>13x</m>. We can also use this word for arithmetic calculations such as <m>8 + 6 \cdot 7 - 12</m>. You will
		sometimes see words like calculate or compute for these types of problems. 
	</p>
	<aside>
		<p>
			We will take a deeper look at the order of operations in a later section. 
		</p>
	</aside>
	<p>
		We didn't bring any attention to it, but in the last section we demonstrated the presentation format for
		problems where the goal is simplification. 
		<me>
			\begin{aligned}
			\text{(Original Expression)} \amp = \text{(Manipulated Expression 1)} \amp \eqnspacer \amp \text{Explanation 1} \\
			\amp = \text{(Manipulated Expression 2)} \amp \amp \text{Explanation 2} \\
			\amp = \cdots \\
			\amp = \text{(Final Expression)} \amp \amp \text{Final explanation} 
			\end{aligned}
		</me>
		You can think of this as a long line of small manipulations. It's helpful to go over to the right before going
		down so that you can more easily visualize the idea that the top expression on the left side is the thing that
		is equal to all of the expressions on the right. But it's not strictly necessary to do that. The more important
		thing is to recognize that each new line is a continuation from the previous one, and not an entirely new
		equation. 
	</p>
	<activity xml:id="sec-sese-1-ac1-simplifying-expression">
		<title>Simplifying an Expression</title>
		<p>
			If you look back at the section on combining like terms, you will see the above presentation in all of the
			presented work throughout the section. The examples exist not only to show you the ideas, but also to model
			how you write things. 
		</p>
		<p>
			<alert xml:id="sec-sese-1-ac1-ti">Try it!</alert>
		</p>
		<p>
			Simplify the expression <m>(3x + 7y) - (4x + 5y)</m> using a complete presentation. 
		</p>
		<solution>
			<p>
				<me>
					\begin{aligned}
						(3x + 7y) - (4x + 5y) \amp = 3x + 7y - 4x - 5y \amp \amp \text{Distributive property} \\
						\amp = 3x - 4x + 7y - 5y \amp \amp \text{Rearrange the terms} \\
						\amp = (3x - 4x) + (7y - 5y) \amp \amp \text{Group the terms} \\
						\amp = (3-4)x + (7-5)y \amp \amp \text{Factor out the $x$ and the $y$} \\
						\amp = -x + 2y \amp \amp \text{Arithmetic} 
					\end{aligned}
				</me>
			</p>
		</solution>
	</activity>
	<p>
		The reason the distinction in presentation is important is because the types of things you're allowed to do when
		simplifying an expression are different from the things you can do when solving an equation. 
	</p>

    <definition xml:id="def-equation">
        <title>Equation</title>
        <idx><h>equation</h></idx>
        
        <statement>
            <p>
				A mathematical <term>equation</term> is a statement of the form <m>A = B</m>, where <m>A</m> and
				<m>B</m> are mathematical expressions. The statement <m>A = B</m> means that both <m>A</m> and <m>B</m>
				represent the same mathematical quantity.
            </p>
        </statement>
    </definition>
	<p>
		The equal sign can be read as "represents the same quantity as," so that <m>A = B</m> can be read as "<m>A</m>
		represents the same quantity as <m>B</m>."
	</p>
	<aside>
		<p>
			Some people use "is" because it's a lot shorter. However, it's a little less precise to say it that way. 
		</p>
	</aside>
	<p>
		If we think of expressions as phrases, then equations are sentences. The important distinction here is that
		equations make a declaration that is either true or false, where as expressions are just ideas. For example,
		"the dog" is just an expression. If we say "the dog" without any context, the response is, "What about it?" But
		we can turn it into a complete thought, such as "the dog is brown," which is going to be either true or false.
		We won't know whether it's true or false until we pick a particular dog to look at. 
	</p>
	<p>
		In the same way, is a mathematical expression. It just represents a number, like 5. It's not until we put it
		into a mathematical equation (such as <m>2x = 10</m>) that we can start to analyze the truth value. Depending on
		the specific value of the equation might be true or it might not be true. If <m>x = 4</m> then the equation is
		not true, but if <m>x = 5</m> then the equation is true. 
	</p>

    <definition xml:id="def-solve-solution">
        <title>Solve and Solution of an Equation</title>
        <idx><h>solve</h> <h>equation</h> </idx>
        <idx><h>solution</h> <h>of an equation</h> </idx>
        
        <statement>
            <p>
				To <term>solve</term> an equation means to find the value (or values) of the variable (or variables)
				that make the equation true. A <term>solution</term> of an equation is a specific value of the variable
				(or specific values of the variables) that make the equation true.
            </p>
        </statement>
    </definition>

	<p>
		We're not going to spend a lot of time discussing <em>truth values</em> and just rely on your intuition. The 
		quation <m>2 + 3 = 5</m> is true and the equation <m>7 - 4 = 2</m> is false. We can apply the same ideas to
		equations with variables. It's true that if <m>x = 2</m> then <m>3x - 1 = 5</m>, and it's false that when
		<m>x = 2</m>, <m>3x - 1 = 7</m>. This means that <m>x = 2</m> is a solution of the equation <m>3x - 1 = 5</m>,
		but is not a solution of the equation <m>3x - 1 = 7</m>. 
	</p>
	<p>
		When working with equations, the key idea is that we have to maintain the equality. If we perform an arithmetic
		operation on one side of the equation, then we must do it to the other side. As you get further in mathematics,
		the types of manipulations become more complex, and there are other types of properties that you have to keep
		in mind when working with equations. 
	</p>
	<aside>
		<p>
			For example, if you take the square root of both sides of an equation, you need to use a <m>\pm</m> symbol
			since that operation creates two possibilities. 
		</p>
	</aside>
	<p>
		The presentation format when working with equations looks like the following:
		<me>
			\begin{array}{ccc}
				\text{(Original Equation)} \\
				\text{(Manipulated Equation 1)} \amp \eqnspacer \amp \text{Explanation 1} \\
				\text{(Manipulated Equation 2)} \amp \amp \text{Explanation 2} \\
				\cdots \\
				\text{(Final Equation)} \amp \amp \text{Final explanation} 
			\end{array}
		</me>
		When reading the meaning of this, what we're saying is that if the original equation is true, then the first
		manipulated equation is true because of the reason in explanation 1. Then the next equation is true because of
		the next manipulation, and so forth. 
	</p>
	<activity xml:id="sec-sese-1-ac2-solving-equation">
		<title>Solving an Equation</title>
		<p>
			If you look back at the section about algebraic presentation, we used the same structure there that we're
			advocating here. 
		</p>
		<p>
			<alert xml:id="sec-sese-1-ac2-ti">Try it!</alert>
		</p>
		<p>
			Solve the equation <m>5x - 7 = 7x + 11</m> using a complete presentation. 
		</p>
		<solution>
			<p>
				<me>
					\begin{aligned}
						5x - 7 \amp = 7x + 11 \\
						5x \amp = 7x + 18 \amp \amp \text{Add $7$ to both sides} \\
						-2x \amp = 18 \amp \amp \text{Subtract $7x$ from both sides} \\
						x \amp = -9 \amp \amp \text{Divide both sides by $-2$} 
					\end{aligned}
				</me>
			</p>
		</solution>
	</activity>
</section>
