<section xml:id="sec-pop-4-closing">
	<title>Closing Ideas</title>
	<p>
		In this section, we saw the last of the algebraic properties of arithmetic. 
	</p>
    <definition xml:id="def-comm-assoc-prop-mult">
        <title>The Commutative and Associative Properties of Multiplication</title>
        <idx><h>commutative property of multiplication</h></idx>
        <idx><h>associative property of multiplication</h></idx>
        <statement>
            <p>
                Let <m>a</m>, <m>b</m>, and <m>c</m> be real numbers. Then the following properties hold:
				<ul>
					<li>
						<p>
							<term>The Commutative Property of Multiplication</term>: <m>a \cdot b = b \cdot a</m>
						</p>
					</li>
					<li>
						<p>
							<term>The Associative Property of Multiplication</term>: <m>(a \cdot b) \cdot c = a \cdot (b \cdot c)</m>
						</p>
					</li>
				</ul>
            </p>
        </statement>
    </definition>
	<p>
		If this looks familiar, it's because we saw something very similar to it a few sections ago. It turns out that
		addition also has these two properties (<xref ref="def-comm-assoc-prop-add" />). And when we combine them
		together with the distributive property (<xref ref="def-distributive-property" />), we get a pretty thorough
		description of how arithmetic and algebra works. 
	</p>
	<p>
		It's important to notice that we've never proven any of these properties. We've relied on our experiences going
		all the way back to when we were first learning basic arithmetic as our foundation. And from those experiences,
		we've built out our understanding that this is how numbers work. The world would be a very different place if
		these things weren't true. 
	</p>
	<p>
		<ul>
			<li>
				<p>
					(The commutative property of addition) If we start with an empty bag, then put one apple into bag
					followed by two apples, we get the same result as if we had put in two apples followed by one apple. 
				</p>
			</li>
			<li>
				<p>
					(The associative property of addition) If we put one apple and two oranges in a bag, and then put
					three bananas in afterward, we get the same result as if we had put the two oranges and three
					bananas in the bag first, and then put the one apple in. 
				</p>
			</li>
			<li>
				<p>
					(The commutative property of multiplication) Three bag of five apples have the same number as five
					bags of three apples. 
				</p>
			</li>
			<li>
				<p>
					(The associative property of multiplication) Two boxes that each contain three bags with four apples
					has the same number of apples as (two times three) bags with four apples each. 
				</p>
			</li>
		</ul>
	</p>
	<aside>
		<p>
			The associative property of multiplication is tricky because we rarely think of what it means to multiply
			three numbers together. 
		</p>
	</aside>
	<p>
		So at a very basic level, we believe these statements are true because our experiences with reality tell us they
		should be true. These are not rules that mathematicians came up with and told everyone else they had to follow.
		Mathematicians simply created a language to describe these things. 
	</p>
	<aside>
		<p>
			Replacing numbers with variables is an example of an abstraction. Symbolically representing multiplication
			with a grid is another. 
		</p>
	</aside>
	<p>
		When it comes to college level mathematics, it can be helpful to think about the work you're doing with that
		framework in mind. As much as you can, try to ground all the work that you do in terms of practical reality.
		You won't always be able to do it. Sometimes, the work that you're doing is an abstraction or generalization of
		a concept. If that's the case, try to bring yourself back to the last example that made sense, and see if you
		can use that knowledge to help you build the next piece. 
	</p>
	<p>
		This isn't always going to be easy. Some ideas will take more time to sink in than others. That's part of the
		nature of learning. But if you invest the time and the energy to slow down and learn to think clearly about what
		you're doing, you'll have a much better chance at being successful.
	</p>
</section>
