<section xml:id="sec-sese-5-deeper">
	<title>Going Deeper: Inequalities</title>
	<p>
		In this section, we talked about the difference between equations and expressions. But there's another type of
		mathematical statement that is like an equation, but instead of declaring that two quantities represent the same
		value, we want one to be greater than or less than the other. These statements are known as inequalities. 
	</p>
	<aside>
		<p>
			In <xref ref="sec-ra-5-deeper"/> , we will see how to visualize these relationships geometrically. This
			geometric framework is particularly useful when negative numbers are involved. But for now, we're going to
			trust your intuition and experience to interpret the meaning of these words. 
		</p>
	</aside>
    <definition xml:id="def-inequality">
        <title>Inequality</title>
        <idx><h>inequality</h></idx>
        
        <statement>
            <p>
				A mathematical <term>inequality</term> is a statement of the form <m>A \gt B</m>, <m>A \lt B</m>,
				<m>A \geq B</m>, or <m>A \leq B</m>, where $A$ and $B$ are mathematical expressions. Each statement has
				an associated interpretation:
				<ul>
					<li>
						<p>
							<m>A \gt B</m> means that <m>A</m> represents a quantity that is greater than the quantity
							that <m>B</m> represents.
						</p>
					</li>
					<li>
						<p>
							<m>A \lt B</m> means that <m>A</m> represents a quantity that is less than the quantity
							that <m>B</m> represents.
						</p>
					</li>
					<li>
						<p>
							<m>A \geq B</m> means that <m>A</m> represents a quantity that is greater than or equal to
							the quantity that <m>B</m> represents.
						</p>
					</li>
					<li>
						<p>
							<m>A \leq B</m> means that <m>A</m> represents a quantity that is less than or equal to the
							quantity that <m>B</m> represents.
						</p>
					</li>
				</ul>
            </p>
        </statement>
    </definition>

	<p>
		<idx><h>inequality</h> <h>strict</h></idx>
		<idx><h>inequality</h> <h>non-strict</h></idx>
		<idx><h>inequality</h> <h>inclusive</h></idx>
		<idx><h>inequality</h> <h>weak</h></idx>
		We often call the first two symbols <term>strict inequalities</term>, emphasizing that we are interested in the
		more stringent condition. Interestingly, we don't have a formal name for the other two. You will sometimes see
		them called <term>non-strict</term>, <term>inclusive</term>, or <term>weak</term> inequalities, but there's no
		consensus term among mathematicians. 
	</p>
	<p>
		Manipulating inequalities is almost identical manipulating equations, though there is one very important
		distinction. When multiplying or dividing, the axioms only allow for doing this with positive values. You should
		compare this definition with <xref ref="def-equality" />. 
	</p>
	<aside>
		<p>
			The first axiom allows us to state these properties for just the symbol rather than having to repeat
			everything with the symbol. We also avoid having to explicitly discuss the <m>\geq</m> and <m>\leq</m>
			symbols because those are simply shorthand to represent both a strict inequality and an equality at the same
			time. 
		</p>
	</aside>
    <definition xml:id="def-inequality-axioms">
        <title>Axioms of Inequality</title>
        <idx><h>axioms of inequality</h></idx>
        <statement>
            <p>
                Let <m>a</m>, <m>b</m>, and <m>c</m> be real numbers. The <term>axioms of inequality</term> state that
                <ol>
                    <li>
                        <p>
                            If <m>a \gt b</m>, then <m>b \lt a</m>.
                        </p>
                    </li>
                    <li>
                        <p>
                            If <m>a \gt b</m>, then <m>a + c \gt b + c</m>.
                        </p>
                    </li>
                    <li>
                        <p>
                            If <m>a \lt b</m>, then <m>a - c \lt b - c</m>.
                        </p>
                    </li>
                    <li>
                        <p>
                            If <m>a \gt b</m> and <m>c \gt 0</m>, then <m>ac \gt bc</m>.
                        </p>
                    </li>
                    <li>
                        <p>
                            If <m>a \gt b</m> and <m>c \gt 0</m>, then <m>\frac{a}{c} \gt \frac{b}{c}</m>.
                        </p>
                    </li>
                </ol>
            </p>
        </statement>
    </definition>
	<aside>
		<p>
			Notice the extra condition that is positive in the last two axioms! 
		</p>
	</aside>
	<aside>
		<p>
			Rule-based thinking treats everything like a axiom. Every time there's a new situation, there's a new rule
			to learn. Mathematicians prefer fewer rules because it helps us identify the most important ideas. 
		</p>
	</aside>
	<p>
		You might remember from your previous experiences that when you multiply or divide by a negative number, that
		you're supposed to flip the inequality. But that's not listed here! What's happening is that this property is
		not an axiom. We can actually show that this property is a logical consequence of the listed properties.
		We will show how the negative sign appears in a simple calculation and let you try to prove the general property
		on your own. 
	</p>
	<aside>
		<p>
			Breaking concepts down into basic axioms is like understanding that all atoms are made of protons, neutrons,
			and electrons. A small set of basic building blocks can create an entire universe of mathematics. 
		</p>
	</aside>
		<me>
			\begin{aligned}
				a \amp \gt b \\
				a + ((-a) + (-b)) \amp \gt b + ((-a) + (-b)) \amp \eqnspacer \amp \text{Add $(-a) + (-b)$ to both sides} \\
				-b \amp \gt -a \amp \amp \text{Combine like terms} \\
				-a \amp \lt -b \amp \amp \text{The axioms of equality} 
			\end{aligned}
		</me>
	<aside>
		<p>
			The general proof is a simple calculation, but remember that simple is not always easy. It's normal for
			students to struggle with this. 
		</p>
	</aside>
	<p>
		To prove the general case, note that if <m>c \lt 0</m>, then <m>-c \gt 0</m> so that you can multiply both sides
		by <m>-c</m> in the first step using the axioms of inequality. From there, you'll need to make a similar
		manipulation to the one above. 
	</p>
	<p>
		We can expand our definition of what it means to solve an equation so that it applies to inequalities. You
		should compare this definition with <xref ref="def-solve-solution"/>.
	</p>
    <definition xml:id="def-solve-solution-inequality">
        <title>Solve and Solution of an Inequality</title>
        <idx><h>solve</h> <h>inequality</h> </idx>
        <idx><h>solution</h> <h>of an inequality</h> </idx>
        
        <statement>
            <p>
				To <term>solve</term> an inequality means to find the value (or values) of the variable (or variables)
				that make the inequality true. A <term>solution</term> of an inequality is a specific value of the
				variable (or specific values of the variables) that make the inequality true.
            </p>
        </statement>
    </definition>
	<p>
		With the exception of worrying about the direction of the inequality, solving inequalities is identical to
		solving equations. In fact, if you go back to any of the problems from previous sections and replace the equal
		sign with any of the inequality symbols, the algebraic steps will be identical and you would only need to check
		whether any of the steps involved multiplying or dividing by a negative number. For example, here is "Try It"
		exercise \#2, except using instead of in the original problem. 
		<me>
			\begin{aligned}
				5x - 7 \amp \gt 7x + 11 \\
				5x \amp \gt 7x + 18 \amp \eqnspacer \amp \text{Add $7$ to both sides} \\
				-2x \amp \gt 18 \amp \amp \text{Subtract $7x$ from both sides} \\
				x \amp \lt -9 \amp \amp \text{Divide both sides by $-2$} 
			\end{aligned}
		</me>
	</p>
	<aside>
		<p>
			Compare this to the solution of the original. 
		</p>
	</aside>
	<p>
		Notice that the change happened right at the step where we divided by -2. It doesn't happen before that step,
		and it doesn't happen on its own line after that step. It also does not happen because the 9 is negative. It
		happens because the algebraic manipulation called for dividing by a negative number. Furthermore, if you use the
		improper presentation from the first section of the book, inequalities lead to some rather unusual and
		nonsensical mathematical statements. We put such a heavy emphasis on presentation in order to avoid many of the
		errors that can arise from these things. 
	</p>
	<p>
		A key distinction is that solutions to inequalities are usually not a single value, but (usually) an infinite
		collection of values. For example, the inequality <m>x > 0</m> is true when <m>x = 1, 2, 3, \ldots</m>. But we
		have to remember that we're thinking about all possible values, so we have to include decimals such as
		<m>0.1, 0.01, 0.001, 0.0001, \ldots</m>. 
	</p>
	<p>
		The second collection of values hints at a very unusual feature about numbers. There is no smallest solution to
		the inequality <m>x > 0</m>. Another way of saying this is that there is no smallest positive number. For any
		positive number you can think of, there's always another that's less than your number but still positive. If
		you've never really thought about why this happens, it's worth taking some time to think about it. 
	</p>
	<p>
		It turns out that this simple notion is connected to a number of profoundly interesting mathematical ideas. Here
		are just a few questions that this one idea leads to: 
		<ul>
			<li>
				<p>
					There are infinitely many numbers between 0 and 1 and infinitely many numbers between 0 and
					0.00000001. Since the first gap is bigger than the second gap, does it make sense to say that the
					infinity of values in the first interval is larger than the infinity of values in the second? (It
					turns out that these two infinities are the same size, but that isn't the same as saying that
					<em>all</em> infinities are the same!) 
				</p>
			</li>
			<li>
				<p>
					What happens to the value of <m>\frac{1}{x}</m> as we let <m>x</m> take the values
					<m>0.1, 0.01, 0.001, 0.0001, \ldots</m>? It looks like it's getting larger and larger. Does it make
					sense to say that <m>\frac{1}{0} = \infty</m>? (It turns out that it doesn't, but the exact reason
					this idea fails is a bit subtle.) 
				</p>
			</li>
			<li>
				<p>
					<idx><h>number</h> <h>surreal</h> </idx>
					Does it make sense to have a number where there are infinite number of zeros before the 1? (It turns
					out that such a mathematical object can make sense if you think about it the right way, but it's no
					longer what we would call a number. Instead, it's what me might call a <term>surreal</term> number.
					And no, this is not a joke.) 
				</p>
			</li>
		</ul>
	</p>
	<aside>
		<p>
			What does it even mean for something to come <em>after</em> an infinite number of other things? 
		</p>
	</aside>
	<p>
		We won't go into further detail about any of these topics here, as it goes way beyond the scope of this course.
		But it is interesting to reflect on how some very basic questions can lead to very profound mathematical ideas.
	</p>
</section>
