<section xml:id="sec-ref3-1-main">
    <title>Yet Another Pause for Reflection</title>

    <p>
        Congratulations! You have just completed the first two "branches" of the course.
    </p>
    <p>
        In the third branch, took a long look at some basic arithmetic concepts that you have probably known for the
        vast majority of your life. But we looked at these things in ways that you may have never seen before in your
        life. This is an important process in our intellectual growth as humans. There is value to periodically
        returning to some basic ideas to explore them again with the added knowledge and insights that can be gained
        only through years of experience. The discovery of new insights from old ideas drives a wide swath of
        mathematical thinking.
    </p>
    <p>
        The big emphasis of this branch was to expand your mental toolbox for working with numbers. Students that can
        only work with numbers as manipulations of digits tend to be less prepared to make conceptual connections than
        those that have multiple ways of thinking about numbers. In particular, being able to relate arithmetic to
        geometric concepts is useful in practical applications. For example, when working with information on a
        coordinate grid, knowing that the distance between two points is the difference between them brings insight into
        certain mathematical formulas, such as the point-slope form of a line, the distance formula, and the equations
        of circles.
    </p>
    <p>
        In this portion of the course, we have covered the following topics:
        <ul>
            <li>
                <p>
                    The Number Line and Base-10 blocks as Visualizations of
                    the Integers
                </p>
            </li>
            <li>
                <p>
                    Visualizations of Addition and the Addition Algorithm
                </p>
            </li>
            <li>
                <p>
                    Visualizations of Subtraction and the Subtraction Algorithm
                </p>
            </li>
            <li>
                <p>
                    Integer Chips as a Representation of Negative Numbers in
                    Addition and Subtraction Calculations
                </p>
            </li>
            <li>
                <p>
                    Movement on the Number Line for Negative Numbers in Addition
                    and Subtraction Calculations
                </p>
            </li>
            <li>
                <p>
                    Visualizations of Multiplication as "A Groups of B" and Area
                </p>
            </li>
            <li>
                <p>
                    Visualizations of Division as Making Groupings and Equal
                    Distribution
                </p>
            </li>
        </ul>
    </p>
</section>