<section xml:id="sec-das-4-closing">
	<title>Closing Ideas</title>
	<p>
		For the overwhelming majority of real life situations (especially work situations) that you can imagine, if
		there are any parts of a whole involved, it will probably be done with decimals. And in most of those real life
		situations, if you need to do a calculation, you would do it with a calculator. So why do we need to learn how
		to do these basic calculations, and what is the value of relating things back to fractions? 
	</p>
	<p>
		Remember that the ability to calculate a number and the ability to understand that number are two separate
		skills. If you type in some calculations and get 5.07 and 5.1 as the results, you may still need to decide which
		of those is greater. You might be surprised (or maybe not) that a fair number of adults will get that comparison
		wrong. Part of this is simply on the level of numerical and computational literacy, which is to help you
		correctly understand and use information in the real world. 
	</p>
	<p>
		The importance of being able to work with fractions is that there's a lot of information that is better
		communicated and more accurately communicated using fractions than decimals. For example, there are situations
		where it's easier to think about getting 8 items for $3 than it is to think about getting each individual item
		for approximately $0.38 each. And that ratio is much more useful as the unreduced fraction
		<m>\frac{\$ 3}{\text{8 items}}</m> if you need to buy in increments of 8 (like hot dog buns). 
	</p>
	<p>
		The value is not only in having two different ways of thinking about it, but also being able to relate the two
		together. Sometimes fractions are the better tool and sometimes decimals are the better tool. And so it is
		beneficial to be able to take the information you have and apply the right tool to solve the problem instead of
		forcing yourself to use the wrong tool because you don't know how to use the other one. There's a well-known
		saying to this effect: "If all you have is a hammer, everything looks like a nail."
	</p>
</section>
