<section xml:id="sec-fb-5-deeper">
	<title>Going Deeper: Reducing Rational Expressions</title>
	<p>
		Usually, when students think of calculus, they think of extremely elaborate calculations and complicated
		algebraic manipulations. And while there are certainly some aspects of the course for which that is true, it
		turns out that the core concepts of calculus are ideas that you can understand without needing a lot of algebra. 
	</p>
	<aside>
		<p>
			Derivatives are basically slopes. Integrals are basically areas. The trick to getting there is the concept
			of a <em>limit</em>, which can be understood intuitively without much algebra at all. 
		</p>
	</aside>
	<p>
		One of the largest hurdles students face when they get to calculus is not the calculus, but the algebra. It is
		very possible to get all the way to calculus without having attained algebraic fluency. As the expressions get
		more complex, the error rate goes up. And this, much more than the calculus, ends up holding students back. 
	</p>
	<aside>
		<p>
			<idx><h>derivative</h></idx>
			The derivative of the function is defined as
			<me>
				f'(x) = \lim_{h \to 0} \frac{f(x+h) - f(x)}{h}.
			</me> 
		</p>
	</aside>
	<p>
		One area of algebra that students struggle with in particular is the manipulation of fractions. This is an
		extremely important skill because the main idea of the first half of calculus (differential calculus) is defined
		as a fraction. In theory, you already have all the skills required to perform the algebraic part of these
		calculations. You know how to perform a substitution, multiply polynomials, and combine like terms. The
		remaining algebraic step is to reduce the algebraic fraction. 
	</p>
	<aside>
		<p>
			All examples and problems except for Problem 4 of Worksheet 5. 
		</p>
	</aside>
	<p>
		In all of the examples and problems in this section, you were given a fraction where all the numerator and
		denominator were simply products of algebraic terms. This helps to give students the practice of matching up
		terms and reducing correctly in these situations. But it also leads students down the path of incorrect
		manipulations when they do not fully understand the cancellation process. 
	</p>
	<p>
		Over the next several sections, the "Going Deeper" sections are going to focus specifically on dealing with
		fractions involving polynomials, which are often called <em>rational expressions</em>. These sections are aimed
		at students who are on the pathway towards calculus to help develop specific algebraic skills that are useful
		along that pathway. 
	</p>
	<aside>
		<p>
			Whether you see it as multiplication or division depends on how you choose to view it. We're just going to
			go with multiplication. 
		</p>
	</aside>
	<p>
		Reducing fractions is a mathematical process built on multiplication. You should be looking for terms that are
		multiplicative in the numerator and the denominator. More precisely, you need to be able to factor identical
		terms from the numerator and the denominator. This is why we chose to explicitly write out the products before
		reducing in this section. 
	</p>
	<p>
		Most of the errors that come from reducing fractions incorrectly result from different forms of simply crossing
		off terms that look the same in the numerator and the denominator. When you look at these calculations, you will
		probably immediately recognize them as being wrong. But it's easy to identify errors when it's someone else's
		work and you're being told that these are errors. It's often more difficult when you're looking at your own
		work. 
	</p>
	<subsection>
		<title>A Collection of Errors</title>
		<aside>
			<p>
				See <xref ref="sec-rme-1-main" /> to review this. 
			</p>
		</aside>
		<p>
			<ul>
				<li>
					<p>
						Canceling addition: Do not cancel out terms when they are being added or subtracted. It must
						always be a multiplicative term to cancel.
						<me>
							\frac{x^2 + 5x + 4}{x^2 - 4x + 4} \overset{\times}{=} \frac{x^2 + 5x \, \cancel{+ \, 4}}{x^2 - 4x \, \cancel{+ \, 4}} = \frac{x^2 + 5x}{x^2 - 4x}
						</me> 
					</p>
				</li>
				<li>
					<p>
						Partial cancellation: This is another version of the previous error. Even though the terms are
						being multiplied by something, that something isn't the entire remainder of the numerator and
						the denominator. The mistake here is canceling out part of an additive term.
						<me>
							\frac{3x + 1}{2x + 1} \overset{\times}{=} \frac{3 \cancel{x} + 1}{2\cancel{x} + 1} = \frac{3+1}{2+1} = \frac{4}{3}
						</me> 
					</p>
				</li>
				<li>
					<p>
						Another partial cancellation: This one is tricky because there's a half-truth to the
						cancellation. We'll discuss this particular step in more detail later. The key for now is to
						recognize how we're still canceling out within an additive term.
						<me>
							\frac{3x + 1}{x} \overset{\times}{=} \frac{3 \cancel{x} + 1}{\cancel{x}} = 3 + 1 = 4
						</me> 
					</p>
				</li>
				<li>
					<p>
						Breaking the order of operations: The multiplication being canceled must respect the order of
						operations. In this example, the and the should be seen as being grouped together, so that this
						cancellation cannot happen.
						<me>
							\frac{3x + 1}{x + 1} \overset{\times}{=} \frac{3 \, \cancel{x + \, 1}}{\cancel{x + \, 1}} = 3
						</me> 
					</p>
				</li>
			</ul>
		</p>
		<p>
			As you continue to move forward into the more algebraically complex world of rational expressions, it's
			likely that you're going to make some of these errors. The important thing is to not be discouraged.
			Mistakes are going to happen. The real key is how you respond to the mistakes when you make them. Students
			often have a reflex of "I forgot" and then quickly move on to the next thing. Unfortunately, this usually
			does not help them avoid that error in the future. It takes a certain amount of intentional effort and
			reflection to internalize the algebra. 
		</p>
		<p>
			A helpful recommendation is to keep a record of your algebraic errors. By writing them down, you can start
			to identify your own patterns of mistakes, which trains your brain to watch out for them in the future. It
			only takes a few seconds per mistake, but that's sometimes all it takes to to get your brain to start to
			recognize it. 
		</p>
	</subsection>
	<subsection>
		<title>Factoring Out the Constant (Including the Negative)</title>
		<p>
			Having gone through a list of examples that don't reduce, it's also important to discuss certain types of
			fractions that do reduce. One type of factorization that students sometimes overlook is to factor out a
			constant. This can sometimes reveal binomial terms that factor out that are not immediately obvious. Here
			is an example:
			<me>
				\frac{x + 2}{4x + 8} = \frac{x + 2}{4(x + 2)} = \frac{\cancel{x + 2}}{4 \cancel{(x + 2)}} = \frac{1}{4}
			</me> 
		</p>
		<aside>
			<p>
				Having a coefficient of 1 for the <m>x</m> term in a binomial is also important for some larger ideas
				related to polynomials. Specifically, if we do this then it's easy for us to identify the <em>roots</em>
				of the polynomial. 
			</p>
		</aside>
		<p>
			One particular example of this is factoring a negative from the binomial. In general, when it comes to
			applications involving factoring, we try to keep the coefficient of the <m>x</m> term positive because it helps
			us to more easily recognize terms that can cancel out. Here is an example of this:
			<me>
				\frac{3 - x}{x - 3}  = \frac{-x + 3}{x - 3} = \frac{-1 (x - 3)}{x - 3} = \frac{-1 \cancel{(x - 3)}}{\cancel{x - 3}} = -1
			</me>
		</p>
	</subsection>
</section>
