<section xml:id="sec-uc-2-worksheets">
	<title>Worksheets</title>

	<p>
		<url href="external/worksheets/35-Worksheets.pdf">PDF Version of these Worksheets</url>
	</p>
	
	<worksheet xml:id="sec-uc-2-worksheets-1">
		<title>Worksheet 1</title>
		<exercise>
			<p>
				Write an equation that relates inches to centimeters, then use it to determine two conversion factors. 
			</p>
			<aside>
				<p>
					You may not know all of these conversions. You can look them up on the internet if you're not sure. 
				</p>
			</aside>
		</exercise>
		<exercise>
			<p>
				Convert 12 inches into centimeters. 
			</p>
		</exercise>
		<exercise>
			<p>
				Convert 100 centimeters into inches. 
			</p>
		</exercise>
		<exercise>
			<p>
				Write an equation that relates cups to quarts, then use it to determine two conversion factors. 
			</p>
		</exercise>
		<exercise>
			<p>
				Convert 32 cups into quarts. 
			</p>
		</exercise>
		<exercise>
			<p>
				Convert 4 quarts into cups. 
			</p>
		</exercise>
	</worksheet>
	<worksheet xml:id="sec-uc-2-worksheets-2">
		<title>Worksheet 2</title>
		<exercise>
			<p>
				Write an equation that relates kilowatts to watts, then use it to determine two conversion factors. 
			</p>
		</exercise>
		<exercise>
			<p>
				Write an equation that relates deciliters to liters, then use it to determine two conversion factors. 
			</p>
		</exercise>
		<exercise>
			<p>
				Write an equation that relates nanometers to meters, then use it to determine two conversion factors. 
			</p>
		</exercise>
		<exercise>
			<p>
				Write an equation that relates hectares to acres, then use it to determine two conversion factors. 
			</p>
			<aside>
				<p>
					A hectare is the area of a square with side lengths of meters. However, it is not equal to square
					meters. We'll explore this in a later worksheet. 
				</p>
			</aside>
		</exercise>
		<exercise>
			<p>
				Write an equation that relates centimeters to meters and another equation that relates meters to
				kilometers. Use these two equations together to determine two conversion factors that relate kilometers
				to centimeters. 
			</p>
		</exercise>
	</worksheet>
	<worksheet xml:id="sec-uc-2-worksheets-3">
		<title>Worksheet 3</title>
		<p>
			In science courses, you will encounter some interesting units that are built to describe specific
			situations. Although you may not have any intuition with these, as long as you have a formula and you
			understand the method, you can be begin to work with the problems. 
		</p>
		<exercise>
			<p>
				A mole of objects is <m>6.022 \times 10^{23}</m> of those objects. For example, a mole of carbon atoms
				is <m>6.022 \times 10^{23}</m> carbon atoms. How many molecules of oxygen are in 5.7 moles of oxygen? 
			</p>
		</exercise>
		<exercise>
			<p>
				An astronomical unit is approximately <m>1.496 \times 10^{11}</m> meters. This is the approximate
				distance from the earth to the sun. Mars is approximately 1.52 astronomical units from the sun. About
				how far is it from the sun to Mars in meters? 
			</p>
		</exercise>
		<exercise>
			<p>
				Words such as millions and billions can also be used as a unit conversion. This is often used when
				talking about finances at a state or national level. Earlier, we talked about the $300000000 Mars
				Climate Orbiter. This could have been written as $300 million. 
			</p>
			<aside>
				<p>
					<me>
						\begin{aligned}
							\text{1 thousand} \amp = 10^3 \\
							\text{1 million} \amp = 10^6 \\
							\text{1 billion} \amp = 10^9 \\
							\text{1 trillion} \amp = 10^{12}
						\end{aligned}
					</me>
				</p>
			</aside>
			<p>
				Write the quantity 2753.78 billion in standard form and using scientific notation. 
			</p>
		</exercise>
		<exercise>
			<p>
				A light-year is the distance that light can travels in one year in a vacuum. This distance is
				approximately <m>9.46 \times 10^{12}</m> kilometers. The distance between the Milky Way galaxy and the
				Andromeda galaxy is approximately 2.5 million light-years. Approximately how many kilometers is it
				between the two galaxies? 
			</p>
		</exercise>
	</worksheet>
	<worksheet xml:id="sec-uc-2-worksheets-4">
		<title>Worksheet 4</title>
		<exercise>
			<p>
				A stone is a measure of weight that is commonly used in the UK and Ireland. One stone is equal to 14
				pounds. If an object weighs 37 stone, how many pounds does it weigh? 
			</p>
		</exercise>
		<exercise>
			<p>
				A smoot is a unit of measurement devised as a prank by a fraternity at MIT. It is considered to be 67
				inches, which corresponds to the height of Oliver Smoot, who was used to measure Harvard bridge. The
				bridge was determined to have a length of approximately 364.4 smoots. Convert this distance to feet. 
			</p>
			<aside>
				<p>
					Convert smoots to inches, then inches to feet. 
				</p>
			</aside>
		</exercise>
		<exercise>
			<p>
				When thinking about very large or very small quantities, it is sometimes useful to relate them to
				quantities that you are more familiar with. For example, we can think of <m>1 \text{ home} = \$400000</m>
				as a relationship for converting dollars into homes. What is the equivalent of $1 billion in homes? 
				</p>
			<aside>
				<p>
					Go through the process of creating a conversion factor. 
				</p>
			</aside>
			</exercise>
			<exercise>
				<p>
					Transistors are an important component for modern electronics. The smallest transistors are about 7
					nanometers in size. A human hair is approximately 100 micrometers in diameter. How many transistors
					would need to be lined up to equate to the thickness of a human hair? 
				</p>
			</exercise>
		</worksheet>
		<worksheet xml:id="sec-uc-2-worksheets-5">
			<title>Worksheet 5</title>
			<p>
				A compound unit is a unit that mixes multiple other units together. Some common compound units are
				speeds like miles per hour (<m>\frac{\text{miles}}{\text{hours}}</m>) and pressures like pounds per
				square inch (<m>\frac{\text{pounds}}{\text{inch}^2} = \frac{\text{pounds}}{\text{inch} \cdot \text{inch}}</m>).
				When converting these, every unit much be converted individually. Here is an example of converting feet
				per day into inches per week: 
				<me>
					\begin{aligned}
						10 \frac{\text{feet}}{\text{day}}
						\amp = 10 \frac{\cancel{\text{feet}}}{\cancel{\text{day}}} \cdot \frac{12 \text{ inches}}{1 \cancel{\text{ foot}}} \cdot \frac{7 \cancel{\text{ days}}}{1 \text{ week}} \\
						\amp = 840 \frac{\text{inches}}{\text{week}} 
					\end{aligned}
				</me>
			</p>
			<exercise>
				<p>
					One mile is equal to about 1.6 kilometers. If a car is traveling 75 miles per hour, how many
					kilometers per minute is it traveling? 
				</p>
			</exercise>
			<exercise>
				<p>
					Water has a density of about 8.34 pounds per gallon. Convert this to ounces (weight) per ounce
					(liquid). 
				</p>
			</exercise>
			<exercise>
				<p>
					A hectare is the area of a square that is 100 meters on each side. Determine the conversion factor
					for hectares to square meters. 
				</p>
			</exercise>
		</worksheet>
	</section>
