<section xml:id="sec-bap-5-deeper">
    <title>Going Deeper: Clearing the Denominator</title>
    <p>
        For the problems in this section, it was possible that you ended up with a fraction in your final answer, but
        you were not given any fractions in the original problems. Students tend to have a negative relationship with
        fractions. Later in the book, we're going to take a very close look at them. But for now, we're going to focus
        on just some basic algebra involving fractions.
    </p>
    <p>
        <idx><h>cross multiplication</h></idx>
        Many students are at least vaguely familiar with something called "cross multiplication." This is a technique
        for working with the specific situation when you have two fractions equal to each other and you're trying to
        solve for the variable. Here is how it's often portrayed:
        <image xml:id="sec-bap-5-cross-mult" width="10%">
            <latex-image>
                \begin{tikzpicture}
                    \draw (0,0) node[anchor=north] {$\begin{aligned}
                        \frac{a}{b} \amp = \frac{c}{d} \\
                        ad \amp = bc
                    \end{aligned}$};
                    \draw (-0.5,-0.1) -- (0.5,-0.8);
                    \draw (0.5,-0.1) -- (-0.5,-0.8);
                \end{tikzpicture}
            </latex-image>
        </image>
    </p>
    <aside>
        <p>
            Notice how if you don't really know what's going on, the presentation is extremely unhelpful. It looks like
            you've just crossed out the whole problem.
        </p>
    </aside>
    <p>
        Many teachers teach this method, but there are some downsides to it. It creates an additional rule for students
        to remember, it's often applied incorrectly, and it doesn't teach or reinforce any specific algebraic concepts.
    </p>
    <p>
        Fractions in equations introduce their own set of difficulties because fraction manipulations involve their own
        concepts (for example, common denominators and reducing) which make things more complicated. Unfortunately, this
        leads to the tendency to create even more manipulations for students to learn so that you have one set of rules
        for fraction equations and a different set of rules for non-fraction equations. (If you're not comfortable with
        fractions, there's a very brief fraction review in <xref ref="sec-mos-1-fraction-review" />, and a more
        thorough discussion that runs through <xref ref="sec-fb-1-main" />, <xref ref="sec-fas-1-main" />,
        <xref ref="sec-fm-1-main" />, and <xref ref="sec-fd-1-main" />.)
    </p>
    <p>
        If you look back at <xref ref="def-equality" />, you might notice that there's one algebraic step that we did
        not use in this section. We never multiplied both sides of the equation by a value in our attempts to solve for
        the variable.
    </p>
    <aside>
        <p>
            Go back and check this claim!
        </p>
    </aside>
    <p>
        A very broad category of algebraic manipulations is known as "clearing the denominators." And this technique is
        built on multiplying both sides of the equation by the same value. The basic premise of this method is that it's
        often much easier to solve equations when there aren't fractions, and so it can make sense to eliminate them
        from the equation as the first step.
        <me>
            \begin{aligned}
                \frac{3x}{4} \amp = \frac{5}{3} \\
                12 \cdot \frac{3x}{4} \amp = 12 \cdot \frac{5}{3} \amp \eqnspacer \amp \text{Multiply both sides by $12$} \\
                3 \cdot \cancel{4} \cdot \frac{3x}{\cancel{4}} \amp = \cancel{3} \cdot 4 \cdot \frac{5}{\cancel{3}} \amp \amp \text{Reduce} \\
                9x \amp = 20 \amp \amp \text{Simplify}
            \end{aligned}
        </me>
    </p>
    <p>
        You can argue that cross-multiplication is "faster" in this case, and you would probably be correct. But that
        doesn't mean that cross-multiplication isn't without its drawbacks. The blind application of
        cross-multiplication can lead to numbers that are larger than necessary. Consider the following:
        <me>
            \begin{aligned}
                \frac{5x}{12} \amp = \frac{3}{8} \\
                24 \cdot \frac{5x}{12} \amp = 24 \cdot \frac{3}{8} \amp \eqnspacer \amp \text{Multiply both sides by $24$} \\
                2 \cdot \cancel{12} \cdot \frac{5x}{\cancel{12}} \amp = 3 \cdot \cancel{8} \cdot \frac{3}{\cancel{8}} \amp \amp \text{Reduce} \\
                10x \amp = 9 \amp \amp \text{Simplify}
            \end{aligned}
        </me>
    </p>
    <aside>
        <p>
            We can do even better by multiplying both sides by <m>\frac{12}{5}</m>, but that requires a higher level of
            skill and confidence with fraction manipulations.
        </p>
    </aside>
    <p>
        If we were to use cross-multiplication, we would have ended up with <m>40x = 36</m>. Then after dividing, we
        would have had to reduce the fraction, which creates more opportunities for error.
    </p>
    <p>
        And then there's the challenge of more complex equations. Consider the following:
        <me>
            \frac{3x}{4} + \frac{1}{3} = \frac{5}{6}
        </me>
        Students that have learned cross-multiplication will often try to apply it to this situation, even though it
        doesn't apply. When students learn rule-based mathematics, they will go through all sorts of interesting
        machinations to try to apply a rule where it doesn't belong because they simply don't know what else to do.
    </p>
    <aside>
        <p>
            "If the only tool you have is a hammer, then everything looks like a nail."
        </p>
    </aside>
    <p>
        We could solve this using fraction manipulations, but most people (including instructors) prefer not to do that
        if they don't have to. And clearing the denominator is the way around that. The trick is to multiply both sides
        of the equation by a number that causes all the denominators to cancel out.
    </p>
    <aside>
        <p>
            <idx><h>least common denominator</h></idx>
            This value turns out to be the <term>least common denominator</term> of all the fractions.
        </p>
    </aside>
    <p>
        <me>
            \begin{aligned}
                \frac{3x}{4} + \frac{1}{3} \amp = \frac{5}{6} \\
                12 \cdot \left( \frac{3x}{4} + \frac{1}{3} \right) \amp = 12 \cdot \frac{5}{6} \amp \eqnspacer \amp \text{Multiply both sides by $12$} \\
                12 \cdot \frac{3x}{4} + 12 \cdot \frac{1}{3} \amp = 12 \cdot \frac{5}{6} \amp \amp \text{Distribute} \\
                3 \cdot \cancel{4} \cdot \frac{3x}{\cancel{4}} + \cancel{3} \cdot 4 \cdot \frac{1}{\cancel{3}} \amp = 2 \cdot \cancel{6} \cdot \frac{5}{\cancel{6}} \amp \amp \text{Reduce} \\
                9x + 4 \amp = 10 \amp \amp \text{Simplify}
            \end{aligned}
        </me>
    </p>
    <aside>
        <p>
            Notice the parentheses in the second line! Those are incredibly important here! And if you don't remember
            the distributive property, it's coming up in a couple sections.
        </p>
    </aside>
    <p>
        This technique is used much further along in mathematics. For example, there's a technique called "partial
        fraction decomposition" that is used in calculus to break apart a fraction into simpler components. It comes
        down to working with an equation that might look like the following:
        <me>
            \frac{A}{x-2} + \frac{B}{x+1} = \frac{x+4}{(x-2)(x+1)}
        </me>
        The goal is to solve for <m>A</m> and <m>B</m>. A common first step is to clear the denominators so that you
        don't have to deal with fractions, and that manipulation looks very similar to the one above.
        <me>
            \begin{aligned}
                \frac{A}{x-2} + \frac{B}{x+1} \amp = \frac{x+4}{(x-2)(x+1)} \\
                (x-2)(x+1) \cdot \left( \frac{A}{x-2} + \frac{B}{x+1} \right) \amp = (x-2)(x+1) \cdot \frac{x+4}{(x-2)(x+1)} \\
                (x-2)(x+1) \cdot \frac{A}{x-2} + (x-2)(x+1) \cdot  \frac{B}{x+1} \amp = (x-2)(x+1) \cdot \frac{x+4}{(x-2)(x+1)} \\
                \cancel{(x-2)}(x+1) \cdot \frac{A}{\cancel{x-2}} + (x-2)\cancel{(x+1)} \cdot  \frac{B}{\cancel{x+1}} \amp = \cancel{(x-2)}\cancel{(x+1)} \cdot \frac{x+4}{\cancel{(x-2)}\cancel{(x+1)}} \\
                (x+1)A + (x-2)B \amp = x+4
            \end{aligned}
        </me>
    </p>
    <p>
        This is only the first step of this part of the problem. In practice, the next step would be to determine the
        values of <m>A</m> and <m>B</m>, then use this equation to substitute for the integrand of an integral, which
        then needs to be integrated.
    </p>
    <aside>
        <p>
            You're not expected to know what all those calculus words mean.
        </p>
    </aside>
    <p>
        Fortunately, you don't need to worry about this right now. The point is that the algebraic techniques you're
        learning right now are the same algebraic techniques you're going to see down the line, especially if you are
        on a track that's taking you towards calculus. It is important to do your best to build a solid foundation now
        so that you will be ready when you see more complicated manipulations in the future. It is an incredibly
        difficult task to do both at the same time.
    </p>
</section>