<section xml:id="sec-mr-1-main">
	<title>Key Words are (Mostly) Evil</title>
	<objectives>
		<ul>
			<li>
				<p>
					Translate verbal relationships into mathematical relationships.
				</p>
			</li>
			<li>
				<p>
					Find mathematical relationships that match given data.
				</p>
			</li>
		</ul>
	</objectives>
	<p>
		Students tend to dislike word problems. This is probably because word problems ask students to do something more
		difficult than pure calculations. Word problems ask students to understand information and then translate it
		into a form that allows them to use their mathematical toolbox. 
	</p>
	<aside>
		<p>
			If you've been following along with the challenges of rule-based thinking that we've been discussing
			throughout this book, you'll know where we're going. 
		</p>
	</aside>
	<p>
		In order to help students with this transition, some teachers started to introduce rule-based patterns into
		reading word problems. The problem is that this has led to students thinking incorrectly about the process of
		thinking through word problems. This approach is sometimes called "key words" and you can find lists of
		"key words" that are categorized by operation. 
	</p>
	<aside>
		<p>
			The grain of truth is that the words do indicate mathematical relationships that involve the operation. But
			that's different from treating the word as a rule. 
		</p>
	</aside>
	<p>
		The problem with this is that these lists are (mostly) evil. There is a grain of truth in them, but it sells
		students short of an actual understanding of how to think through word problems. It causes students to read word
		problems in ways that are sometimes incorrect and does not advance the cause of mathematical thinking. 
	</p>
	<activity xml:id="sec-mr-1-ac1-problem-with-key-words">
		<title>The Problem with Key Words</title>
		<p>
			Here is a classic example: "Bob has 5 rocks. Alice has 3 more rocks than Bob. How many rocks does Alice have?"
			The common thought process for people is that "more" tells us we need to add, so Alice has 8 rocks. The answer
			is correct, but the reasoning is wrong. But to understand why the reasoning is wrong, we need to look at a
			slightly different problem. 
		</p>
		<p>
			<alert xml:id="sec-mr-1-ac1-ti">Try it!</alert>
		</p>
		<p>
			Alice has 5 rocks. Alice has 3 more rocks than Bob. How many rocks does Bob have? Explain your reasoning. 
		</p>
		<solution>
			<aside>
				<p>
					Your exact language may vary, but the ideas should be basically the same. 
				</p>
			</aside>
			<p>
				Since Alice has 3 more rocks than Bob, Bob has a smaller number of rocks compared to Alice. So if Alice
				has 5 rocks, we need to subtract to get the number of rocks that Bob has, which means Bob has 2 rocks.
			</p>
		</solution>
	</activity>
	<p>
		In the example, the mathematical operation that was required was subtraction, but "more" means to add (if you
		believe in the rule-based key word approach). And so this leads us to the question of what's really happening in
		the word problem. 
	</p>
	<activity xml:id="sec-mr-1-ac2-relationship">
		<title>Mathematical Relationships</title>
		<p>
			In most word problems, the words do not directly describe mathematical operations that you need to perform.
			They are not instructions. Rather, they are representations of mathematical equations using words. In the
			example above, the relationship is "Alice has more rocks than Bob." We can translate this into the
			following:
			<me>
				\begin{array}{c}
					a = \text{The number of rocks Alice has} \\
					b = \text{The number of rocks Bob has} \\ \\
					a = b + 3
				\end{array}
			</me> 
		</p>
		<p>
			There are some key points to remember. The first is that the variables used are all defined. This is an
			important element of communication. If you introduce a symbol, you need to be clear what the symbol means.
			Furthermore, it's not acceptable to say that <m>a</m> represents "Alice." Variables are symbols that represent a
			quantity or a mathematical expression. Alice is a person, not a number. So it is good to get into the habit
			of being accurate in describing your variables. 
		</p>
		<p>
			Once we have the relationship established, we can then move to plug in the variables. If we are told that
			"Bob has 5 rocks" then we can set <m>b = 5</m> and solve: 
			<me>
				\begin{aligned}
					a \amp = b + 3 \\
					5 \amp = b + 3 \amp \eqnspacer \amp \text{Substitute $a = 5$} \\
					b \amp = 2 \amp \amp \text{Subtract $3$ from both sides} 
				\end{aligned}
			</me>
			Or we are told that "Alice has rocks" then we can set <m>a = 5</m> and solve: 
			<me>
				\begin{aligned}
					a \amp = b + 3 \\
					5 \amp = b + 3 \amp \eqnspacer \amp \text{Substitute $a = 5$} \\
					b \amp = 2 \amp \amp \text{Subtract $3$ from both sides} 
				\end{aligned}
			</me>
		</p>
		<p>
			The actual decision to add or subtract is based on the relationship that is established by the words, not
			through identifying a specific word as if it were an instruction. This distinction once again highlights
			mathematical thinking. You're not looking for a specific rule or algorithm to follow, you're looking to
			understand a relationship so that you can apply the appropriate tool to solve your problem. 
		</p>
		<p>
			If you are unsure about the mathematical relationship you've created, it can always be checked by plugging
			in a couple numbers. There is clarity in examining specific values that can sometimes be lost when looking
			at symbols. For example, when reading <m>a = b + 3</m> some students will think that <m>b</m> is the bigger
			value "because 3 is being added to it." But this is not true, and the clearest way to see it is to just pick a
			value of <m>b</m> and see what the formula actually gives as the result. 
		</p>
		<aside>
			<p>
				Implicit in writing the relationship is that you should define your variables. 
			</p>
		</aside>
		<p>
			<alert xml:id="sec-mr-1-ac2-ti">Try it!</alert>
		</p>
		<p>
			Annika is 4 inches taller than Carlos. Write an equation that describes this relationship. 
		</p>
		<solution>
			<p>
				<me>
					\begin{array}{c}
						a = \text{Annika's height in inches} \\
						c = \text{Carlos' height in inches} \\ \\
						a = c + 4
					\end{array}
				</me> 
			</p>
		</solution>
	</activity>
	<activity xml:id="sec-mr-1-ac3-full-word-problem">
		<title>Solving a Full Word Problem</title>
		<p>
			Once a mathematical relationship is established, it then becomes the foundation for solving a word problem
			based on that relationship. 
		</p>
		<p>
			<alert xml:id="sec-mr-1-ac3-ti">Try it!</alert>
		</p>
		<p>
			Annika is 70 inches tall. She is also 4 inches taller than Carlos. How tall is Carlos? 
		</p>
		<solution>
			<p>
				<me>
					\begin{aligned}
					a \amp = c + 4 \\
					70 \amp = c + 4 \amp \amp \text{Substitute $a = 70$} \\
					c \amp = 66 \amp \amp \text{Subtract $4$ from both sides} 
					\end{aligned}
				</me>
			</p>
		</solution>
	</activity>
	<p>
		Students shy away from word problems because of the extra step of effort that's required to translate the words
		into mathematical symbols. However, that extra step is the step that covers the gap between "real life" and
		mathematics. Making that connection is an important piece of the puzzle for mathematical thinking. 
	</p>
	<p>
		In addition to having mathematical relationships described by words, there are situations where the relationship
		is described by a chart of values.
		<me>
			\begin{array}{c|c}
				x \amp y \\ \hline
				1 \amp 2 \\
				2 \amp 4 \\
				3 \amp 6
			\end{array}
		</me>
		After some thought, the pattern that you will likely see is that <m>y = 2x</m>. And you can check this by
		plugging in values. 
	</p>
	<aside>
		<p>
			You might want to try to figure out how we got that other equation. 
		</p>
	</aside>
	<p>
		It turns out that there are all sorts of formulas that would match those values. If you were to use the equation
		<m>y = -\frac{1}{6} x^3 + x^2 + \frac{1}{6} x + 1</m>, you would find that it also works! However, for these
		problems we are going to stick with the "obvious" answer and not worry about more complicated relationships. 
	</p>
	<activity xml:id="sec-mr-1-ac4-find-relationship">
		<title>Finding a Mathematical Relationship</title>
		<p>
			When trying to find a formula that matches a given table, there is no magic formula. And while there is a
			computational method if you can guess the "form" of the equation, it's better to develop intuition. The
			relationships that you will be given to work with are going to be relatively simple, and you should be able
			to come up with them by trying to think logically and in an organized manner. 
		</p>
		<aside>
			<p>
				There are multiple ways to represent the relationship. Just make sure that your form works for the
				given values. 
			</p>
		</aside>
		<p>
			<alert xml:id="sec-mr-1-ac4-ti">Try it!</alert>
		</p>
		<p>
			Find a formula that relates and based on the following chart. 
			<me>
				\begin{array}{c|c}
					x \amp y \\ \hline
					1 \amp 9 \\
					4 \amp 6 \\
					8 \amp 2
				\end{array}
			</me> 
		</p>
		<solution>
			<aside>
				<p>
					Your answer may vary, but it must be equivalent to the one provided. 
				</p>
			</aside>
			<p>
				<me> x + y = 10 </me> 
			</p>
		</solution>
	</activity>
</section>
