<section xml:id="sec-nonl-5-deeper">
	<title>Going Deeper: The Absolute Value Function</title>
	<p>
		Consider the following question: Is -1,000,000 a bigger number than 1? The answer you give depends on how you
		interpret the notion of size. For example, we can say that <m>1 \gt -1,000,000</m> by just thinking about the
		number line, and if we think that "bigger" is the same as "greater than" we can conclude that -1,000,000 is not
		bigger than 1. On the other hand, if you think about "bigger" as meaning the "size" of a number, then we might
		conclude that -1,000,000 is a pretty big number relative to 1. The notion of the "size" of a number is not
		captured by the inequalities we used earlier, and so we need to introduce a new mathematical object. 
	</p>
	<p>
		The <em>absolute value</em> of a number has several different representations, and the choice of representation
		depends on the details of the situation. We will start with the geometric interpretation. 
	</p>
	<aside>
		<p>
			Implicitly, the distance is a nonnegative value. If we need something like a negative distance, then it's
			better to use displacement. 
		</p>
	</aside>

    <definition xml:id="def-absolute-value-distance">
        <title>Absolute Value</title>
        <idx><h>absolute value</h> <h>as distance</h> </idx>
        
        <statement>
            <p>
				The <term>absolute value</term> of a number <m>x</m> is denoted by <m>|x|</m> and is the distance
				between 0 and <m>x</m> on the number line.
            </p>
        </statement>
    </definition>

	<p>
		Because of how the number line is constructed, it's easy to see that when <m>x \gt 0</m>, we have
		<m>|x| = x</m>. Here is an example of that:
	</p>
	<image xml:id="sec-nonl-5-positive-abs-value" width="60%">
		<latex-image>
			\begin{tikzpicture}
				\draw[stealth-stealth] (-1,0) -- (7,0); 
				\foreach \i in {0,...,6} {
					\draw[fill=black] (\i, 0) circle (0.1); 
					\draw (\i, -0.1) node[anchor=north] {\small $\i$}; 
				}
				\draw (0,0) -- ++ (0,1); 
				\draw[stealth-stealth] (0,0.5) -- ++ (5,0) node[midway,anchor=south] {\strut \small $|5| = 5$}; 
				\draw (5,0) -- ++ (0,1); 
			\end{tikzpicture} 
		</latex-image>
	</image>
	<p>
		When we have a negative number, takes the value of when we ignore the negative sign. 
	</p>
	<image xml:id="sec-nonl-5-negative-abs-value" width="60%">
		<latex-image>
			\begin{tikzpicture}
				\draw[stealth-stealth] (-7,0) -- (1,0); 
				\foreach \i in {0,...,6} {
					\draw[fill=black] (-\i, 0) circle (0.1); 
					\draw (-\i, -0.1) node[anchor=north] {\small $-\i$}; 
				}
				\draw (0,0) -- ++ (0,1); 
				\draw[stealth-stealth] (0,0.5) -- ++ (-5,0) node[midway,anchor=south] {\strut \small $|-5| = 5$}; 
				\draw (-5,0) -- ++ (0,1); 
			\end{tikzpicture} 
		</latex-image>
	</image>
	<aside>
		<p>
			If you pay close attention, you'll see that the definition of absolute value invokes the concept of
			distance, but then we later say that distance is the absolute value of displacement. This feels like
			circular reasoning, but it's actually a reflection of what concepts you're using as your assumptions. For
			our definition of absolute value, we're using your intuitive notion of distance as the starting point. 
		</p>
	</aside>
	<p>
		<idx><h>distance</h></idx>
		This framework for the absolute value should remind you of some of the ideas we used when we were working with
		subtraction. In fact, we can use this to define the distance between two points. The <em>distance</em> between
		the numbers <m>a</m> and <m>b</m> is <m>|b - a|</m>. Notice that this has the same value as <m>|a - b|</m>. You
		will see both definitions used, but the first definition draws a better connection between distance and
		displacement. In fact, sometimes distance is simply defined to be the absolute value of the displacement, and
		you're just expected to know how to compute the displacement. 
	</p>
	<image xml:id="sec-nonl-5-distance-a-to-b">
		<latex-image>
			\begin{tikzpicture}
				\draw[stealth-stealth] (-6,0) -- (6,0); 
				\draw (-4, -0.1) node[anchor=north] {\small \strut $a$}; 
				\draw[fill=black] (-4, 0) circle (0.1); 
				\draw (4, -0.1) node[anchor=north] {\small \strut $b$}; 
				\draw[fill=black] (4, 0) circle (0.1); 
				\draw (-4,0) -- ++ (0,1); 
				\draw[stealth-stealth] (-4,0.5) -- ++ (8,0) node[midway,anchor=south] {\strut \small $|b-a|$}; 
				\draw (4,0) -- ++ (0,1); 
			\end{tikzpicture} 
		</latex-image>
	</image>
	<p>
		The algebraic definition is slightly more complicated because it requires a special type of notation: 
	</p>
    <definition xml:id="def-absolute-value-algebra" width="80%">
        <title>Absolute Value</title>
        <idx><h>absolute value</h> <h>algebraic</h> </idx>
        
        <statement>
            <p>
				The <term>absolute value</term> of a number <m>x</m> is denoted by <m>|x|</m> and is given by the
				following formula:
				<me>
					|x| = \begin{cases}
						x \amp \text{if $x \geq 0$} \\
						-x \amp \text{if $x \lt 0$}
					\end{cases}
				</me>
            </p>
        </statement>
    </definition>
	<p>
		<idx><h>piecewise defined function</h></idx>
		We first need to describe this notation. This is the notation that is used for a
		<term>piecewise defined function</term>, which is a function that uses different formulas depending on the value
		that it has been given. You can see that this definition is broken into two parts. The first formula is applied
		when <m>x \geq 0</m> and the second formula is applied when <m>x \lt 0</m>. This means that you have to decide
		which category your number is in before you apply the formulas. If you take a precalculus course, you will
		probably run into this idea there and get a lot more experience. For now, it is enough to understand that this
		is a special way of building a function using multiple different pieces. 
	</p>
	<p>
		From this definition, we can see that this is the same as we had with the geometric definition. When the value
		of <m>x</m> is positive, then we have <m>|x| = x</m>. This is also true when <m>x = 0</m>. When <m>x</m> is
		negative, the geometric definition led us to ignoring the negative sign. Unfortunately, that concept doesn't
		have a good algebraic equivalent. However, it's computationally true that the negative of a negative number is a
		positive number, and so that's how we communicate it. 
	</p>
	<p>
		Working with equations involving absolute value can feel very different depending on whether you're thinking
		about it from the geometric perspective or the algebraic perspective. For example, let's consider the equation
		<m>|x| = 4</m>. 
	</p>
	<p>
		Geometrically, this is asking us to find the numbers that are a distance 4 from the number 0. And we can
		immediately determine this by looking at the number line and moving 4 spaces in either direction starting at the
		origin.
	</p>
	<image xml:id="sec-nonl-5-abs-value-solve" width="80%">
		<latex-image>
			\begin{tikzpicture}
			\draw[stealth-stealth] (-6,0) -- (6,0); 
			\foreach \i in {-5,...,5} {
				\draw[fill=black] (\i, 0) circle (0.1); 
				\draw (\i, -0.1) node[anchor=north] {\small $\i$}; 
			}
			\draw (0,0) -- ++ (0,1); 
			\draw[stealth-stealth] (0,0.5) -- ++ (-4,0) node[midway,anchor=south] {\strut \small $|-4| = 4$}; 
			\draw (-4,0) -- ++ (0,1); 
			\draw[stealth-stealth] (0,0.5) -- ++ (4,0) node[midway,anchor=south] {\strut \small $|4| = 4$}; 
			\draw (4,0) -- ++ (0,1); 
			\end{tikzpicture} 
		</latex-image>
	</image>
	<p>
		This tells us that the solutions are <m>x = -4</m> and <m>x = 4</m>. We can express this as <m>x = \pm 4</m>,
		where the symbol <m>\pm</m> is a shorthand for two different possibilities. 
	</p>
	<p>
		In order to solve this from the algebraic perspective, we need to think about the two different situations. When
		<m>x \geq 0</m>, we have <m>|x| = x</m>, so that the equation becomes <m>x = 4</m>. On the other hand, if
		<m>x \lt 0</m>, then <m>|x| = -x</m>, so that our equation becomes <m>-x = 4</m>, which we can solve to get
		<m>x = -4</m>. We still arrived at <m>x = \pm 4</m> as the solution, but it required us to work with two
		different cases. Here is one way of presenting that work:
		<me>
			\begin{array}{c}
				|x| = 4 \\  \\
				\begin{array}{c}
					\text{If $x \geq 0$:} \\ \begin{aligned} x \amp = 4 \\ \\ \end{aligned}
				\end{array} \qquad
				\begin{array}{c}
					\text{If $x \lt 0$:} \\ \begin{aligned} -x \amp = 4 \\ x \amp = -4 \end{aligned}
				\end{array}
			\end{array}
		</me> 
	</p>
	<p>
		The same ideas can be employed for more complicated equations. When you have mathematical expressions inside of
		the absolute value sign, you need to treat that as a single object.
		<me>
			\begin{array}{c}
				|x + 7| = 3 \\  \\
				\begin{array}{c}
					\text{If $x + 7 \geq 0$:} \\ \begin{aligned} x + 7 \amp = 3 \\ x \amp = -4 \\ \\ \end{aligned}
				\end{array} \qquad
				\begin{array}{c}
					\text{If $x + 7 \lt 0$:} \\ \begin{aligned} -(x + 7) \amp = 3 \\ x + 7 \amp = -3 \\ x \amp = -10 \end{aligned}
				\end{array}
			\end{array}
		</me> 
	</p>
	<p>
		Most textbooks do this calculation in a much more condensed presentation: 
		<me>
			\begin{aligned}
				| x + 7 | \amp = 3 \\
				x + 7 \amp = \pm 3 \\
				x \amp = -7 \pm 3 \\ x \amp = -4 \text{ or } -10 
			\end{aligned}
		</me>
	</p>
	<p>
		This is ultimately the same process, but it starts to mask some of the ideas and turns it more into an exercise
		of executing rote calculations rather than providing insight into how the absolute value function works. Since
		our focus is on the ideas, we've left it in the slightly longer form. Ultimately, you can do this however you
		choose. 
	</p>
	<p>
		There's a catch to the algebraic approach, which is that it is possible to go through the algebra and get an
		answer, but find that the answers don't satisfy the original equation. For example, let's look at
		<m>|x| = -4</m>. If we simply pushed ahead with the algebra, it would look like this:
		<me>
			\begin{array}{c}
				|x| = -4 \\  \\
				\begin{array}{c}
					\text{If $x \geq 0$:} \\ \begin{aligned} x \amp = -4 \\ \\ \end{aligned}
				\end{array} \qquad
				\begin{array}{c}
					\text{If $x \lt 0$:} \\ \begin{aligned} -x \amp = -4 \\ x \amp = 4 \end{aligned}
				\end{array}
			\end{array}
		</me> 
		If we only looked at the last lines, we would say that <m>x = \pm 4</m>, just as before. But if we tried to plug
		those values in, we would find that they aren't actually solutions. 
	</p>
	<p>
		<idx><h>solutions</h> <h>apparent</h> </idx>
		<idx><h>solutions</h> <h>phantom</h> </idx>
		The problem is that the conclusion in each column is in contradiction with the assumption. On the left, we were
		supposing that is a nonnegative number, but we concluded that <m>x = -4</m>. On the right, we have a similar
		problem. These are sometimes called <term>apparent</term> solutions (or sometimes <term>phantom</term>
		solutions) because they seem like they should be solutions even though they aren't. 
	</p>
	<p>
		There are a number of methods that you can employ to identify these situations. The first is to simply check
		that your solutions really work in the original equation. This is the most common approach that math textbooks
		teach. The reason this is often suggested is that it's straight-forward to perform all the calculations, and you
		don't really have to think very much about what's going on. You can simply grind out the calculations from
		beginning to end without really thinking about things. And from a practical perspective, there's nothing wrong
		with this approach. It will get the job done. 
	</p>
	<p>
		However, It can be helpful to practice being more thoughtful. By thinking ahead, you can sometimes save yourself
		the extra work by simply asking whether your absolute value equation is equal to a positive or a negative value.
		For the equation <m>|x| = -4</m>, we can immediately conclude that there are no solutions because the absolute
		value function will never give a negative value. 
	</p>
	<p>
		Ultimately, neither approach is inherently better or worse. For simpler equations, thinking ahead can save some
		work. But there are more complicated examples (such as when the variable is both inside and outside the absolute
		value) where it can be more work to think through the possibilities than to simply grind out the algebra and
		check to see if they work. Regardless of the approach, this is a feature that you will need to keep in mind when
		solving equations involving the absolute value signs. 
	</p>
	<p>
		(There is another set of complications that arise when working with absolute value inequalities. You end up
		needing to work with compound intervals and paying close attention to the exact form of your equation. These
		skills are sometimes taught in courses, but sometimes not. It usually ends up being another set of memorized
		algebraic rules, and it has limited value to students at this level. So we're just not going to go there.)
	</p>
</section>
