<section xml:id="sec-fqp-4-closing">
	<title>Closing Ideas</title>
	<p>
		As mentioned earlier, factoring quadratic polynomials is viewed as an important marker of your algebraic skill
		level. But the skill isn't just in getting the answer. In fact, the bulk of mathematics is not about getting
		the answer. If you look back over everything we've done so far, you will see that there is a heavy emphasis on
		understanding and communicating the thought processes involved in performing these algebraic manipulations. 
	</p>
	<aside>
		<p>
			Do you know why these are true? Or is it just another thing that you memorized at some point? 
		</p>
	</aside>
	<p>
		On the last worksheet page, instead of having you do more factorizations, you were asked to seek out patterns in
		the factorizations you've already done. You were only asked to identify the information you could conclude in
		each situation, but you were hopefully also able to discover the underlying logic. That logic goes all the way
		back to basic arithmetic, with ideas such as the following: 
		<ul>
			<li>
				<p>
					A positive number multiplied by a positive number is a positive number.
				</p>
			</li>
			<li>
				<p>
					A negative number multiplied by a negative number is a positive number.
				</p>
			</li>
			<li>
				<p>
					A positive number multiplied by a negative number is a negative number.
				</p>
			</li>
			<li>
				<p>
					A negative number multiplied by a positive number is a negative number.
				</p>
			</li>			
		</ul>
	</p>
	<aside>
		<p>
			The third one may feel a bit tricky if you don't slow down. Remember the skill of thinking about specific
			numbers. Pick a large positive number and add a small negative to it. What is the sign of the result? 
		</p>
	</aside>
	<p>
		There are also ideas that perhaps we don't have "memorized" phrases for, but should make sense when you think
		about it. 
		<ul>
			<li>
				<p>
					A positive number plus a positive number is a positive number. 
				</p>
			</li>
			<li>
				<p>
					A negative number plus a negative number is a negative number. 
				</p>
			</li>
			<li>
				<p>
					When adding a positive and a negative number together, the sign of the result will match the sign of
					the number that is larger (in absolute value).
				</p>
			</li>
		</ul>
	</p>
	<p>
		Factoring quadratic polynomials is not an end in and of itself. It is a tool that allows you to do advanced
		algebraic manipulations, such as solving more complicated equations. So we usually do not use it in complete
		isolation. There is an important property of numbers that can be a useful supplemental tool.
	</p>
    <theorem xml:id="thm-zero-product-property">
        <title>Zero Product Property</title>
        <idx><h>zero product property</h></idx>
        
        <statement>
            <p>
				The <term>zero product property</term> states that if <m>a \cdot b = 0</m>, then we must have either
				<m>a = 0</m> or <m>b = 0</m> (or possibly both).
            </p>
        </statement>
    </theorem>

	<p>
		The combination of factoring with the zero product property allows you to take an equation with higher degree
		and convert it into multiple equations of lower degree. Here is an example of solving the equation
		<m>x^2 + 3x - 4 = 0</m>:
		<me>
			\begin{array}{ccl}
			    \begin{aligned}
        			x^2 + 3x - 4 \amp = 0 \\
        			(x-1)(x+4) \amp = 0
    			\end{aligned} \amp \phantom{.}\hspace{1cm}\phantom{.} \amp
    			\begin{aligned}
        			\\
        		\amp \text{Factor} \\
    			\end{aligned} \\
				\begin{array}{rlcrl}
					x - 1 \amp = 0 \amp \phantom{.}\hspace{5mm} \text{or} \hspace{5mm}\phantom{.} \amp x + 4 \amp = 0 \\
					x \amp = 1 \amp \amp x \amp = -4
				\end{array} \amp \amp 
				\begin{aligned}
					\amp \text{The zero product property} \\
					\amp \text{Solve each equation} \\
				\end{aligned}
			\end{array}
		</me> 
	</p>
	<aside>
		<p>
			Think of two non-zero numbers and multiply them together. Is the result ever zero? 
		</p>
	</aside>
	<p>
		Notice how the factorization was reduced to just a single step and that none of the steps for solving the
		equation were justified. When you get further along in your math courses, you will be expected to know how to do
		many of those steps for yourself, which is why we're strongly emphasizing the steps here. We are creating a
		foundation for you to build on in the future. 
	</p>
	<p>
		In this section, we can see the full scaffolded nature of algebraic reasoning. The skill of factoring is right
		in the middle of the tower. Below us, we see that everything we're doing is premised on having basic fluency
		with algebraic concepts such as the distributive property, and it also requires us to have enough experience
		with numbers to search through different combinations to find the one we want. Above us, we see that there's an
		entirely new set of equations that we can solve once we add in some more ideas. Every time you learn a new idea
		in mathematics, you should take a step back to see how it fits into the bigger picture.
	</p>
</section>
