<section xml:id="sec-rme-1-main">
	<title>So Many Symbols!</title>
	<objectives>
		<ul>
			<li>
				<p>
					Correctly write and interpret algebraic expressions.
				</p>
			</li>
			<li>
				<p>
					Recognize common algebraic errors.
				</p>
			</li>
			<li>
				<p>
					Solve linear equations
				</p>
			</li>
		</ul>
	</objectives>
	<aside>
		<p>
			We've mentioned before that math can be understood as a language. This is just another example of that. 
		</p>
	</aside>
	<p>
		As we continue forward into higher levels of mathematics, we will encounter more mathematical notation. Students
		sometimes start to struggle because they've never developed a set of tools to help them interpret those symbols.
		It's like trying to read a language when you don't have a sense of the grammar. You can sometimes piece things
		together and follow what's happening, but most of the time you're completely lost. 
	</p>
	<p>
		We will begin with familiar territory. At some point in their lives, most students learned some version of the
		order of operations (often called PEMDAS). This is a set of instructions for the correct way to perform a complex
		calculation by prioritizing certain calculations. Here is how the order of operations is usually presented: 
		<ul>
			<li>
				<p>
					Parentheses and other grouping symbols. 
				</p>
			</li>
			<li>
				<p>
					Exponents 
				</p>
			</li>
			<li>
				<p>
					Multiplication and division (performed left-to-right) 
				</p>
			</li>
			<li>
				<p>
					Addition and subtraction (performed left-to-right) 
				</p>
			</li>
		</ul>
	</p>
	<aside>
		<p>
			Unfortunately, some students learn this as "multiplication THEN division" and "addition THEN subtraction"
			which is incorrect. Do you see the difference?
		</p>
	</aside>
	<p>
		This is fine as far as the basics are concerned. And when working with numbers, students are usually able to do
		this correctly. But it's not long after we start introducing variables that students can feel overwhelmed by
		symbols. 
	</p>
	<p>
		The best analogy for understanding this comes from thinking about a complex sentence in English: "The man
		carrying a large bag containing three apples and two pears bought a blue shirt with six silver buttons from the
		store on the corner of Main Street and West Park Avenue." There are a lot of details in that sentence, but
		there's also the "big picture" of the sentence. What is actually happening in the sentence? Some man bought a
		shirt from a store. From there we can go into specific details, such as what the man was holding, the color of
		the shirt, and the location of the store. But those details add information to the big picture without changing
		the core of the picture. 
	</p>
	<p>
		The focus of this section is not really on algebra, but on helping you familiarize yourself with the language of
		mathematics. Fortunately, mathematicians have created an entire notation to help you do this. Consider the
		following polynomial:
		<me>
			x^3 - 3x^2 - 7x + 11
		</me>
		At this point, your experience should lead you to interpret this as the sum of four terms. You should be able to
		visualize the plus and minus signs as being separators for the different terms. Compare this to how we would
		have to write it if we had to write everything out:
		<me>
			x \cdot x \cdot x + (-3) \cdot x \cdot x + (-7) \cdot x + 11
		
		</me>
	</p>
	<aside>
		<p>
			We still have to use order of operations with multiplication and addition. 
		</p>
	</aside>
	<p>
		It is much harder for our brains to process this because we have to do a lot of extra work. It's harder to
		locate the plus signs from among all of the symbols, and we have to count out all of the products to figure
		out how many factors of there are. 
	</p>
	<p>
		The two key features here are the use of implied multiplication and exponents. These two bits of notation help
		us to visually condense the information and make it easier to read. The exponents also mean that we don't have
		to count out the products. We also have the convention that subtraction means addition of the opposite, which
		lets us write the negative coefficients as subtraction. 
	</p>
	<aside>
		<p>
			Implied multiplication is when we write two symbols next to each other to indicate multiplication instead of
			using a multiplication symbol between them. 
		</p>
	</aside>
	<p>
		All of this notation helps us to identify that the "big picture" of this is that we have a sum of four terms.
		From there, we can choose to look at the details of those terms to see (for example) if there are any like terms
		that we might want to combine. 
	</p>
	<p>
		Another mathematical notation that was developed is the use of fractions for division. Interestingly, it's very
		rare in the modern mathematical world to use the <m>\div</m> symbol. It is not as rare, but still uncommon to
		use <m>/</m> to represent division as well. These tend to cause more confusion than clarity, which is why modern
		mathematics prefers the use of a fraction. This way, we can clearly distinguish between the numerator and
		denominator of a fraction.
	</p>
	<aside>
		<p>
			If you've ever seen the meme about calculating <m>8 \div 2(2+2)</m>, then you've seen how the
			symbol is problematic. It's not so much a math problem as it is a pedantry problem. 
		</p>
	</aside>
	<p>
		For example, consider the following expression: <m>x^2 + 3/x + 2</m>. The strict (and proper) application of the
		order of operations is that this result is the same as <m>x^2 + \frac{3}{x} + 2</m>. But students will write
		that to mean <m>\frac{x^2 + 3}{x + 2}</m>. If you insist on writing your fractions with a diagonal slash, you
		will need to use parentheses to separate out the numerator and the denominator: <m>(x^2 + 3)/(x + 2)</m>. 
	</p>
	<aside>
		<p>
			Note: Please do not insist on using the diagonal slash 
		</p>
	</aside>
	<p>
		For this reason, students are strongly urged to not use the diagonal slash for division, but write their
		division using a long horizontal bar (long enough to span the width of all the terms in the numerator and the
		denominator) so that it is clear what is in the numerator and what is in the denominator. 
	</p>
	<p>
		Similarly, when using the square root, it is important that the bar of the square root is long enough (and only
		long enough) to cover the parts inside the square root. For example, <m>\sqrt{x + 3}</m> is not the same as
		<m>\sqrt{x} + 3</m>, and <m>\sqrt{x \,+ \, } \, 3</m> doesn't even make sense. So please be careful with what
		you're writing. 
	</p>
	<activity xml:id="sec-rme-1-ac1-big-picture">
		<title>Identifying the "Big Picture" of an Expression</title>
		<p>
			A basic skill when learning to read mathematical notation is to mentally "group together" things to be able
			to process what's happening. For example, the polynomial from before can be seen as the sum of four terms.
			<me>
				x^3 - 3x^2 - 7x + 11
					\longrightarrow \boxed{x^3} + \boxed{(-3x^2)} + \boxed{ (-7x) } + \boxed{11}
					\longrightarrow \boxed{A} + \boxed{B} + \boxed{C} + \boxed{D}
			</me>
			Similarly, we can think of fractions as being basically a numerator divided by a denominator.
			<me>
				\frac{x^2 + 3}{x + 2}
					\longrightarrow \frac{\boxed{x^2 + 3}}{\boxed{ x + 2} }
					\longrightarrow \frac{ \boxed{A} }{\boxed{B}}
			</me> 
		</p>
		<aside>
			<p>
				There is no standard language for this. But potential examples are "this is a division calculation" or
				"this is a sum." 
			</p>
		</aside>
		<p>
			<alert xml:id="sec-rme-1-ac1-ti">Try it!</alert>
		</p>
		<p>
			Consider the expression <m>\frac{x + 3}{x - 2} + 3x</m>. Describe the "big picture" perspective of the
			expression and put boxes around the terms as appropriate.
		</p>
		<solution>
			<aside>
				<p>
					If you also put boxes around the numerator and the denominator, that would also be acceptable. But
					the "big picture" is the sum of two terms. 
				</p>
			</aside>
			<p>
				<me> \boxed{ \frac{ x + 3 }{ x - 2 } } + \boxed{ 3x } </me> 
			</p>
			<p>
				This is the sum of a fraction and a monomial. 
			</p>
		</solution>
	</activity>
	<p>
		After seeing the "big picture" we can then break things down further. Once we're inside of the numerator or the
		denominator of the fraction, and that may consist of multiple terms.
		<me>
			\frac{x^2 + 3}{x + 2}
				\longrightarrow \frac{\boxed{x^2 + 3}}{\boxed{ x + 2} }
				\longrightarrow \frac{\boxed{ \boxed{x^2} + \boxed{3} }} {\boxed{ \boxed{x} + \boxed{2} } }
				\longrightarrow \frac{ \boxed{\boxed{A} + \boxed{B} }}{\boxed{\boxed{C} + \boxed{D}}}
		</me> 
	</p>
	<aside>
		<p>
			It's rare that you have to diagram a sentence to understand it. Sometimes, you may need to reread a portion
			of it, and the same is going to be true of reading mathematical sentences. 
		</p>
	</aside>
	<p>
		And we can go deeper into the individual terms and break them up into the coefficient (which is sometimes an
		unwritten and the variable part. And the variable part can be broken down into individual variables. But at this
		point, it's like focusing on the number of apples in the bag and you've lost sight of the big picture. 
	</p>
	<p>
		But so far, we've only focused on the basic arithmetic operations. The next large piece of language you will
		encounter are functions. We aren't going to go into the details of what functions are here. We're just going to
		use the notation to help you understand how to think about it when you get to them. 
	</p>
	<p>
		The basic shape of a function is <m>f(x)</m>. This represents a number just like the variable <m>y</m> would
		represent a number. The	only difference is that with a function, there is a "rule" that tells you how to
		calculate the number. When we write <m>f(x)</m> we are saying to use the rule associated with <m>f</m> to do the
		calculation. In addition to the letters <m>f</m> and <m>g</m> (which are used for generic functions), there are
		also a number of special functions that have names. Here are a few examples:
		<tabular>
			<row>
				<cell>Name</cell>
				<cell>Notation</cell>
			</row>
			<row>
				<cell>sine</cell>
				<cell><m>\sin()</m></cell>
			</row>
			<row>
				<cell>cosine</cell>
				<cell><m>\cos()</m></cell>
			</row>
			<row>
				<cell>tangent</cell>
				<cell><m>\tan()</m></cell>
			</row>
			<row>
				<cell>common logarithm</cell>
				<cell><m>\log()</m></cell>
			</row>
			<row>
				<cell>natural logarithm</cell>
				<cell><m>\ln()</m></cell>
			</row>
			<row>
				<cell>exponential</cell>
				<cell><m>\exp()</m></cell>
			</row>
		</tabular>
	</p>
	<p>
		The empty parentheses indicate that there is a value to "plug into" the function. So there would normally be
		some expression inside of those parentheses, which can be a number (such as with <m>\ln(2)</m>), a variable
		(such as with <m>\sin(x)</m>) or a variable expression (such as with <m>\exp(-x^2 + 1)</m>).
	</p>
	<p>
		At this point, it doesn't matter what these functions represent, other than they represent a method for
		calculating some specific number. So it doesn't matter that <m>\ln(2) \approx 0.693</m>, only that <m>\ln(2)</m>
		is some number that your calculator can calculate for you. 
	</p>
	<p>
		At least in terms of algebra, functions behave very similarly to variables. Here are some examples: 
		<me>
			\begin{aligned}
			2f(x) + 3f(x) \amp = 5f(x) \\
			x \ln(3) - x \amp = (\ln(3) - 1)x 
			\end{aligned}
		</me>
	</p>
	<aside>
		<p>
			Think of "factoring out" the appropriate symbols. 
		</p>
	</aside>
	<p>
		The important note is that the function name cannot be separated from its argument (the parentheses and
		everything inside of the parentheses). All of that notation should be seen as a single object. That is,
		you cannot factor out the <m>f</m> in the first example:
		<me>
			2f(x) + 3f(x) \overset{\times}{=} f(2(x) + 3(x))
		</me>
		It may help for you to put a box around the function and its argument.
		<me>
			2f(x) + 3f(x) = 2 \, \boxed{ f(x) } + 3 \, \boxed{ f(x) }
		</me> 
	</p>
	<aside>
		<p>
			In practice, you will probably just do this mentally. 
		</p>
	</aside>
	<p>
		The error of breaking apart the function from its argument is similar to other errors where students
		"distribute" incorrectly: 
	</p>
	<aside>
		<p>
			In fact, all of these errors are of the same type. They are all misinterpretations of function notation. 
		</p>
	</aside>
	<p>
		<me>
			\begin{aligned}
				\frac{1}{a + b} \amp \overset{\times}{=} \frac{1}{a} + \frac{1}{b} \\
				(x + y)^2 \amp \overset{\times}{=} x^2 + y^2 \\
				\sqrt{n + m} \amp \overset{\times}{=} \sqrt{n} + \sqrt{m} \\
				\sqrt{n^2 + m^2} \amp \overset{\times}{=} n + m \\
				\sin(\theta + \phi) \amp \overset{\times}{=} \sin(\theta) + \sin(\phi) 
			\end{aligned}
		</me>
		It all comes down to not understanding what the symbols mean or how they behave. 
	</p>
	<activity xml:id="sec-rme-1-ac2-box-substitutions">
		<title>Hiding Information in Boxes</title>
		<aside>
			<p>
				This is a lot like ignoring the details what was in the man's bag in the complex sentence we used
				earlier. 
			</p>
		</aside>
		<p>
			Students often feel intimidated by the notation. One trick is to think of the the function as being hidden
			inside of a box. This will "hide" the details so that you can focus on the big picture. 
			<me>
				\begin{aligned}
					x \ln(3) + 4 \amp = \ln(6) \\
					x \cdot \boxed{ A } + 4 \amp = \boxed{ B } \amp \eqnspacer \amp \text{Substitute} \\
					x \cdot \boxed{ A } \amp = \boxed{ B } - 4 \amp \amp \text{Subtract $4$ from both sides} \\
					x \amp = \frac{ \boxed{ B } - 4}{\boxed{A}} \amp \amp \text{Divide both sides by $\boxed{A}$} \\
					x \amp = \frac{ \ln(6) - 4}{\ln(3)} \amp \amp \text{Substitute} 
				\end{aligned}
			</me>
		</p>
		<aside>
			<p>
				It is more traditional to use variables to replace expressions rather than boxes. However, students tend
				to connect better to the boxes than variables, at least at first. The long-term goal is to not need to
				use substitutions at all. 
			</p>
		</aside>
		<p>
			<alert xml:id="sec-rme-1-ac2-ti">Try it!</alert>
		</p>
		<p>
			Solve the equation <m>x \sin(1) + 5 = 3x - \cos(2)</m>. Do it once using a substitution similar to the
			example above, and then do it without that substitution. Use a complete presentation both times. 
		</p>
		<solution>
			<p>
				<me>
					\begin{aligned}
						x \sin(1) + 5 \amp = 3x - \cos(2) \\
						x \cdot \boxed{ A } + 5 \amp = 3x - \boxed{ B } \amp \amp \text{Substitute} \\
						x \cdot \boxed{ A } \amp = 3x - \boxed{ B } - 5 \amp \amp \text{Subtract $5$ from both sides} \\
						x \cdot \boxed{ A } - 3x \amp = - \boxed{ B } - 5 \amp \amp \text{Subtract $3x$ from both sides} \\
						\left( \boxed{ A } - 3 \right) x \amp = - \boxed{ B } - 5 \amp \amp \text{Factor out the $x$} \\
						x \amp = \frac{ - \boxed{B} - 5}{\boxed{A} - 3} \amp \amp \text{Divide by $\boxed{A} - 3$} \\
						x \amp = \frac{ - \cos(2) - 5}{\sin(1) - 3} \amp \amp \text{Substitute} 
					\end{aligned}
				</me>
			</p>
			<p>
				<me>
					\begin{aligned}
						x \sin(1) + 5 \amp = 3x - \cos(2) \\
						x \sin(1) \amp = 3x - \cos(2) - 5 \amp \amp \text{Subtract $5$ from both sides} \\
						x \sin(1) - 3x \amp = - \cos(2) - 5 \amp \amp \text{Subtract $3x$ from both sides} \\
						\left( \sin(1) - 3 \right) x \amp = - \cos(2) - 5 \amp \amp \text{Factor out the $x$} \\
						x \amp = \frac{ - \cos(2) - 5}{\sin(1) - 3} \amp \amp \text{Divide by $\sin(1) - 3$} 
					\end{aligned}
				</me>
			</p>
		</solution>
	</activity>
	<activity xml:id="sec-rme-1-ac3-solve-expression">
		<title>Solving for an Expression</title>
		<p>
			When we solve equations, sometimes we're not solving for the variable, but some expression involving the
			variable. This is often the case when the variable is wrapped up in a function. The same type of process can
			be done by making a substitution similar to the ones above. It is important to remember to substitute back
			to the original variable if you do this. 
			<me>
				\begin{aligned}
					2 \sin(x) + \sqrt{2} \amp = 0 \\
					2 y + \sqrt{2} \amp = 0 \amp \eqnspacer \amp \text{Substitute $y = \sin(x)$} \\
					2 y \amp = -\sqrt{2} \amp \amp \text{Subtract $\sqrt{2}$ from both sides} \\
					y \amp = - \frac{\sqrt{2}}{2} \amp \amp \text{Divide both sides by $2$} \\
					\sin(x) \amp = - \frac{\sqrt{2}}{2} \amp \amp \text{Substitute back to the original variable} 
				\end{aligned}
			</me>
		</p>
		<aside>
			<p>
				This last step is easily forgotten. 
			</p>
		</aside>
		<p>
			<alert xml:id="sec-rme-1-ac3-ti">Try it!</alert>
		</p>
		<p>
			Solve the equation <m>4 \exp(x) + 6 = \ln(4)</m> for Do it once using a substitution similar to the example
			above, and then do it without that substitution. Use a complete presentation both times. 
		</p>
		<solution>
			<p>
				<me>
					\begin{aligned}
						4 \exp(x) + 6 \amp = \ln(4) \\
						4 y + 6 \amp = \ln(4) \amp \amp \text{Substitute $y = \exp(x)$} \\
						4 y \amp = \ln(4) - 6 \amp \amp \text{Subtract $6$ from both sides} \\
						y \amp = \frac{\ln(4) - 6}{4} \amp \amp \text{Divide both sides by $4$} \\
						\exp(x) \amp = \frac{\ln(4) - 6}{4} \amp \amp \text{Substitute back to the original variable} \\
					\end{aligned}
				</me>
			</p>
			<p>
				<me>
					\begin{aligned}
						4 \exp(x) + 6 \amp = \ln(4) \\
						4 \exp(x) \amp = \ln(4) - 6 \amp \amp \text{Subtract $6$ from both sides} \\
						\exp(x) \amp = \frac{\ln(4) - 6}{4} \amp \amp \text{Divide both sides by $4$} 
					\end{aligned}
				</me>
			</p>
		</solution>
	</activity>
</section>
